Welcome to measure theory! This is part 1 of a
series where I want to give you an introduction
into measures and integrals  and where we will
prove some interesting results, in the end, which
are used very often in mathematical topics.
The motivation is indeed the famous Lebesgue
integral. And to define the Lebesgue integral, we
need a meaningful notion of a measure. So let's
start here with the real line. Now we can look at
subsets on the real line and ask how to measure
this subset. Or in other words what is the measure
of this subset? And this is what Measure Theory is
about: we want to give the subsets a meaningful
measure or, in other words, a generalized volume.
Or, in this case of the real line, a generalized
length. The notion of length is what you know
from the real line if you look at intervals.
If you have an interval in the real line from a to b,
(you would write it as a to b, and the whole subset
is this), then you would say this has a length of
b minus a. The natural question is now: what do we do
if the subset looks more complicated than such an
easy interval? How can we then calculate the length?
There immediately, the Measure Theory comes in.
And maybe we also want to deal with different
notion of lengths. So we want to generalize this
natural length. So maybe depending on the problem,
we want to choose different lengths or different
definitions of the length, so giving some weights
at different parts to make our problem easier.
Here you immediately see, the real line
gives us a lot of motivation why you want to
measure subsets of the real line. But obviously, we
don't want to stop there, we also want to measure
areas, so in R^2, or even higher dimensional volumes,
for example, normal volumes in three dimensions, and
so on. So therefore it makes sense to immediately
start an abstract measure theory, which now means we
just look at an abstract set, and we call it just
X. So X is just set. And for the set, we want to
measure the volume, the generalized volume, of the
subsets. So we will define a map which we will
call later just a "measure". Of course, this map
should fulfill some rules but I will talk about
this later. First let us start on the set level.
Because we want to measure the subsets of X, it's
good to start with the power set of X.
The power set is just the set of all subsets of X.
And to give you a short reminder, let's do an example.
If we have the set with two elements (so let's call
the elements just lowercase a and b), then we can
write down the power set. The empty set is always
a subset of the set so, we always have the empty
set in the power set. And the set itself is also
a trivial subset. So X is in the power set. Now we
have only two elements in the set. So we can't form so
many subsets, so the only possible way would be:
okay choose one element, so a, and form a subset,
and choose the other one. And in fact, these are
all the subsets, so we now have defined the whole
power set. So this is what you have to know.
You have to know how to form subsets of a given set.
And now we can give the definition for measurable
sets. When I say "measurable set", you may recognize
immediately the idea that, maybe, we don't have to
measure all the subsets we can form but only some.
If we have quite an amount of subsets we can and
want to measure, maybe that's good enough for our
theory. And therefore we call such sets "measurable".
We will later see that we indeed have to do that
because if we want to generalize even this easy
measure, given by the length, to all the subsets,
it's not possible. Yeah, it's only possible if we
choose good sets as subsets. For these sets,
we can generalize this length in a meaningful way.
In the sense, we now look at a subset of the power
set. So we look at a family of subsets that could
be the whole power set (so there could be equality here)
but, in general, we would have a smaller
family of such subsets of X. So keep in mind
this fancy A has as elements subsets of X. And
such a collection is called a "Sigma algebra"
if it fulfills the following rules. And these
will be three rules. Please keep in mind that
this notion of a Sigma algebra is indeed the
important definition in the whole measure theory.
and therefore we start with this here.
The elements in the Sigma algebra will be called the "measurable sets".
So these are the sets we can measure in the
end. Therefore, we immediately have the first rule
here because we want to measure the easiest sets,
which will be the empty set (also here in the
power set given) and the whole set itself. So we
want these two sets as elements in our Sigma algebra
because we want these sets to be measurable.
In the same sense, we get out the next rule:
So what happens if we know we can measure a set A?
So A in this curly A. Then we want to be able
to also measure the complement of the set.
And I denote the complement by A^c, so A^c means X without  A itself.
So this should also be a measurable set,
so in the Sigma algebra A. To visualize this maybe
a short sketch. So we have here an arbitrary set X
and inside also some subset A. Measurable now means
we know we can give a sensible generalized volume
to the set A. If we know this generalized volume, we
should also know the generalized volume outside.
But this means, the complement so A^c should also
be a measurable set. Therefore this rule (b) totally
makes sense. This is what we naturally need.
In the same sense, the third tool comes in.
One could say that this third rule comes in from a
measure process point of view. And it also gives the "Sigma" in the Sigma algebra a meaning. However, maybe,
I first tell you what the rule says and then we can
discuss where it comes from. So we start here with
countably many subsets, which means we have A_i
where the index i goes through all natural numbers.
We could repeat the same set here, so
then we only have finitely many subsets chosen,
but the important thing is, if we have infinitely
many, they are countable. Then we can look at the
union of all the sets. So I can write the union
symbol going from 1 to infinity. This defines us
again a subset of X. And the claim is now: this
is also in our Sigma algebra. This means that we
can't leave the Sigma algebra by using the normal
union, so union of two sets and even not if we use
a countable union of infinitely many sets. Maybe
we visualize that again in a short picture. This
is again our set X and we have a subset A inside.
Now assume we have measurable sets inside (so given
as these squares or rectangles, so this would be A_1 and then we have here A_2 and so on). The idea
would be now that we can form the set A out of
a countable union of the smaller sets A_i. If the
blue sets are measurable, which means they have
generalized volume, then the generalized volume
of A should be the limit of the sum of all these
generalized volumes. Or speaking of areas: if you
add up all the areas inside we can form, then you
should get out the area of A. And in order to speak
of an area or a generalized volume of A, we need that the
set A is measurable. So it should be an element in
a Sigma algebra. So this countable union should
also be an element in a Sigma algebra. And these
are all the rules. All systems of subsets with
these three rules now are called Sigma algebras.
To close the definition I now write down
what I told you the whole time: An element in
the Sigma algebra is called a measurable set.
So "Sigma algebra" and "measurable" are important
notions in this Measure Theory, here. "Measurable"
is given with respect to a given Sigma algebra,
therefore sometimes also A is in the definition
of "measurable" so it's called "A-measurable" if we
should emphasize which Sigma algebra is used here.
So now, of course, we need some examples.
We know that a Sigma algebra needs at least two
elements, namely the empty set and set X itself.
And this is always smallest possible Sigma
algebra. So A defined with these two elements
is a Sigma algebra because (b) and (c) in the rules
are trivially fulfilled. The complements are in
and also all possible unions you can form with
these two elements are also in. Hence, this is the
smallest possible Sigma algebra. The question is
now what is the largest one but this is also easy
to see because the power set itself fulfills, also trivially,
all these rules. Because by definition,
all possible subsets are immediately in the
powerset. So you can't leave it with the complements,
and also not with the unions. No matter if they
countable and uncountable. Therefore this would
be the best case scenario that we can measure all
possible subsets. However I already told you for
important examples we can't fulfill this. And
therefore our sigma-algebra will lie between
these two extrema. Of course, it would be nice
to have a lot of measurable sets therefore the
rule would be to get as close as possible to the
second case, to the power set. But this is what we
will do in later videos here in this series. So
maybe that's good enough for the introduction here.
Now you know what a sigma algebra is.
And next time we will talk more about measures and
define what a measure is. Therefore thank you
very much for listening and see you next time.