Hello and welcome back to measure theory. This
is part 3 and today we will finally start talking
about what measure is. I will start talking
about the definition and then I explain you
all the details. Afterwards then I can show you
some examples for measures. To summarize in this
video the question would be: what is a measure?
To answer this question let's immediately start
with the definition. What we need is a set X and
a sigma-algebra on the set X and let's call this
Sigma Algebra just A. And such a pair is then just
called a measurable space. So nothing special,
it just means you have a set X and you fixed one
Sigma algebra on this set. And by now you know
that a sigma algebra is a special collection of
subsets of this set X. Now we will look at special
maps that are defined on the Sigma algebra A. And
such map I will always call by our lowercase mu.
So it's defined on the Sigma A and maps into
the positive real numbers. However we include
some small detail: on the one side we include 0,
so 0 is allowed, and then we go to infinity, so
this would be our normal interval: so we just look
at a positive real line including 0. But here in
the measure theory, we will change this a little
bit we also include infinity. OK, this might look
a little bit strange, and it is, because we just
include one new symbol, so this means, we have our
positive real line where we include the 0, so this
is normal, but we also include a new symbol and we
just call this symbol infinity. And to shorten
this notation, we just write here also infinity
is included in the interval. This means that it is
just a short notation for saying that we have also
a symbol infinity involved. How to calculate with
this new symbol, I tell you later. First I want to
tell you how such a map is now called. Maybe not
so surprising such a map is now called a measure.
However only if the following two conditions are
fulfilled. To see what these two rules should be,
maybe recall what we want. We want to measure
subsets of this set X, which means we want to
give a volume to such a subset. So a generalized
length or generalized volume. Therefore makes
totally sense to restrict ourselves to the
positive real numbers where we also include zero
and the symbol infinity; which means we could also
have a volume of zero and maybe also an infinite
volume. But all other volumes should be positive
numbers. From this, we immediately get our first
property because we know that the empty set is a
subset of X and in all Sigma algebras A involved.
Therefore we want to measure this empty set or we
want to give it a volume. But the only sensible
volume we can give the empty set would be zero.
If there are no elements involved, the generalized
volume should be zero. Okay for the start not so
complicated so let's go to our second property,
this property should fix the idea that we can
add up volumes. Or in other words, if we have
a subset given (so maybe just in this rectangle),
then we could split it up into subsets (so maybe
in this way maybe here line and here line). So I
would call this A1, this is A2, this A3, A4, and
A5. Now if we add up all these separate volumes,
we should end at our original volume. And this
is the condition I can write down. So adding up
all the volumes where we start with i equals to 1
and we'll end with five, or we just write an N in
this generality. So we're adding up the volumes,
which means I add up mu of A_i. And we also
know, we chose the sets to be disjoint, pairwise
disjoint, because we want a decomposition of our
original set. Pairwise disjoint means now that
A_i intersected with A_j is the empty set if the
indices do not coincide. So i is not equal to j.
Now you see something's missing in our condition
but we can fix that immediately because we know
this should be the original volume. So I can write
this as the volume of the union of all these sets.
So I write here i equals to one going to N and
here I have my A_i. This is the union that gives
us indeed our original green set here. And this
condition should be satisfied no matter which
sets we chose. So I just write this should hold
for all A_i out of our Sigma algebra. And this
property is what one calls just additive. It tells
you that if you have a finite union, you can split
that up into a finite sum of the volumes. However
I should tell you, this is not the full story. We
also want to include the intuition that we can
also approximate volumes. Maybe I explain it
again in the picture. So if you want to calculate
the volume of this rectangle, we can split it up
again into subsets so this is my set A_1. Then I
also choose an A_2 here and A_3 here and then I go
on and on. So this would be my A_4 and A_5 and
you see I get smaller and smaller. But you see
I get again the decomposition of my original set
into disjoint subsets. However, I have infinitely
many subsets now. But they are countable, which
means I have a sequence of subsets. Now you know,
I can still form the union of all the subsets to
get out my original set. Which means I put in here
an infinity symbol to denote this union. And if
I add up the infinitely many unions, I should
also get out the original volume. So instead of
a finite sum, I have now a series here; but it's
the series of non-negative numbers. Therefore to
denote this countable infinite additive rule, we
usually call it sigma additive. And please recall
we had the same idea in the definition of the
Sigma algebra: we want this union, this countable
infinity union, also be in the Sigma algebra. And
therefore this is also well-defined because if we
choose elements from the Sigma algebra, we know
that this countable union is also in a sigma
algebra. Therefore we can calculate mu of this
one. And now we have it this is the definition
of a measure. Maybe let's summarize that:
a measure has to live on a Sigma algebra. It does
not have to be the whole power set (it could be),
but in general we will see we can't do it for
the whole power set. This just means that we
want to measure some meaningful subsets from our
set X. Measuring subsets now means giving them
a generalized volume, so it makes sense to give
them a volume in the non-negative numbers where
we also include a symbol infinity. And then the
two properties generalize the ideas from a volume
measure. The first thing tells you nothing should
have a zero volume and the second tells you that
you can calculate the volume by splitting it up
into countable many subsets. Now let's assume you
have a measure chosen, then we can also fix that
in our informations here. You would write X with
the Sigma algebra A and with our measure on the
Sigma algebra A: mu. And this is what we call a
measure space. This is of course a very important
notion because the measure space is the space we
work in. Very good. Now you learned what such
a general measure space is. And now we can talk
about some simple examples. Let us fix for all
the examples, an arbitrary set X and also a Sigma
algebra on the set X. And maybe we start with the
best case scenario that we can choose the whole
power set for the Sigma algebra. The first measure
is very important and very easy, it's called the
counting measure. No matter what set X is, you
can always define this counting measure. Simply
by setting that the measure of an arbitrary subset
a is defined in the following way and I consider
two cases here. The first case would be that A
has only finitely many elements. In this case,
I want the measure to be this number, so I can
just write down the number of elements just by the
number symbol. So this is a well-defined natural
number or zero. So we don't have a problem,
defining exactly this. Okay for the other case,
I set it to infinity. Which means if A has not
finitely many elements, I say it has infinitely
many elements. There you see: it makes sense to
use our symbol infinity. What you can now show is
that this defines really a measure, so it fulfills
these two rules. So that the empty set gets sent
to zero is immediately clear because the empty
set has finitely many elements and the number of
elements is zero. So no problem there and also
the Sigma additivity, you can easily show if you
just deal with finite sets. If you deal with the
infinite sets, it's also easy to show but then you
need to know what are the calculations rules when
I deal with this infinity symbol. And this is
what I now want to show you. So just the basic
calculation rules. The idea is of course thinking
in the volumes. So if you have one volume x,
and then you add up an infinite volume (so you add
up infinity), you also should get out to infinity
again. And this should hold for all x in our set.
So also for the symbol infinity. Or other words
infinity plus infinity is always infinity. In the
same way we can do this for the multiplication:
so x times infinity should be also defined as
infinity. However now be careful, I want to
exclude 0 now. So if I multiply a positive number
with infinity, we get out to infinity again, but
not for 0. For the special case 0 times infinity,
there are different conventions. In general, you
would just say this is undefined because it could
mean anything. However in most cases in measure
theory, it's also nice to have a definition
for this combination of the symbols, and we
set it to 0. However keep in mind, this is not
always applicable and, outside of measure theory,
it could be completely wrong. Often this occurs
if we want to multiply two volumes. Then let's
go to the next example and this one is called the
Dirac measure. Maybe for this one visualize your
set X here where we choose one fixed point, so we
choose here maybe a point p inside X. And now we
just want that the whole measure is concentrated
in only this point. The usual notation one chooses
for this measure is a delta where we have an index
p to denote the point. Now for a given subset A,
we also define it with two cases. It is either 1
or 0. The idea we could also sketch in our drawing
here. So if this is our set A, we see that p is
inside the set A. And if we want to volume to be
concentrate at the point p, we now would say: okay
this set has measure 1. So it doesn't matter how
small the set is. As long as the special point
p is inside, it has measure 1. But if P is not
inside the set, then it has measure 0. A good
visualization would be to think of this point as
a point charge. The whole charge is in the point
but if you look at the surrounding you would give
also the surrounding exactly this charge. Okay so
these were two measures that work on every set X,
so in particular also for our special case R^n.
Or in other words these measures don't measure
the normal volume you, for example, have in R^3.
They are indeed generalized measures. But we know
we also want to have this normal volume measure in
R^n. Therefore the exercise for measure theory is
in particular to find a measure on X equal to R^n
that has some nice properties. The first property
would fix that it measures the normal volume.
This means that if I put in the unit cube in
the measure, which is a cube that has length 1 in
all directions, then I want to get out the volume
1 as well. And the second property means it does
not matter where we measure the volume in space.
In other words, the measure is invariant under
translations. So I can write that as x plus our
set A is equal to the volume of the set A. And
this holds for all translation vectors x in R^n.
Also visualize always this property in a short
picture. If you have your volume here so maybe
this might be the set A. And now I translate all
the points with a fixed vector x. Then I find the
new set x plus A here. So this is my set x plus A.
And of course this should have the same volume in
our surrounding space. Of course this is not true
for an abstract generalized measure from before.
But it should be true for our measure that we
want to find that generalizes the normal volume
measure in R^n. However keep in mind: we only know
how to measure such cubes or cuboids and not how
to measure such an arbitrary subset. And that's
the idea that we want to extend this notion and
still conserve these two properties. Later we will
see that we can indeed define a measure with this
two properties and that is what we then call the
Lebesgue measure. And in the next video you will
see that we can't choose the whole power set as
a sigma-algebra. We have to choose a smaller one
such that we can conserve these two properties.
And there you will see that we can easily work in
the Borel sigma-algebra. Well very good. That's
all I wanted to tell you today and I hope that
helped you a little bit. For the next videos,
the real measure theory can start because now we
have the notion what a measure and a measure space
is. So thank you very much and see you next time!