Hello and welcome back
to measure theory.
This is part four in our
series.
And today I will finally
explain you why we can't
define the Lebesgue measure
on the whole power set.
And this should give you
at least one motivation.
Why it's so important to
study the measure theory
for a start here.
Let me state the measure
problem again,
we search and measure mu
on the power set of
R. So as you can see
this is the one dimensional
case.
So we first deal with the
real number line.
Before we go to higher dimensions,
we call this the measure
problem because we want
now two natural
properties that are fulfilled
by this measure mu
first, the measure of a
normal interval
should be just the length
of this interval.
Hence just b
minus a where I say
that b is of course larger
than a.
Of course, this is what we
want.
We want to generalize
the measuring of lengths.
And now the second natural
property is that we have
some, we call translation
invariance.
This means that if we have
a set A and shift that
by a fixed vector X,
we don't change the length
or the measure of the set.
This means that we get out
mu of a on
the right hand side here
and there you have it.
That is what we call our
measure problem.
And such a measure mu
would truly
generalize the length
measure of intervals.
However, for more than 100
years, it is known that
this measure problem is not
solvable.
So we can't define such a
measure mu on the whole
power set on R.
Therefore, it makes sense
to build the whole measure
theory with Sigma algebras.
In the end, we will see that
we can choose a suitable
Sigma algebra where we indeed
can solve this measure problem.
However, in this video, I
start by proving
that the measure problem
on the power set does not
have a solution.
The claim I will prove now
is the following.
Let mu be a measure on the
power set with the property
one and two, but I will
weaken the property
one a little bit.
I just want that the
measure of the unit
interval is finite.
So not infinity.
This is of course fulfilled
when property one is
fulfilled.
And why I excluded
zero in this interval here
you will see later.
In addition, mu should now
also fulfill property
two, which means it is
translation invariant.
The result is now that there
is only one measure that
satisfies this
and this is the
zero measure.
And of course, the trivial
measure is not what we want.
The trivial measure does
not fulfill poverty one in
our measure problem.
So this explains this
implication here.
The whole video is now about
proving this claim.
And indeed, this is a typical
exercise you find in
measure theory lectures.
Therefore, I strongly advise
you to try for
yourself and then maybe
fill in the details by
using this video.
And of course, if you're
not interested in technical
details, you can happily
skip this video and go to
the next one in the series
for everyone else.
Now comes the proof,
I will structure it a little
bit.
So I start with a, by
giving some definitions,
we will study the interval
where we know that the measure
is finite.
So this is what I call
capital I,
which means the unit interval
where I exclude the zero
and include the one.
And on I, I now
define an equivalence
relation.
And this equivalent equivalence
should ignore rational
numbers inside the interval
which means I
define X and
Y as equivalent
if and only if the
following holds
the difference between both
of them is only a rational
number.
So X minus
Y is in
Q,
this means that we don't
want to distinguish
numbers that only differ
by a rational number.
We want to deal with these
numbers as the same.
Therefore, the equivalence
class of such an X can
be written as X
plus.
All rational numbers
are.
So we put all these numbers
in one box and call it
the X with the brackets.
However, keep in mind, we
define the equivalence relation
on our set.
I, so now we just
live on the unit interval.
Therefore, these numbers
should also live on the unit
interval.
Therefore, I have to add
here that also X
plus R lies
still in the unit level.
So I can't add a
big rational numbers because
then I would leave the unit
level.
Otherwise now we hit
all the numbers we want
there.
We have the well-defined
equivalence relation with
the well-defined equivalence
classes to give
some visualization.
I may draw these boxes
for real.
They are sets, sets with
elements.
So I could call this
X one and I have
one box here,
then I have another one.
So this would be X two,
X three and X
four.
And of course, this picture
goes on for
forever.
We don't know if we have
countable many boxes as the
picture suggests here.
So please be careful.
But we know that we have
a disjoint decomposition
of the unit interval.
This is what we always have
if we define an
equivalence relation.
Now we already reached the
essential part of the
proof because we
define a set
A in
I that describes
all these boxes
that means each element
A describes or
represents exactly
one of these boxes.
And this picture would look
like OK, I choose
one element here.
Maybe I call this a one,
then I go to the next box,
I pick an element A two.
Here I pick out an element
A three here, a
four and so on.
And then I put all
these elements in a
set and this is
what I call the set
A,
this looks nice now.
But keep in mind if we have
uncountable many boxes,
this picture is not the
correct way to represent
this.
And therefore we need another
definition for set A.
But of course, with exactly
the same idea behind
the first property is therefore
for each box.
So for each equivalence class
X, I find such an
a in A,
this just means picking
out an element A out
of the box.
And then the second property
should tell us that this
element is unique.
So I only choose one
element of each box.
So for all A B and
A, we have the
property that A
and B come out of the
same box X,
we can imply
that A is equal
to B.
Hence the definition tells
us that the set A
has exactly one
representative out of
each box.
The equivalence classes are
therefore exactly
represented by the set
A.
However, it's not clear how
to do this representation.
You don't find a
construction how we can
find the set A.
It looks very nice in the
picture.
And there you might see we
have a lot of possibilities
to define such a set A
But keep in mind if we are
in the uncountable picture,
we might not know if such
a set A could
exist.
And indeed, this justification
is very strong here.
What we need here is indeed
the axiom of choice
that is given in the set
theory.
Therefore, it's an axiom
that guarantees the
existence of such a set A
with exactly these two
properties.
OK.
That was a lot.
But we are still not finished
with all the definitions
I want to give.
Now we have fixed the set
A and now I want to shift
it a little bit.
So I translated by a
rational number.
So this is what I define
as A N.
So this would be
RN plus the
set A and
RN is a rational number.
More concretely, I want a
sequence RN.
So this goes over the natural
numbers that
enumerate the whole rational
numbers.
That's not completely correct.
I just want an
enumeration of rational
numbers intersected
with the real
interval minus one
till one.
And of course, why I want
that you will see later.
However, you should see that
we can use that the rational
numbers accountable when
we want to apply the sigma
additivity later.
And now we can finally go
over to part B of
my proof.
First, we show here that
the sets are here defined
are indeed disjoint.
So we have a
intersected with
AM and this gives
you the empty set
if N is
not equal to M,
the proof works easily
by contraposition.
This means you could read
this one here as an
implication.
So if N is
unequal M, this
implies that
this sets are disjoint.
Now contraposition now
means OK, they are not disjoint
and this implies
N equals M.
So this is logically
equivalent,
however, not being disjoint
means there is an element
we can choose out of this
intersection.
So that's what we do.
And this implies
immediately to properties
being in A N means
I can write X
as rn
plus some, well, the
lower case a in A so
I have an A here or
being in A_m means I
can write it as
r_m
plus some a.
But of course, these could
be two different A's.
So I also give you an
index to say
this, OK.
But of course, the X is the
same on the left.
So I can equal them.
This means that I have
RN plus A
N equals two,
two RM
plus AM.
And there you see what I
can do is put all
the A's on the one side and
all the RS on the other side.
And now on the right, we
subtract two rational numbers.
So you know what comes out
is also a rational number.
Now remind yourself that
we defined an equivalence
relation exactly
when the difference of two
numbers is a rational number.
So in other words, a_n and
a_m are now
equivalent or
to put this.
In other words, we could
also say our A
N is in the
equivalence class
represented by
AM.
If you want, you could also
now add AM
here as well.
So of course, am is also
in the equivalence class
here.
And then you see we have
property two for
set A and it tells
you if two elements come
out of the same box or the
same equivalence class, they
have to be the same.
So the conclusion here is
a_n is equal
to a_m.
OK.
So this tells us the left
hand side here is zero,
but then also the right hand
side is zero.
And therefore, we can again
imply that
also the rational numbers
here are the same.
So RN is equal
to RM but
the R MS were chosen
as an enumeration of the
rational numbers.
And therefore here also
the indices have to
coincide
and this proves now the claim
by contraposition
very good.
Now I want to go over to
the next part.
In part C I want to look
at the union of
these disjoint
sets.
So I have
union n
over N,
OK.
Now keep in mind what the
definition of A was that
was defined by our set
A that lives in the unit
interval, shifted by
rational numbers that live
in minus 1 to 1.
This means by using the
union, I still should not
be able to leave the
interval.
That is given by minus
one and now I
shift one with
maximum one.
So here I have two.
And on the other side, you
can use how we
defined a.
So this was
representation of all the
equivalence classes and where
the equivalence classes were
defined by the
differences with the rational
numbers.
And now I add
back all the rational numbers.
So I should
get at least the unit interval
out again.
OK.
So this one is to claim
we should prove here in part
C.
However, I already
told you most of the things
you need.
Therefore, I think it's not
hard for you to do the proof
for yourself.
So the proof is an
exercise for you just
put all the ideas I gave
you now into formulas,
OK?
With all these parts in mind,
I can now go to the core
of the proof, we
now assume
that we have a measure on
the whole power set of the
real line.
And it also should fulfill
the two properties we have
given in the claim.
And now we can use all the
things above, for example,
by our translation
invariance (2), we
can write that
the measure
of a
ARN plus
A is the same as the
measure of
A.
And this holds for all
natural numbers N.
And maybe let us, you see
here immediately, we know
that the measure is always
monotonic, which
means the measure of
this set is less or
equal than the measure of
this set.
And this is less or equal
than the measure of this
set.
So we have exactly this
inequality here.
We need it later again.
So I call the inequality
here by star.
Before we go further, let
us use now our second
condition here that the
measure of the unit interval
is at least finite.
Let us give this number a
name.
So I write the measure of
equals to
number and I call it just
capital C.
With this, we can indeed
calculate the measure here.
We can use the properties
of a measure namely the
Sigma Additivity.
So I split the set
into unit
intervals or shifted unit
intervals.
Here I go to zero and include
it.
And then I have a disjoint
unit when I exclude
the zero here and go
to one
included here
again, union
one and he had
two.
OK.
And here we can now use the
Sigma additivity.
Now you can write this as
measure of this set plus
measure of this set.
And by using the
translation invariance in
two, you know all this
measure have the same value
namely C
hence we have C plus C
plus C.
So we
c
OK.
Very good.
Now, I want to use this in
the quality I called star
before.
So this one, what
you should see immediately
now is that on the left we
have C itself but on the
right we now calculate three
C.
So let us write it down.
So I have C less so
equal then.
And now I can use the Sigma
additivity as always
because this one is
disjoint.
Now this was part B
from before.
So I have now here the
sum or the series
from one to
infinity
of mu of
A N and this is
less for equal than three
times C.
And now we also know that
we can get rid of the
N here because
here you see it, this is
a N.
So the translated
version of A but by
translation invariance, we
know the measure is the same.
So we can write mu
of A on this case.
And I want to write that
down as the important
inequality here.
So C less or
equal the series of
MU A and less or equal than
three C.
So please look
closely at this
inequality.
You see a fixed number
mu of A in the middle and
then the series
then you know the series
will explode, it gives you
infinity if
mu of A is greater than
zero.
So the only possible
case when this is finite
needs mu of A
equals to zero.
And this is the case because
we know that C is
less than infinity.
So the series has to be
convergent by
this calculation, we now
can conclude that the measure
of our set A has to be
zero.
However, this means now the
value of the series is
zero.
So we have zero in the middle
and left and right, we have
C and three C.
So there's also no other
possible way other
than C to be
zero.
However, remind yourself
that C was just a short
notation for the measure
of the unit interval.
Hence, this measure
is also just
zero.
And indeed, this helps us
now calculating the
measure of the whole real
line just
because I have translation
invariance and sigma
additivity.
So we split the real
line into unit
intervals and shift them.
So what we can do is
just use an interval
starting with an integer
M and then go to M
plus one.
And if I use the union here,
which is then the disjoint
union where M goes over
all integers, I
have what I want.
Now I use Sigma additivity
and then translation variances
and then I get also
out adding up zero
stays at zero.
This now means that the
volume or length of the
whole line measured in mu
is just zero.
So we are dealing with the
real measure this zero measure.
And in fact, this is what
we wanted to prove.
And there we have it the
full proof how to
see that the measure
problem is not
solvable.
I know it was a long
proof with a lot of technical
details, but I hope you learn
something here
and maybe I should close
this proof with some
interpretation of the whole
thing you saw
that it is possible to
construct such a set
a where we
can't have a reasonable
length or measure,
we would get contradictions
if we're not dealing with
the trivial zero measure.
So the only possibility
to deal with such
sets that behave so
strangely that we can't measure
them is to exclude them
from the beginning.
We won't measure all
possible subsets.
We just deal with sets, we
then call the measurable
sets.
Now these are the sets that
behave nicely
enough such that we
can solve the measure
problem in this so
called Sigma algebra then .
In fact, the Borel Sigma
algebra you learned in
part two of the series about
is a correct choice to
solve the measure problem.
We will go into details
about this in the future.
But first in the next videos,
I want to talk about
maps that preserve
our measurable structure
here.
So these are so called
measurable maps.
OK.
Then see you in the next
video.
Bye.