Hello and welcome back to
measure theory.
We have reached part 5
in our series.
And today I want to talk
about measurable
maps.
Now let us immediately
start with the definition.
Of course, we will talk about
the usual map between
two sets.
Let us denote the map by
F and the two sets by
Omega_1 and Omega_2.
In addition, both sets
should also comprise a Sigma
algebra respectively.
So let me denote the first
Sigma algebra by A_1
and the
second by A_2.
By now, you know that such
a pair consisting of a
set with a corresponding
Sigma algebra is called a
measurable space.
And you also know that we
need such a measurable
space to define a
measure on it.
However, please note that
we don't need a measure here.
We just need the sets
and the Sigma algebras, nothing
else.
Now f is called
measurable
if the following
holds the
preimage of a
set coming
from the Sigma algebra
A_2.
So A_2 is an
element in
A_2,
is an element
in the sigma algebra
A_1.
And this holds for all
sets from the Sigma
algebra A_2.
If you remember that we also
call elements from a sigma
algebra just
measurable, then we can
say a map is
called measurable,
if the preimages of
measurable sets is again
measurable.
And of course, this could
be confusing if there are
a lot of different sigma
algebras involved.
Therefore, we would also
include the sigma
algebras in the
definition of
measurable.
So the map f is here
measurable with
respect to the two sigma
algebras.
OK.
So this concept seems
meaningful because it connects
the two sigma algebra here in
the definition.
However, of course, you can
ask why do we need
this?
And why do we need this
exactly in this fashion
with the preimages?
We can easily explain that
when we recall why we
do measure theory
and how we could define
an integral in the end.
Therefore, let us look at
an easy function like from
school, so a one dimensional
function where you can draw
the graph.
OK.
So here the function has
the value zero.
And here I set the value
one.
Now the integral of this
function should be exactly
the volume of the
set that is sent to one.
So you could imagine that
in this way,
there's the set and this
is what we want to measure
in our measure.
So this set here on the
x-axis is the
preimage of the value
1.
So exactly this
set here
and what we need and have
for the x-axis is just a
measure space.
So set
Sigma algebra and
a measure  mu.
So an abstract measure space
is enough.
And then we can measure
the volume of this set here.
Hence, for a meaningful
integral, we want
to measure sets of
this form.
However, the measure mu is
only defined on the Sigma
algebra.
So what we really need
is that this one is an
element in the Sigma algebra
on Omega.
So which is here our
A
and there you see why we
need the preimage in the
definition, we want to
guarantee that if we have
a measurable set on the
y-axis, we also
get a measurable set
on the x-axis
and the set on the x-axis
we get with the preimage.
And that is what we want
to put in the measure in
the end or to say it
in a few words, the
definition of measurable
maps solves a
problem that will come
later.
OK.
Then let's talk about a
few examples
now. Then let us
start with an
abstract measurable
space.
So Omega,
A and
also the
real number line
with the Borel Sigma
algebra.
Now one can look at the
common characteristic
function. Sometimes
also called the indicator
function.
And I will always
use the greek letter Chi
to denote this
characteristic function.
Namely Chi with an
index A, where A is
just a set in Omega.
So the map goes from Omega
to the real numbers
and is defined by the
following two cases.
By the way, I rather should
use a lower case omega
to denote the variable here.
So the two cases then are
one or zero depending
if our lower case omega
comes from A
or not.
So omega in A is
one and omega
not in A
is zero
from this, we can now
conclude that for
all measurable
sets, which means
A in our Sigma algebra
A, the
characteristic function Chi_A
is a
measurable
map.
In order to prove this, we
just have to look at all
the preimages.
And because we only have
two values for the function,
there are not so many
preimages we could have.
For example, if you look
at the preimage of the
empty set and then of
course, you get out the empty
set and
the other trivial case
would be looking what the
preimage of the whole real
number line is and of
course, what you get out
is what you put in.
So the preimage is
here Omega itself,
of course, this is what we
have for all maps of this
form.
So let us look at more
interesting cases.
So the preimage
of for
example, the set that contains
only one
and there we know the
whole set A
is sent to one.
So the preimage here is
exactly A.
On the other hand, if we
look at the preimage of
the set that only contains
zero, then we get
out everything
else.
So not A. Which means
this is the complement of
A.
And in fact, these are all
the preimages we can get
out.
So if you choose another
set here you get one of
these four sets.
And important to note here
is of course, yeah,
empty set, omega
are in the sigma algebra.
And by assumption our A is
also the Sigma algebra.
But then by the definition
of the Sigma algebra, we
also know that the
complement is also the Sigma
algebra.
And please recall that is
exactly the definition of
a measurable map.
So you see a characteristic
or an indicator function
is a typical example of a
measurable map.
And indeed an important one,
because if you look at the
picture here again, these
are maps that we could
easily integrate if we have
a notion of integration.
So this is what we will do
in the next videos later.
However, here we should first
continue with the next
example.
Let us choose here three
measurable spaces.
We do this because I want
to look at compositions of
measurable maps.
In other words, we start
with the set Omega_1 go
in Omega_2
and then in Omega_3.
let us then call the map
here by f
and this one should be the
map g.
So and then we can do
the composition. Which
means a map going
from Omega_1
directly to
Omega_3.
And this is then defined
as g after
f.
So the composition of both
maps. The claim is
now, if we put in
two measurable maps,
then also the composition
is measurable.
So in short, this
implies g
after f
measurable.
Indeed, this is very easy
to see if you look again
at the preimages.
So the preimage of
g composed with f
of a set
coming from the Sigma
algebra A_3.
So let's call it A_3
is equal to
and now we can go
stepwise.
So we have
the preimage of g
first
of A_3.
So this step and then the
preimage of this.
So this equality holds for
all maps.
But now we can put in what
we know of f and
g. Maybe first we know
that g is measurable.
So we know this one is
an element in the Sigma
algebra A_2.
But now we know that f is
also measurable.
So we know that the whole
thing here now
lies in the Sigma algebra
A_1 or in other
words, does not matter
which element from the sigma
algebra A_3
you choose here the
preimage always lies in
the sigma algebra A_1.
And this is indeed what
measurable for maps
means.
Well, let's close this video
with some important facts
about measurable
functions.
And when I say function,
I just mean a map that
maps into the real number
line. This means
that we now have two
measurable spaces.
And one of them is just the
real number line with the
Borel Sigma algebra.
Now let us look at two maps.
So just functions.
Let's start with omega
and land in the real
number line.
And of course, they should
now be measurable
with respect to these two
Sigma algebras
because we have the whole
structure of the real
numbers, we can now
look at combinations of these
two functions.
For example, f +
g and f
- g again will
define functions.
And the result here is they
are still measurable
in the same manner.
We can look at the multiplication
of the two functions just
by multiplying the values
and defining the function.
So as always,
and this new function is
then again measurable
and also very important
if you ignore
negative values, so make
them positive.
So you get out the absolute
value as a function.
This one is also
measurable.
There are also other important
combinations one considers
and we will later see if
we need them.
However, the idea is always
the same.
So you can prove this in
general and use it the whole
time in measure theory.
OK.
I think that's good enough
for today.
So now you learned what a
measurable map is
and as I promised before,
you will need this definition
when we consider
integration theory.
And that is what you will
see in the next video
when we indeed start
with the Lebesgue integral
then see you next time
there.
Bye.