Hello and welcome
back.
First, let me thank all the
nice people that support
this channel on Steady.
And now let's continue with
measure theory namely
with part six.
And we will finally talk
about the Lebesgue integral but
first about the Lebesgue
integral of so
called-step functions.
So we will learn how to
integrate functions that
are defined on an
abstract measure space.
As a short recap, a
measure space is
nothing more than a
triple.
There.
We have a set X,
a sigma algebra A
and also a measure
mu.
This means that X could
be any set
but A is a special
collection of subsets of
X.
And the third ingredient,
the measure mu itself is
indeed a map
where the domain is the sigma
algebra A and the co-
domain is the
interval included
zero and also
included the symbol
infinity.
Now, with respect to
this abstract measure
space, we want to
integrate some special
functions.
Indeed what we need are
measurable maps defined in
the last video I
will use the letter F for
such maps that start
with X and go into
the real number line.
Now you should not forget
that we have a Sigma algebra
on the left namely
A and also a Sigma
algebra on the right.
And there we have the Borel
Sigma algebra.
Also recall
that measurable means
that all the preimages
from elements from the sigma
algebra here lie
in the sigma algebra A.
In other
words, preimage
of a set
E is in
A for all
Borel sets E
OK.
So these are the functions
where we want to be able
to integrate them in the
end.
However, at the moment,
they might be too complicated.
So we start with functions
that we already know.
For example, we already
know that the characteristic
function is a measurable
map.
If we choose a measurable
set,
this means A
lies in the Sigma algebra.
We already know how to sketch
this function.
If we have our abstract X
here on the line
and maybe this
is the set A.
So these two things together
are A, then we
can sketch the graph of
our characteristic function.
It will be zero here
and has to value you
one where the set A
lies.
So here it will be one and
here also zero
and there also zero
for visualization of the
integral, it's always
good to see the integral
as the area below
the graph
And the x axis
here, this would mean we
look at this area
here
and the area here.
And because the value of
the function is just one,
it does not matter how abstract
this whole measure space
is, this area should
be exactly the same as
the volume, the measure
of the set A
or in other words, a
meaningful integral
notion.
And maybe let's call it just
by capital I
of this characteristic
function should always
fulfill that.
This integral
is the measure of the
set A.
Now we have a new symbol
on the left I of a
function.
So you should read this indeed,
as a definition,
this means now you know
how to integrate characteristic
functions.
In fact, there are other
functions where we can
define the integral
also in such a simple
way.
And these are called simple
functions.
There are also a lot of other
names that one uses for such
simple functions.
For example, step
functions as I
did in the
title of this video
and also
staircase functions
and also other
names.
And you see the name
might not be important.
You just have to know what
such simple functions are.
In short.
A simple function F
is just a linear
combination of such
characteristic functions.
This means you can write
F of X as a
sum.
Where we will start with
one and go to a fixed
N and where we
have numbers C
I and
characteristic functions
corresponding to some
measurable set A
I.
In other words, a
function F is called
simple.
If you can find
measurable sets A_1
till A_n
and real numbers c_1
to c_n
such that you can write the
function in this form
because we know that the
characteristic functions
are measurable and also
sums of measurable
maps are also measurable.
We also know that this
simple function is
therefore
measurable.
Also here, I would
say to get some
visualization, let's
sketch the graph of such
a simple function.
This is the same as before.
So we have X here and
R here and
maybe here now we have set
A_1 and
here a set A_2
.
And let's choose a split
set A three here.
And for these sets, we can
now choose some
constant c_i.
Hence, we have for the graph
of the function some value
here over A_1,
another value over A_2
here.
And maybe a lower one
here for A_3
and outside of this set, we
are just at zero.
If we now go back to our
visualization of the
integral, we know it's given
by rectangles.
For example, here we have
the rectangle
with length given by a
one and the height
given by C one.
Therefore, this rectangle
here just
represents the part of the
integral that is given
by C one times the
measure of a one.
And the contribution for
the integral given by the
set A two is just
this rectangle here.
And of course, now given
by C two
times the measure
of A two.
And then the last part is
coming from a three which
consists of three parts.
But in the sum, of course,
this is also C
three times the
measure of a
three.
And now you should see that
we just have to add
up all these
contributions to get the
full integral, to get the
full area in this picture.
Hence, again, for
meaningful integral
definition, we need a sum
of all these parts.
So I of
F is then
given by a sum
and they have the same C
I as before, but
now not the characteristic
function but the
corresponding measures
of the sets.
And indeed, this will be
our integral for
simple functions in the end.
However, at the moment,
you should see immediately
one problem with this definition.
What happens if we have
a set with volume
infinity?
So that this number
here is the symbol
infinity.
There we could have for example,
three as the C
times infinity.
Maybe that's not a problem
for you because it's just
infinity itself again.
But then what happens if
the next C here is
minus two and it measures
also infinity.
And of course, this is not
simply just one infinity.
This is not defined at the
moment.
In fact, we have a
problem with the definition
in general.
In order to solve this problem,
there are essentially two
ways one can go.
Now on the one
hand, one can restrict
oneself to such simple
functions where the corresponding
AIS only have
finite measure.
Obviously, then there's no
problem with such infinities
because there is no simple
infinity involved in the
whole sum.
And on the other hand, one
can demand that these
constants have to be
positive, then there
might be infinity in the
sun, but only with the same
sign.
And then of course, we don't
have a problem adding up
positive infinities.
And exactly this second
possibility is the way
I want to go here.
Now, finally, we can put
the integral into a
definition
for this.
We will consider now, just
functions defined on X.
And as before, there should
be step or simple
functions.
Moreover, we want now to
consider only the positive
ones or more concretely
the non-negative ones.
The whole set of such
functions is now
denoted by a
curved S where I put
in A plus
and this S plus is now
almost a vector space
in the sense that we can
add functions as we want.
But we can't scale them as
we want because
only positive scalars are
allowed otherwise we would
leave this space.
So you should imagine
this as a half space.
If we go now back to our
definition of simple
functions, you
immediately recognize
that this representation
here is not unique for the
function F.
For example, we could split
the set A two into two
parts.
And then we have one
term in addition in
the sum here, but
it does not change the function
F itself.
So the graph looks still
the same just this
sum is different.
Therefore, another description
which is independent of this
representation for a simple
function would be
I have a measurable
function.
And it only takes
finitely many values.
In this case, I can always
find such a representation
here.
The idea is now
always choose a
suitable
representation for your
simple function F.
In our case here, if
F comes from our S
plus,
then choose a representation
as always.
So we can write it as a sum.
But now where the c_i's
are also non-
negative.
Of course, if the function
is non-negative, then we
can always choose such a
representation.
And now it's very easy
to define the Lebesgue integral.
So this is our new notion
and of course, often we will
ignore the Lebesgue and
just speak of the
integral because this is
the integral we define here.
And to be more concrete,
we also would say with
respect to our
given measure mu.
And this integral is now
given as we already
know.
And also denoted by
I of F where we
just add up
the measures of the
sets A I where we
scale them also by the
CIS.
So we have C I
times the measure
of A I.
And because the C I are
non-negative and the measure
itself is non-negative or
in the worst case just
infinity, we know this
integral is now also in the
interval zero
to infinity where we
include both parts.
One fact I can give you
immediately this definition
for integral is a
well-defined
object.
This means that it does not
depend on the chosen
representation for our simple
function F.
So if you choose another
representation with this
property, you get the same
number out, maybe
this is a thing you could
try to prove.
However, of course, the
visualization should be the
important thing.
So it does not matter how
you split up these
rectangles here.
Yeah, the sum or the sum
of the areas should be always
the same no
matter how you split up the
set here on the X axis or
you split up the C
values on the Y axis.
In other words, it makes
sense that this integral
here is indeed well-
defined.
And finally, I can give you
the usual notation one
uses for the integral,
of course, an integral sign,
we put the set X
here then comes the
function F and
then the measure mu
by d
mu
sometimes also a
variable is needed.
And the notation looks almost
the same.
So you just
include a variable
name for the function.
So a lower case X
here and then d mu
X.
So this is the Lebesgue integral
for step or
simple functions.
The idea is now that we
expand this definition
such that we can also
integrate more complicated
functions.
But before we do that, let's
first look at some properties
this integral has
firstly, it is
almost linear.
I already told you
we almost have vector
space for our S plus.
And in this sense, it's
linear, we
just have to restrict the
scalars to non-negative
numbers.
And then we can pull out
the addition sign.
And also the scalars,
hence this equality
holds for all simple
functions FG and
for all scalars
alpha beta greater
or equal to zero.
And of course, this immediately
comes from this sum here.
Also by using a, we
can now show that if we
have a step function or a
simple function that is always
bigger than another one,
so we have F less or
equal than G,
then also the area
between the graph
and the X axis should be
bigger for G than for F.
And of course, this is what
the integral tells us.
So I of F
is also less or equal
than I of G.
And this is what one calls
monotonicity.
In fact, this monotonic
behavior is what we now
can use to expand our
definition to
general measurable maps
in order to get a
visualization, let's
sketch again a graph.
Now this is the graph of
some measurable map
which is not a simple function.
As you can see.
Now, the integral should
be now again represented
by the area below
the graph and the X axis.
However, we only have this
notion for the moment for
the simple functions.
And as you know, by now,
a simple function has
only finitely many
values.
And this blue curve here
shows you there are infinitely
many values.
The whole idea of the Lebesgue
integration is now to
approximate the function
by finitely many
values.
So I just choose some values
here on the y axis
such that the whole
curve is in some sense
covered.
And now the idea is to
define a suitable
simple function.
Therefore, maybe I choose
this interval here
and look what happens to
the values of the function
there.
And now you see we have two
parts that are
mapped to this
interval here.
For the X axis, this
looks like this.
So we have this part here
that ends here
and we have this part that
starts here
and also ends
here.
This means we have one part
of our set here and the other
part here.
And of course, this should
be our set that we
usually call A
I.
So this is just one A
I and the
corresponding C
you find now here.
So this would be our C I.
So I chose the lower part
of the interval because then
our step function is also
below the graph of the
function.
So this would be the
value of our step function
here.
And now you see all the other
values on the Y axis
give us the other
c_i's and also the
corresponding A_i's
therefore, with this decomposition
of the Y axis, we get
out the usual step function
where we have our C is there.
And the so defined A
is where we have now the
characteristic function here.
So this is a new simple function
which I should call
h now.
And the important part is
that h itself
lies always
below F so
always below the graph that
is blue here.
Therefore, if we want to
contain the monotonicity
in the general integral,
we now have an estimate
for the real integral value
of the function F.
We know that the integral
of this step function is
smaller than the real
integral.
And this gives now rise to
the following definition.
Hence, we choose a positive
or better a non-negative
function F that is
defined on our measure
space X.
And of course, it should
be measurable.
And now for each decomposition
of the Y axis, we can
choose such a
step function or simple
function h that lies
pointwisely below
the graph of the function
F itself.
And if we choose the function
h out of the
step function that are
positive or non negative.
So S plus, we know
we can look at the
integral of this
h.
What we have is then a whole
set of integral
values where the only condition
is that our step function
is always below
the real function F.
The general idea is now
OK.
So this integral value for
the step function is always
smaller than the
actual integral value for
the function F.
And we should get closer
and closer to this value
if we choose a finer and
finer decomposition of the
Y axis, so
we approximate something
with the set here.
And of course, this should
be the supremum of the
set.
In fact, this is what we
choose as the
definition of the
integral for our function
F.
So we have F d mu
and also this is our measure
space X.
So the integral of a nonne
measurable map
F is given
by the supremum of
all integral values for
step functions that
lie below the function
F.
And that is now the
definition of the Lebesgue
integral.
And we also see this is well
defined the
supremum of a
set in the real numbers always
exists.
In the worst case, it would
be infinity.
Therefore, in addition, we
also have another definition
F is called mu-integrable
if the integral is
finite.
So it's not the symbol
infinity.
And there we have it, this
is our result for today,
the Lebesgue integral in
complete generality
because you see the only
thing we needed here
was a measure space
X.
So we only needed to know
how to measure the
volumes of these sets
on the X axis.
However, what we use is that
we map into the real
numbers.
So indeed, here we have R
on the Y axis.
Therefore, we can do this
decomposition, we can't do
this decomposition on the
X axis because there's no
order is nothing more than
just the measure.
But on the y axis, we can
do it.
Now, we should always keep
in mind the Lebesgue integral
is just defined within
supremum where we use
simple functions to
define the integral first.
So this was a long video
today and I hope you
learned something here.
Of course, we had to define
a lot of stuff.
But in the end, you saw
it is just a simple function
where we can write down the
integral immediately.
And then the
general integral is just
an approximation concept.
In the next video, I will
continue with the Lebesgue
integral and also
write down a lot of
properties we have for it.
And afterwards, you will
finally see why the Lebesgue
integral is so powerful,
then have a nice day
and see you next time.
Bye.