Hello and welcome back.
And I want to thank all the
nice people that support
this channel on Steady
here we continue
now our measure theory
series and today
we do part seven.
The most important topic
for today will be the
monotone convergence
theorem.
Before explaining this very
important convergence theorem,
I first want to start
showing you some essential
properties of the Lebesgue
integral.
Recall, we have introduced
the Lebesgue integral for
non-negative
measurable
functions defined on
some measure space X.
For such functions
We now know that the Lebesgue
integral is well-defined.
And the notation we have
chosen is this integral
symbol where we put the measure
space X here.
The function F here and the
measure itself goes in with
the mu where mu is the
measure defined on X.
The integral is well-defined
Now means that this
symbol is a number
between zero and
infinity.
And in the worst case, it
could be the symbol infinity.
Also recall
this symbol was defined
by a supremum over all
step functions that lie point-
wisely below F
OK.
Now I want to collect some
properties that follow
immediately from this definition.
So let's choose two of
these nice functions,
which means they are non-
negative and also
measurable.
Now we have the following.
The first thing would be
if both functions
coincide,
then also the
integrals coincide.
However, of course, this
is trivially fulfilled.
Therefore, I want to weaken
the left hand side a little
bit here, I want
the functions to be equal
mu-almost
everywhere.
The abbreviation one chooses
here is always A
E.
So mu A E means
mu-almost everywhere.
This means now that the
functions don't have to be
equal, but they should be
equal almost everywhere
with respect to the measure
mu. more
concretely
This whole property here
means that you
look at the set
of all
lowercase X in
our X for
which this property
does not hold.
So you have F of
X unequal to
G of X,
then this whole set
should be of measure
zero with respect to our
measure mu.
In other words, if you put
the whole set into the measure,
you get out zero.
This means that the Lebesgue
integral cannot see
things that happen on
zero measure sets.
Maybe for visualization,
it's good to recall what
we had for the Riemann integral.
If you integrate a
continuous function with
our classical Riemann integral,
you get out the
area between
the graph function and the
X axis.
And now if you change the
function at one point,
so the result is a non-
continuous function now
and then of course, you don't
change the area here at
all, which then
means the integral is
the same for
Lebesgue integral.
Now, this works in an
abstract sense
which means that you can
change the function as much
as you want.
As long as the set
of all these changes
has measure zero.
I will talk about this later
in another video.
When I show you a lot of
examples. Here, I
want to continue with the
second property which is
the monotonicity.
It is descriptively given
by saying that if a function
is bigger than another one,
then also the area here
should be bigger.
However, as before we
need the less of equal sign
only almost
everywhere.
And then we can conclude
that the integral of
F is less or
equal than the integral of
G.
And now to the last property
which is related to the first
one, I want my function
F to be zero
and also mu-
almost everywhere.
Now, by using a, I know
that the integral of F
is therefore also
zero because the integral
of the zero function is zero.
However, here I want to emphasize
another direction.
If the function has an integral
of zero, then we
already know that the function
has to be zero mu-
almost everywhere.
Please don't forget that
we only consider non-negative
functions here.
So all the areas we consider
are above the X axis and
therefore positive.
Therefore, there is no cancellation
whatsoever with positive
and negative
Areas here.
Well, now I could say
all the three properties
are easy to prove.
So you could do this for
yourself.
However, I also want you
to learn some
technical steps here.
And therefore I will do the
proof of B
after seeing this proof,
I think you will be
capable of doing the proof
A and C for yourself.
If not, please ask in the
comments for
starting the proof.
Let us choose a
simple function h.
This means that we have a
representation with
characteristic functions.
So we know we can write it
as a finite
sum.
Maybe we end with N
and we have constant C
I and also sets
A I.
When we put that into
characteristic functions,
the corresponding sets here
should be measurable.
And therefore, the simple
function is always
measurable.
And the other property of
a simple function is that
it only has
finitely many
values.
Therefore, there's
always a canonical way to
write down a representation
for a simple function.
You're forming the sum over
all the values.
So you have T
in and now comes
the image of the simple function.
And I write that as h
of X,
then instead of C, we just
have this T and
then comes the characteristic
function of a
set I will now
describe
there we have all the X
points that
fulfill that.
If I put in this
point in my function, I
get out this special
T.
Do you see this is a
representation that is
allowed.
And often it is very helpful
to choose this special one
because you don't have to
define N or the CIS or
the A is you just write down
this representation.
And also the integral
can then easily be written
down as
always, it is defined by
our sum.
And our summation goes
over T in the
image of H
and then simply T
times the measure of
this set.
So we have
mu of the
whole set where I write all
the X that
fulfill HX
equals to this T.
And to make it a little bit
easier, you can
always ignore the zero.
So you omit the zero as an
element in the image.
And because you don't change
anything for the integral
here by multiplying with
zero.
The question for you is now
what happens if we
change the simple
function on a
set which has measure
zero in
order to investigate this,
I need a little space here.
So we push this one
here to the bottom now.
OK, maybe a quick sketch
is helpful here.
So this is the whole measure
space X.
And now let us split that
up into two sets.
So this one would be the
big X tilde.
And of course, the complement,
the whole rest is just
X tilde c.
The compliment of X tilde,
this means that our x is
now divided into two
sets.
We want that
the x tilde
complement has
measured zero.
And with respect to this
set, with measure zero, I
want to change our simple
function.
And of course, I call it
H tilde and define it
by using two
cases.
The first case would be as
before.
So H tilda X
is equal to HX for
all X in
X tilde.
So nothing changes on the
green set.
But on the gray set, I will
set it to a new value And
I just choose an A.
So this is for all X
in X tilde
compliment, and
A is now just an arbitrary
chosen positive number.
So zero to infinity
by definition, this is of
course, again, a simple
function because
the set X tilde, I didn't
say it.
But of course, it should
be in the Sigma algebra.
So it should be measurable.
And then we can write down
again a representation
for this step or simple
function.
I can use the representation
from before.
So now let's go over all
the values of the
original function h.
And now I know it only
occurs for X in
X tilde.
So I write down T
times characteristic
function.
And now I put only the
XS from X Tilde
into this characteristic
function.
Not included in this sum
is what happens outside of
X tilde.
And therefore we add
this one as the value
a times
characteristic function.
And now we have all the
X
in X where
H tilda is equal to
a but this is simply
X tilde complement.
So we can write in
short just this
X tilde compliment here.
OK.
I have explicitly written
down the representation
because then we can write
down the integral as well.
Now I of
H tilde
equal to the
sum with T
over
HX
and you will have t times
the measure of this
set
plus a times
the measure of this set,
which is again, X tilde
the compliment.
However, you already know
the measure of X tilde compliment
is zero.
So this whole thing here
on the right, it's
still zero.
That simply means we can
just omit it.
And now you should see the
differences above and below
are not so big.
The only real difference
is to tilde the here
because the zero does not
make any difference.
As I said before,
our task is now to
fill in the middle ground
here.
Now, it depends what you
find easier.
So maybe we come from the
bottom and just use
what we know there.
So we have
mu of
the whole X
and now we just split it
up into X tilde
where the condition is fulfilled
union.
And here we have
just x tilde
C.
Now, obviously this is the
same as the bottom part.
And we know it's a disjoint
union which means we
can easily use the sigma
additivity  here.
Therefore, parentheses here
and here I write
plus or
maybe first close
parenthesis here as well.
So this would be black
then plus
mu of
this set.
However, we already know
that X tilde complement
is a set with measure
zero with or without this
condition, it only gets
smaller with the condition,
which means this is still
a set with measure
zero.
And now we have all the
equalities here.
We just add a zero here.
So this is equal and this
is equal, everything is equal,
which means the integral
of H tilde is equal to
the integral of H.
This means now that we can
change the simple function
on a set with measure
zero as much as we want.
Indeed, this is a very important
result.
And you can use that
for proving some of these
parts here.
But we wanted to prove part
B
there, we have two measurable
functions whether one
is bigger than the other
one almost everywhere.
Therefore, now we know how
to choose our x tilde.
It simply should be the
set of all x
where F of
X is less or
equal than G of
X.
Then by assumption we
also know that X tilde
complement has
measure zero.
Well, then let's look at
the integral of F
by definition, it's the
supremum of
all integrals of step
functions.
And we denoted them by S
plus where the
step function or the simple
function is less or
equal than F.
Now by the results from
before we know that we
don't change the integral
value when we change the
step function on a
set with measure zero.
Therefore, the supremum is
still the same when I put
in our step functions
where I have H
tilde less than
F but
only on
X tilde.
That is the whole point.
If we change something outside
of X tilde, we
can't change I of
H tilde.
So the whole supremum is the
same as the supremum here
on the left.
Very good.
And now we can use what we
know from F and
G on
X tilde G
is always bigger than F.
So we have here
always this
inequality.
Hence, if we write down the
same thing again,
but now with G
instead of F,
then this set gets
bigger than this set because
there are more step functions
maybe inside this set.
Therefore, we have an
inequality at
this point.
Now with the same reasoning
as before the supremum
is equal to the
supremum where I
ignore x tilde and
use step functions
on the whole set X.
And this one is
exactly the definition of
the integral of
our function G.
And if we put everything
together, so this one, the
inequality and this
one, we have proven our
claim and this
is the monotonicity property
of the Lebesgue integral where
we only need this
inequality
almost everywhere.
OK.
So this one was a long
proof and I showed you all
the technical details
because we need them again.
When we prove the monotone
convergence theorem.
However, maybe let's
first state the
monotone convergence
theorem.
Remember this was our
goal from the beginning of
the video.
The first condition is that
we have a measure space.
So set X Sigma algebra
and a measure mu.
And we also have some
nonne
measurable
functions
FN and
F
from X to zero
to infinity.
And as I said, they are
measurable for
all N in
N.
And in addition, they
satisfy two
properties.
First, they are
monotonically
increasing.
So we have F one less or
equal than F two, less or
equal than F three
and so on.
And this holds
almost everywhere.
So mu
This always means that the
points X where this condition
is not satisfied
form a set with
measure zero.
And the second condition
is that the pointwise
limit of the
sequence of functions
is equal to
F of X
also mu
almost everywhere
for X in X.
OK.
Here is now an X and we
say it holds almost
everywhere which just means
OK, there is a set X tilde
where this one holds and
a compliment of X tilde
has measured zero.
And this one is just the
common abbreviation of this.
So we just say X and X mu-
almost everywhere and then
everyone knows what we mean.
And now the monotone
convergence theorem states
that we can push the
limit inside
the integral.
Hence the limit of
the integrals
f n d mu
is equal to OK.
Limit inside means
integral over
X.
And the limit inside is
just the function F
mu-almost everywhere.
So we can put
f dmu here.
And that is the convergence
theorem.
Now, you know, when you
can push the limit
inside the, the call, when
you have a monotonic sequence
of functions.
Indeed, such convergence
theorems are
mostly the best
advantages the
Lebesgue integral has over
the Riemann integral.
And therefore, I really want
to show you the proof of
this monotone
convergence theorem.
However, this is a thing
we will do in the next video
because this video is
already very long
and it is good to do a short
break.
Maybe now recall
everything we did here in
this video.
And then maybe you can
come to the next video where
we do the proof of the
monotone convergence
theorem.
I really hope you will be
there.
So then see you next
time.