Hello and welcome back to
the next video in this
series.
I thank all the nice people
that support this channel
on Steady
Well, this is measure theory
part eight.
And we are still talking
about the monotone convergence
theorem.
But today I want to show
you mainly the proof
of this theorem
for the start of this video.
It might be helpful to
give you a recap what the
monotone convergence theorem
states. For the
ingredients, we need a measure
space and
measurable maps
as always they are non-
negative.
And we have a whole sequence
of such measurable maps.
And in addition, we also
have the limit where we call
this just F without an
index.
OK.
Because the theorem is called
monotone convergence theorem.
We need two things first,
a monotonic property and
also a convergent property.
The first thing is therefore
the sequence is
monotonically increasing
but only almost everywhere
with respect to our measure
mu
And the second property I
already told you F should
be the limit of
FN and the limit should
be in the pointwise sense which
means I fix a point
X and then I have a normal
limit of real numbers.
However, as before, this
property only has to hold
almost everywhere.
So much about the premise.
Now let's talk about the
conclusion.
The theorem tells us that
we can push the
limit into the
integral.
This means that the sequence
of integrals converges
to an integral where in the
integral there's the
limit of the sequence.
And of course, this is just
our F here.
And now we have again our
monotone convergence
theorem.
However, I should tell you
there is an alternative formulation
of this theorem which is
a little bit more general
what you do there is you
include also
functions that have the
symbol infinity as an
outcome.
Of course, then you have
to extend the Borel Sigma
algebra to this
new bigger set
and also extend the notion
of measurable.
And indeed, that's not a
problem at all
in the same way.
Also the definition of the
Integral does not change
at all because in the worst
case, as always, it could
be infinity.
The advantage of this formulation
is now that you can get rid
of the F completely.
So we don't need this
and we don't need
this
simply because everything
follows from the monotonic
property here, we have
measurable functions and
we know the supremum is also
measurable and they are
monotonically increasing.
So we know the supremum is given
almost everywhere as the
limit.
And there you see this is
just a more compact formulation
of the theorem.
And as I told you before,
in the worst case, you have
infinity left and
right in the conclusion here.
Well, so this was the
introduction.
Now, let's look at
the proof,
of course, we use what we
know we have a
monotonically
increasing sequence
of functions.
This property holds almost
everywhere.
And if you remember what
we did in the last video,
we know that we have the
monotonicity property of
the Lebesgue integral.
This means that the integral
conserves
these inequalities.
Now we have a monotonically
increasing sequence of real
numbers where also
infinity can occur
in the same sense, we can
write down the inequality
for all N.
So we know that the limit
is always bigger or equal
than FN for
all N and almost
everywhere,
simply because the limit
is almost everywhere, the
supremum and because
this holds almost everywhere,
we know it holds for the
integral as well.
And there you see, we already
have one part of the
equality here.
We want to show.
So let's call this star
for a reference
and let's show the one
inequality.
So we formed the limit on
both sides here.
Of course, we don't change
the inequality here.
And we have no limit on the
right hand side because there's
no N involved.
And therefore we have this
as the inequality.
And this is exactly one
part of our
equality star.
Do you see this was not so
hard.
This part comes immediately
but for the other part we
need to use the definition
of the Lebesgue integral.
And this always means that
we go back to step or simple
functions.
Therefore, let h be an
arbitrary chosen simple function
that lies below
our function F
and also choose a
fixed error
epsilon
at this point.
I think a short sketch is
very helpful to get the idea.
Here is our function F
and this one should be the
step function H so maybe
it looks like this.
OK.
So this would be the usual
idea.
Now we know we have the pointwise
convergence of this
sequence of functions to
F.
So maybe we can choose some
FN that lies
very close to F.
So maybe this is
our chosen FN.
The idea of the epsilon is
now that we can always push
down the step function by
this epsilon.
So this would be epsilon
and then the new step function
looks like this.
And this should then always
be a step function that lies
below FN.
Hence I define now
sets XN
where I put in all the
points X
where FN of X
is bigger than the
shifted step function.
And the shifted step function
is just one minus
epsilon h
because we have our
convergence of the
sequence FN to F
almost everywhere
we know that
almost every X
in X lies
in at least one of these
XN.
In other words, we can look
at the union of all these
XN and
let's call it X tilde,
then we know that the complement
of X tilde is a set with
measure zero.
Knowing this, we can now
look at the integral again.
Now we start here with the
left hand side.
So I want to look at the
integral of FN.
This integral gets not
bigger if I change the set
to a smaller set.
So here I want to choose
XN
Fn dmu.
Now inside the set XN,
we have this inequality
and can use the normal
monotonicity of the integral.
Therefore, I have the same
inequality here.
And a new function inside
the integral which is now
one minus epsilon
h dmu.
And of course, we want to
look at the limit.
So we found the limit here
on both sides,
then we get
limit
of the integrals.
And on the right hand side,
we have the limit of
these integrals.
OK.
At this point, I want to
omit some details because
otherwise we will lose our
focus completely.
What one can show now is
that this is indeed
the integral over
X tilde.
And we don't change the
function at all.
And what we need in the details
is of course that this is
a step function.
So the integral is very easy.
Essentially, it's just a
sum of our measures.
And we know that the
sets here are
increasing, you
have to find the sets appropriately.
But then you get out that
you have a monotonically
increasing sequence
of sets.
OK.
In summary, I'll leave the
details here for you.
But remember we can do
this because this is just
a step function and integral.
It's very easy there.
OK.
But after this, you see it
doesn't make any difference
to choose X tilde here or X
because for the integral,
it does not matter what happens
on a set with measure
zero.
And in the last video, I
have shown it explicitly
for the step functions.
OK.
Now we have an
inequality that holds
for all epsilon here on the
right hand side, this
means now that we can choose
the epsilon as
small as we want.
And therefore we have a
limit process for the epsilon
and still have the
inequality if we
would set epsilon to
zero.
So this means here we
have the integral greater
or equal than the
integral.
And here just h
remains.
Now in the same sense,
this h was arbitrarily
chosen.
It was just a step function
that lies below our
function F.
This means now that we can
go to the supremum
over all the step
functions.
And then we get on the right
hand side, the integral of
F and there you have
it.
This is the second part of
our equality star.
Both things together
gives us the proof of the
monotone convergence theorem.
OK.
For the end of the video,
I want to show you an
application of this very
important monotone convergence
theorem.
One can always use this
for series if
you have any sequence of
functions, then I use now the
letter G that are
non-negative and also
measurable.
Then you can apply the
monotone convergence theorem.
So here I use also to assume
the infinity for the functions
and measurable.
So we don't need a monotonic
behavior here.
Then we can say that the
series
which now goes from one
to infinity.
This is also a well defined
function and also measurable.
The trick is now of course,
that the partial sums
form a monotonically
increasing sequence of
functions.
Therefore, we can write down
the integral of the
series.
So it goes to infinity.
g n de mu
is equal, putting
the series outside the
integrals
So here's the series of
the integrals
So gn
d mu
this means that the monotone
convergence theorem allows
us to switch
integral and series.
The only thing we have to
put in is that we have
non-negative measurable
functions and we
need no other assumptions
at all.
And there you see the power
of this theorem, it gives
you immediately such a nice
property as this
very well.
That's all I wanted to tell
you about the monotone convergence
theorem.
And I hope you learned
how one can prove it.
And more importantly, you
now learned when you can
apply it, you
need a monotonically
increasing sequence of
functions that are non-
negative.
Later, we will see how we
can weaken a little bit this
assumption.
However, for the moment this
version here is powerful
enough.
In the following next videos
we will talk about other
convergence theorem that are
also very important.
I hope I see you there and
of course, I wish you a nice
day.
Bye.