Hello and welcome back to
measure theory.
First.
Let me thank all the nice
supporters on Steady.
We have come very far in
a series and reached now
part nine,
I was talking about the very
important convergence theorems.
And today I want to tell
you about Fatou's Lemma.
This lemma is much more
important than it sounds
first.
However, it's not
quite a convergence theorem,
more or less half a convergence
theorem, but it is
so general that you can apply
it very often.
OK.
Then let me explain you
what the Lemma states.
As always, we have a measure
space consisting
of a set, a Sigma
algebra and a measure.
And we also have a
sequence of measurable
functions.
OK.
Here I want to write down
the codomain of the functions
and there I have to tell
you there are different
possibilities and they
lead to different variations
of Fatou's lemma.
However, I think the best
way to describe it is again
to choose non-negative
functions.
When I say non negative,
then it's clear that the
zero is included, but it's
not clear if infinity
is included.
However, here, that's not
a problem.
We can just include it.
And now to the statement
of this lemma,
because we are in the realm
of the convergence theorems,
the question would be again,
OK, I have integral over
X and a limit
inside.
Can I pull out
this limit?
However, Fatou's Lemma
is a little bit more specific,
it does not look at the limit
rather than at the limit
inferior.
Now, Fatou's Lemma claims
that if we look at the limit
inferior of our sequence
of functions FN, so
here's d mu
then I can pull out the limit
inferior and then I have
to limit inferior here of
the numbers given by the
integrals of FN.
But we don't have an
equality sign here,
just an inequality sign.
And Fatou tells us the
left hand side can't be
bigger than the right hand
side.
So you see the Lemma is not
so strong as a convergence
theorem.
But please note that our
requirements are very weak.
We only need non-negative
measurable maps.
Nothing else.
The actual convergence
theorem that follows from
this claim here is Lebegue's
theorem which we will consider
in the next video
before showing you the proof
of this nice lemma.
Let me first explain
what this new function liminf
in of the sequence of functions
actually is.
Well, of course, it is a
function
which means it is
defined on X
and maps also
into our non negative
numbers including
infinity.
And now I want to give you
the definition.
So the functions are defined
for all lower case X.
And now we use what we know
from the limit inferior.
It is given by the
limit of the infima
but cut it at the beginning.
So we go from
N to infinity
and then we look what happens
when n goes to infinity.
This is the definition of
the limit inferior for a
sequence of numbers.
And here we just have numbers
because we look at
FX
and they will see the lowest
level that the infimum can
have would be zero.
But in the limit, of
course, it could go to infinity.
So we also have to include
infinity
also in the case when we
would exclude infinity
here because in a limit it
could happen.
And because we need the infinity
symbol for this function,
we can just add it from the
beginning.
And of course, it just makes
the claim stronger.
The beauty of this is that
we know that the limit
inferior is also
measurable
simply because you can easily
show that if you put in
measurable functions in
infima are measurable
and also limits of
measurable functions are
also measurable
for the whole proof.
Now it makes sense to use
some abbreviations here,
let's call the limit inferior
just by G of X.
So we have the function G
now and
also these functions
here given by the
infima let's call them
GN of X.
And of course, all the functions
here are measurable
and we get another information
out here.
These functions here are
now monotonically increasing.
So G one is less or
equal than G two,
less or equal than G
three.
And so on,
this follows immediately
from the definition of the
infimum.
Because if we shift the cut
point and to divide
the inimum can only get bigger,
not smaller.
OK.
So we get out a sequence
that is monotonically
increasing.
And of course, this would
be very helpful for our proof
now because we can
use our convergence theorem,
we already know.
And of course, you know,
it's the monotone convergence
theorem.
And indeed, with this, the
proof is not so long
on the left hand side, we
have the limit inferior.
And now I write that as
the limit of our
GNS
indeed, that is just our
limit inferior here.
And now we want to pull out
the limit here.
And you know, now it's allowed
by the monotone convergence
theorem.
And we also have the equality
here.
Please check with the last
videos that we have indeed
satisfied all the requirements
of the theorem.
Now the next step, I
substitute the limit
with the limit inferior
simply because this is the
thing we want to talk about
in Fatou's Lemma.
And of course here it's the
same thing doesn't make any
difference at all.
However, in the end, we want
FN and not GN in the
integral here.
Therefore, you can ask, what
is the connection between
G and and FN
and then you look at the
definition and see,
OK, the G and is defined
about all FK where
K is bigger than N
and then you choose the infimum,
the smallest possible value.
And therefore, of course
GN is always less or
equal than FN as
being the infimum.
So let's say that as we
know
GN, less or equal to FN
for all N and
now you want to use the
monotonicity of the integral,
which is a very nice property
of the Lebegue integral.
So if we have the inequality
here, then it also
holds for the integral.
OK.
So this inequality we now
want to use here on the
right hand side.
So let me summarize what
we have here.
The left hand side is the
limit inferior
inside the integral.
And on the right hand side,
we can use this
inequality, the limit
inferior, conserve the
inequality, which
means we have here less or
equal and limit
inferior outside
FNDmu.
And there we have it that
is Fatou's Lemma.
You see the proof was not
so hard and not so long because
we could use our monotone
convergence theorem here.
OK.
So I hope you learned something
today and then you will see
in the next video how we
can apply Fatou's lemma.
And then we can finally prove
one of my favorite
theorems.
OK.
I wish you a very nice day
and see you next time.
Bye.