Hello and welcome back
to measure theory first.
As always, let me thank all
the nice supporters on
Steady.
I am very happy to see that
we have already reached
part 10.
And today we will do my
favorite theory in the
integration theory.
And this is Lebesgue's
dominated convergence
theorem.
Indeed, the name is quite
fitting because it is as
before a convergence theorem
and something has to
dominate the given
function.
Recall a convergence
theorem tells you when
you can pull in a
limit into the
integral.
It turns out that this
convergence theorem that
is named after Lebesgue is
very useful and you can apply
it very often
before I state the theorem,
let me first start by
introducing some notations.
As always we choose a measure
space.
So set X and
Sigma algebra A and a measure
mu.
Now we define a set of Lebesgue-
integrable functions.
Therefore, we use this curved
L most of the
time the set X and the Sigma
algebra are so fixed in the
context that only the
measure can vary.
And therefore, I just use
mu here in a notation.
In other cases, you would
write the whole measure space
here inside. The set
is now defined as
the set of all Lebesgue-
integrable functions.
Now the functions should
be defined on
X and have values in
R.
You could also generalize
that to complex
values in the end.
But that's not so hard indeed.
The important thing however
is that they are
measurable.
Now, remember we defined the
integral for
non-negative functions.
And for that reason, I look
at the integral for the absolute
value of F, this is a
non-negative function and
we know it's still
measurable.
So we can look at the integral,
we know this exists in all
cases, but in the worst case,
it could be infinity.
Hence integrable in this
sense means it's not
infinity, which means
less than infinity.
OK.
So this is the important
set here, the set of
Lebesgue-integrable functions
in this sense,
maybe I should give you a
small remark here,
totally unnecessary in this
context.
But it will be important
later there.
You will be interested in
the power for which the
function is integrable
this means that you have
here, the exponent, the power
one.
And you also put it on
the L
in short, you then call it
just the L one
space for such
functions.
You can also define the integral
just by looking at the
positive and the negative
part here separately.
This means that for F in
our L one
space,
we write the function F
as the combination of two
non-negative functions and
I call this first one F
plus and the second one
F minus
and the combination is given
by a minus sign.
And, and the idea is F
plus F minus
are non-negative.
OK.
Maybe a short picture for
this.
If this is the
graph of the function F,
then this part here
is the graph of our function
F plus.
And of course, this part
here then is
the graph corresponding
to F minus.
It's not exactly F minus,
this would be
minus F
minus.
However, obviously adding
both these functions gives
you back our original F.
Now you may immediately believe
me that for all functions
F, you can split them up
into these two parts
in the positive part above
the X axis.
And the negative part below
the X axis,
we have to do this because
we only define the integral
for non-negative functions.
As you remember, the
idea is then I have an
integral for F plus
and also an integral for
F minus.
And then I will subtract
the areas then I
don't get out the area
but I get out an orientated
area where I
subtract the parts that
lie below the X axis.
This is the integral notion
we want.
And we also have this for
the Riemann integral, as
you remember.
Hence, therefore, the definition
is given as the
following symbol, the integral
over X for the
function F dmu
defined as
the well-defined integral
of F plus
has a non-negative function minus
The well-defined value
for the integral F minus,
both parts have a
positive value.
And we also know it's
finite by this
assumption here.
Therefore, the subtraction
is no problem at all.
We get out a real number
in the end.
OK.
Now you know what the integral
symbol is for measurable
functions with real values.
I skipped some details for
the definition of F plus
and F minus because I think
the picture is sufficient
here.
OK.
Now I can finally
state Lebesgue's
dominated convergence theorem.
What we need here is a
sequence of functions and
I call it FN defined on
X and they can
have real values now
and of course, they should
be measurable.
Of course, you can visualize
this always as
sequence of graphs.
So this would be F one.
And then the next thing would
be here as F two
and then here at F three
and so on.
For such a sequence of functions
you can always ask
about the pointwise limit.
This means that you fix a
point X on the X
axis and
look at the values for the
functions.
So you have one value here,
the next one here.
So you get out a
normal sequence of
real numbers.
Therefore, you can ask what
happens with this
normal sequence of
numbers.
If it is convergent, you
get out a limit which is
then a point here.
In the case, you can do this
for all X here, you get
out a lot of points here.
And indeed, you get out a
new graph and therefore a
new function.
And this is the pointwise
limit function.
And we will call it just
F here.
And this is what I also want
to put into the assumptions
of our theorem here.
This means that we also have
our function F here
also with the
values.
And the following property,
if we fix a point X
for all our functions
FN, then this should
be convergent to
F of X.
And I told you we want this
property for all
X on the X axis.
So for all lower
case X in our capital
X, however,
you know, we are in the realm
of measure theory,
this means we don't need
this property exactly
everywhere.
It's sufficient that we have
it almost everywhere,
almost always means
with respect to our measure
mu here.
And in short, we write this
as mu
almost everywhere.
Please recall that this
means exactly that the
set where this does
not hold is a
set of measure
zero.
So mu of the set
is equal to zero.
OK.
So until now the assumptions
are not so strange,
you have a sequence of measurable
functions and also
the pointwise limit of
this sequence.
And now you could ask a lot
of questions are the
functions integrable?
So do they lie in our
L one space.
And if they do, what about
our point was estimate function
F then and more
importantly, can I
swap the limit
And the integral? Or in
other words, can I pull
in the limit into the
integral?
Now Lebesgue's dominated
convergence theorem says
yes to all of these
questions,
if we add one
more assumption
and this is where the dominated
comes into the play,
we have that the absolute
value of all these
functions is
bounded by a function
G.
Of course, you should read
this point wisely.
So if you put in an X
here, this inequality
holds the
function G now has the
property that it is
integrable, which means it
comes from our L one
space
and obviously it should be
the same G for
all N.
Now this G is what one
usually calls an integrable
majorant.
So this is what Lebesgue's
dominated convergence theorem
indeed needs it needs an
integrable majorant.
So a function that
lies above all
the other functions here.
This means it's not important
what exactly the function
G is.
You only need this
inequality and you
need that it's integrable
from these two properties.
Now, all the other things
follow, for
example, if you know
that G has a finite
integral, then all the
other functions should be
also integrable.
OK.
So let's write that down
as the implication of the
theorem,
all the functions F
one F two
F three and so on
lie in our
L one space.
And we can say the same
for our point west limit
function F.
Of course, we know it should
be measurable as a limit,
but it's also
integrable.
Now let's look at the integrals
we know
for all FN, the
integral will exist
and defines a real
number.
Therefore, we have here a
new sequence of real numbers
and we can ask what is the
limit?
And the answer is you can
pull the limit
inside and there we
have our pointwise limit
of f_n.
So this is what we called
F
and that's now Lebesgue's
dominated convergence theorem
as a convergence theorem,
it tells you when you are
allowed to push the limit
inside the integral.
And here you see, you just
have to find a suitable
function G nothing more.
And that is the reason why
this theorem is so
useful and you can apply
it very often.
OK?
I hope you're also intrigued
by the theorem as much as I
am and that you will
watch the next video in the
series
where I of course show
you the whole proof of
this dominated convergence
theorem.
And after this, I can show
you a lot of examples
where Lebesgue's dominated convergence
theorem is very important.
OK.
Thank you very much for listening
and see you next time.
Bye.