Hello and welcome
back.
And as always, I thank
all the nice people that
support this channel on
Steady today,
we consider part
11 in our measure
theory series.
And as promised, it will
be about the proof
of Lebesgue's dominated
convergence theorem.
I already told you this is
one of my favourite theorems.
And you will see that the
proof is indeed not so
hard.
OK.
Then let's recall the
theorem from the last part
of the series.
Here you see all the
assumptions we need for
Lebesgue's dominated convergence
theorem.
On the one hand, we have
a sequence of measurable
maps and
also the pointwise limit
function which we will call
just F.
And on the other hand, we
have another function G
which is integrable.
And this function G is
indeed the
important ingredient in the
whole theorem.
It should lie
above all the
functions FN.
And therefore we call it
an integrable majorant.
From these nice
assumptions.
We now can conclude
that all the functions in
the sequence are also
integrable.
And moreover, also the
mu almost everywhere point-
wise limit function F is
also integrable.
From this, we can conclude
that all these integrals
here make sense.
And the equality tells us
that we can pull in the
limit into the integral.
And that's the reason we
call it a convergence theorem.
Well, then let's start
with the proof
the ingredients we need for
the proof are on the one
side properties of the integral.
And also on the other hand,
Fatou's lemma
from the properties of the
interval, we can immediately
show the first property here.
Please recall that lying
in L1 means that the
absolute value of
FN has a finite
integral.
Please remember we have
measurable maps and this
is a non-negative function.
Therefore, the integral always
exists.
But in the worst case, it
could be infinity.
Therefore lying in L1
means this is not
infinity.
So smaller than
OK.
Now we can use our assumption
we know that we have an integrable
majorant
called g.
So we have an inequality
here.
And you remember we have
a monotonicity property of
the integral.
This means we also have the
inequality in the
integral sense.
So let's put that to the
left.
And then I know this is less
or equal than the
integral of G.
Now note that this right
hand side is indeed our
assumption that the integral
of G is indeed
finite.
Our conclusion is now this
integral is also
finite.
And this means all the
FN lie in
L one.
Obviously we can do the
same for F
instead of FN
because we know it's a point
where it's limited almost
everywhere.
Therefore, this inequality
holds almost
everywhere.
And of course, also almost
everywhere, the monotonicity
property still holds, which
means we get the same
inequality here for the integral
of F.
In other words, we also
have F in L
one.
OK.
Very good.
So what you have seen now
is that the first part in
the theorem was very easy to
show.
Hence, the crucial thing
in the theorem is
indeed this
convergence statement here.
OK.
So this is what we do in
the next five minutes.
And indeed, I want to show
something a little bit
more stronger.
We will show that the
integral of the absolute
value of
FN minus the
pointwise limit F
goes to zero
if N goes to
infinity.
And from this, we can immediately
conclude the property we
want here.
However, let us start
showing this property here.
OK.
In the integral, we have
the function FN
minus F.
But in the absolute
value now we
know that for the absolute
volume going a detour
makes it greater or in the
best case, it stays the same
now going the detour to
0.
This means we have the absolute
value of FN plus
the absolute value of
F.
This is just the
triangle inequality for the
absolute value.
When we read it point-
wisely, this means
we could put in x's
here for the functions,
but it holds for all the
x's.
Therefore, this is just the
short notation we use
also what we know is that
we have our majorant
G for FN.
And also for F, as I told
you, therefore,
we have this as less
or equal than
two G,
one G plus one G.
Now you could say this
inequality only
holds mu almost
everywhere.
However, it does not matter
at all because the integral
does not see changes that
happen almost
nowhere,
which is the complement of
almost everywhere.
Therefore, we could change
or choose another function
G where this
inequality here does
indeed hold everywhere.
Hence, we can assume that
we do this here.
And therefore, I can omit
the mu almost everywhere
and it makes the proof just
shorter.
OK.
Now I can bring this on the
other side and I get
out a non negative
function I want to call
h_n.
So this would be two G
minus our absolute
value FN minus
F.
And we know it's non-
negative.
Obviously, this holds for
all N and we know
by the properties of
measurable functions that
h_n is
also measurable.
Now, I have written that
down in such a way that you
should recognize
immediately Fatou's
Lemma simply
because we have
measurable functions
and they are all non-
negative.
Therefore, now we can
apply Fatou's Lemma.
Fatou's Lemma tells us something
about the limit
inferior.
So liminf.
namely, it tells us that
we can look at the integral
of the liminf and we can
pull it out with an
inequality sign.
In fact, it's possible that
it gets bigger if we
pull the liminf
outside.
However, the inequality
always holds and that is
what we can need here.
Of course, you should ask
yourself, do we
know the liminf here?
And here,
maybe we should look first
on the left hand side
inside the integral, it
always means the point
wise limit.
Now it's the pointwise Liminf
.
But we know that the point
wise limit of
HN indeed
exists
and therefore, it should
be the same as the limits.
OK.
So let's write it down.
We know this is the integral
of our point wise limit of
HN two G
is two G.
But we know F is the point
limit of FN and
therefore this one is
zero.
So only two G
remains here.
OK.
Then let's look at the right
hand side there.
We have the integral of HN.
However, the integral is
linear.
So we have indeed two
integrals, one of two G
and the other one of our
F and minus F in the absolute
value.
For the first part, the liminf
does not matter.
So we can write down
immediately we have
two G here.
Then for the second part,
you have to be careful, we
subtract something positive.
And we look at the liminf
which means to get
out the liminf we have to
subtract the limsup, the
limit superior
or maybe in other words,
if you want to find the
smallest outcome here
as a non negative
number, yeah, you have to
subtract here.
The biggest possible number.
OK.
So this explains why we have
to limsup here, but we
don't change the integral
at all.
So this is FN
minus F dmu
OK?
We have the left hand side
here and the right hand side
here, we have a very nice
inequality
if I then add what I
missed before here.
So the d mu and our
X then you will recognize
immediately that we have the
same on the left and the
right here.
Of course, now you
should subtract the same
thing on both sides.
If we do this, we find
zero on the left
obviously
and only this part here
on the right hand side.
So minus our
limsup
OK.
So the minus sign is not
so beautiful.
Therefore, I want to bring
this on the other side,
which means we now
have the inequality here
on the right, which means
this would be without the
minus sign less or
equal than zero.
OK.
So now please note this is
very interesting.
The limsup of non-
negative numbers
should be non-
positives.
Hence, from this, we
can conclude that the
limit exists.
We do this in the following
way, we say OK, I
have to limsup
here, so this is always
greater or equal than
the liminf
Of course, this holds for
all sequence of
numbers.
The liminf is always less
or equal than the limsup.
But still we have non-
negative numbers here.
Therefore, the liminf should
be also nonnegative.
So we have this inequality
here.
This one here is now always
nice.
We have inequalities but
on the left is the
same as on the right.
This simply means that
all the inequalities here
are in fact
equalities.
There is simply no other
way, which means the liminf
is equal to the limsup,
which means the limit
exists and is equal to
the limsup and liminf which
is zero.
So let's write it down limit
exists and the limit
of this integral
is equal to
zero.
Well, this is what we wanted
to show and I explained
before this is a stronger
result than that what we
have in Lebesgue's
theorem.
But I will now show you how
we get to the result
in Lebesgue's dominated convergence
theorem.
OK.
Let's do that now.
So we want to
show that
the limit of the
functions
and the integral is
equal to the
integral of our
function.
F
therefore, we can look at
the difference and in the
absolute value and show
that this goes to
zero for N to
infinity.
OK.
The first part we can note
is this is also
nonnegative because it's
an absolute value.
And then the next steps we
can use the properties we
already know from the integral,
for example, the
linearity.
So we know this is indeed
just one integral where we
have F and
minus F in
the integral
itself.
And the absolute value around.
Now, in the next part, we
use something that is also
called triangle
inequality.
But here now for
integrals, which means now
put the absolute value inside
and then we can get bigger
or stay the same.
Here, we now reach something
that we already know at
least in a limit.
So it goes to
for N
to infinity.
Hence the last step we need
here now is just a
small sandwich theorem.
Now, on the limit we have
the zero left and
right.
And therefore we know this
limit also exists
and is equal to zero.
And therefore the whole thing
in the absolute value has
a limit and is equal to
zero.
So putting that on the other
side, we now can conclude
limit of the integrals of
FN is
equal to the
integral of F.
And here you see this is
the convergence statement
that we wanted to prove in
the beginning.
And that was the proof of
Lebesgue's dominated
convergence theorem.
I already told you
this part dominated
is the important ingredient
for the theorem because
we need such an
integrable majorant
we call this majorant just
G but you saw
we need this and
then we can apply
Lebesgue's dominated convergence
theorem.
If you want to see some
applications of
this theorem, please let
me know because this
could be a very good idea
for the next part in the
series.
So thank you very much and
see you next time.
Bye.