Hello and welcome to a
new video in the topic of
measure theory.
First, let me thank all the
nice people that support
this channel on steady.
And today's topic is Lebesgue-Stieltjes
measures.
It sounds like something
different than a normal measure,
but it's not, it's just a
way to construct an
ordinary measure.
And in this way, we can start,
we will now construct a
measure.
The only thing we need here
is a monotonically
increasing function
defined on the real number
line.
And when I say monotonically
increasing, I mean
non-decreasing.
In other words, a constant
function is also
monotonically increasing.
The best way to see that
is of course to draw a short
graph of such a function.
So maybe the function is
first increasing here
then at it is constant
and maybe, then we have a
jump point at this point.
So no value here, the value
is here then still the
constant
and maybe after this, it's
still increasing and then
comes the next jump point.
So here's the point and then
it goes to an
increasing function till
here and then maybe it's
constant after that.
OK.
So this is a typical example
of a graph of a
monotonically increasing
function.
In particular, it's allowed
that the function is
constant at some
parts.
And there could be also points
where the function is non
continuous.
So where we have jumps,
but of course, the jumps
has to go upwards.
Now, with the help of such
a function, we want to
measure the length of
intervals.
First, I want to calculate
intervals of the form A
B where A is
included but B is
excluded
for better visualization,
I can put that here in the
picture.
So here's A and
there's our B,
obviously, the normal notion
of the length would be just
B minus
A.
But here I want that F
as a function scales
the length of this interval,
this means that the length
should be longer where the
increase of the function
is stronger.
Therefore, we have to look
what the function does with
the interval.
So we look at the
image of the
interval under the
function F
in the picture.
This would roughly look like
this.
So we have a point
FB here
and F of A
here
scaling the length of this
interval of the function
F.
Now just means we look at
the Y axis here,
which means the length of
this interval which is
just F of
B minus
F of A.
OK.
Now, I hope you immediately
recognized a mistake here.
You see B is not
a point in our interval.
Therefore, it would be wrong
to use this point.
So the image of B we
should rather use this point
here.
This one is the correct point
that describes the right
hand bound of the
image of A B.
Therefore, on the Y axis,
we also have this point
here.
The important one
and I would call it
FB minus in a
short notation.
Therefore, I would also include
the point here on the right
for calculating the length
of the interval.
Well, now you should see
we have the same problem
here.
We have the same problem
on the left hand side with
the point A, you
see A is included in
our interval.
And therefore, we should
include this full
jump in our calculation of
the length of this interval.
On the right hand side, we
ignored the full jump because
B was not in the interval,
but now A is in the
interval.
And therefore we should add
the jump to our calculation.
You see this immediately,
if we change this point
maybe to the middle here,
then we would change the
whole calculation of the
length, but we wouldn't
change the total jump.
Hence, the only meaningful
way to choose a point here
would be to choose the point
the value at the bottom here.
And as before, I also would
call this in short
by fa
minus and then we
include the minus sign here
as well.
Now this thing is now our
new notion of the length
of an interval.
And of course, I should give
it a name and we call it
mu with index
F of this
interval.
And to be more precise, I
also add the definition
of our FB
minus or FA
minus.
As you can see, this is nothing
else than a left limit.
So we get closer and
closer coming from the
left.
Therefore, we can write this
as an epsilon that goes to
zero plus, which means
it's an epsilon greater than
zero that goes to zero.
And then we subtract it
from A
and then you see we get back
the points we have seen in
our drawing here.
And at this point, you are
allowed to ask what
happens if I come from the
right hand side instead of
the left hand side.
And then what you get is
an alternative way to
write this down.
So we have FB
plus
minus FA
plus where the plus
now means the right hand
limit.
Now, if you go back to our
graph, then you see,
now we describe
another interval, not
this one because
now we ignore this jump,
but we add this jump on the
right, this means that
we exactly change the
boundaries here.
Now we measure an interval
where A is not
included.
But B is
hence, if you want to work
with these intervals, then
you have to consider the
right hand limit.
I personally want to work
with these intervals.
And therefore, we don't need
the alternative here.
Nevertheless, it's very important
to note that if you look
at the points where the function
F is not continuous,
then it does not matter at
all where the value
of the function at this point
is it only
matters what the limit from
the left hand side is.
And what the limit from the
right hand side is
because these two points
describe how large the
jump is.
OK.
I said before, I want to
work with these intervals
here because we know
from another video that
they form a so called semiring.
This is what I
explained to you in the video
about Carathéodory's
extension theory.
And now we can apply this
theorem to conclude
that we can extend this
definition to a
measure defined on the
full Borel sigma algebra
of R.
This means there is
exactly one measure
defined on
B(R)
to 0 infinity
with the property
that we have here.
So maybe let's call this
property here star and then
I can write star here.
Now it's useful to call this
uniquely given measure
again by
mu F.
And if we construct a measure
in this way, we call it a
Lebesgue Stieltjes measure.
And to be more concrete,
you call it the Lebesgue
Stieltjes measure for the
function F
here, you recognize how
strong Carathéodory's
extension theorem really
is.
You only have to find the
measure for the
intervals and then you get
exactly one measure
for all Borel sets out,
OK.
Now, you know how this
construction works.
And I would suggest that
we now look at examples.
An example means of course,
we choose a monotonically
increasing function capital
F and then we look
what is the associated Lebesgue Stieltjes
measure.
OK.
Maybe the easiest
example is the Lebesgue
measure itself.
For this, we choose
simply the
identity.
So the function FX
equals to X, then
we don't change the
normal measuring of
lengths of intervals.
So we get out
B minus A
as before.
Hence, we get out our
ordinary Lebesgue measure.
Another example of a
very easy
monotonically increasing
function would be a constant
function.
So let's choose FX is
equal to one
everywhere.
Obviously, in this case,
measuring the length of
intervals is very boring
because we subtract right
from left.
So we have here everywhere
zero.
Hence this is not so
surprising we get out
our zero measure.
OK.
Maybe more interesting would
be the case where we have
two values for the function.
So constant function, with
the exception of one jump,
for example, we could choose
zero if X is
less than zero and
one if X is
greater or equal than zero.
And please remember it does
not matter where the equality
sign is here.
The measure just doesn't
care about this.
The measure can't see this
point there.
Now, obviously, we have the
same result as before.
For all intervals that
lie completely to the left
of zero.
Or completely to the right
And we get out again, the
measure zero.
Hence, the interesting
cases would be where
zero is inside the
interval.
For example, let's look at
the interval minus
epsilon till
epsilon.
Of course, where epsilon
is a positive number.
Now, what do we get on the
right hand side, we have
one on left, we have zero.
So we have one minus
zero.
So we get out one.
And please note this holds
for all epsilon,
we already know a measure
that does this and this
is the Dirac measure at
zero.
Now, by the uniqueness result,
we know that the
extension has to be this
Dirac measure.
So you see we can use this
strong result very often.
Now for the end of the video,
let's look at a very general
example.
Therefore, let's choose a
general monotonically
increasing function F
but in addition, it should
also be continuously
differentiable both
things together.
Now means that the
derivative is
continuous and
also has values in the
non-negative
numbers.
On the other hand, F
itself is of course
continuous.
Therefore, there are no jumps.
This means that we don't
have the problem with the
left hand limit.
And the right hand limit
from before, for this
continuous function, we can
just use the values of the
function.
This means the length of
the interval is nothing
more than
FB minus
FA.
Now, if you learn calculus,
you should immediately recognize
this one here,
namely, here you can
apply the fundamental
theorem of calculus
which tells you this is
the integral of the
derivative of
F dX where
dx just denotes the normal
Lebesgue measure here.
OK.
And this is all we need
because you would believe
me that we can define a
new measure.
So for each Borel set
A, we define the
measure as this
integral.
Yeah.
So we send the Borel
set to this number
here.
This defines us a measure
on the Borel Sigma algebra
of R.
And now we apply the uniqueness
result of Carathéodory's
extension theorem.
And then we get out that
our measure mu F
looks exactly like this
one.
We know it looks like this
for all intervals
and therefore it should also
look like this for each Borel
set.
OK.
Here you see a very general
result for such
Lebesgue Stieltjes measures.
And this part here in the
integral is then often
called a density
function.
However, that's a thing we
could discuss in another
video later
here.
I really hope you learned
something today and that
you can apply these
results in other
applications.
If you see a monotonically
increasing function,
now you can
construct the Lebesgue Stieltjes
measure for this function.
Well, thank you for listening
and see you next time.
Bye.