Hello and welcome to a new
video about measure theory.
First, let me thank all the
nice people who support this
channel on Steady.
Today's video is about
Carathéodory's extension
theorem.
Okay, so this is a video
in my measure theory
series.
But you don't have to know
all the videos there
for understanding
Carathéodory's extension theorem.
It's sufficient when you
know what a measure is
and what a sigma algebra
is.
All the other notions we
need I will explain here
today.
So let's start immediately
with the theorem.
As always, we have a set
X and we also look at
subsets of the set
X.
So we look at a collection
of these subsets and we always
call this by this curved
A.
In general, this is not
a sigma algebra now, but
only a so called
semi ring.
To be more specific, I will
call it a semi ring of
sets.
Then you know that we are
talking about a collection
of sets.
The explicit definition of
a semi ring I will give you
later.
However, in the same way
as for the sigma algebras,
we also have a map
we call mu
defined on
the whole collection of subsets.
So on this semi ring
here, and it maps into
the non negative real
numbers where we
include infinity
as a symbol.
Okay.
In the case that A is not
a sigma algebra, this can't
be a measure.
And therefore there is another
name for such a thing.
We call it a pre
measure.
Of course, this name tells
you a lot.
It's a map that you
define before you can
define a real measure.
Okay, I will tell you more
about this later.
First let us focus on the
theorem here.
The first claim.
Obviously you have an
extension,
then mu
has an
extension
and we call this
extension by
mu tilde.
And indeed this is an
ordinary measure as we already
know it.
Therefore it really needs
a sigma algebra as
its domain.
So we call this
sigma of
A.
Please remember this one
is just a short notation
for the sigma algebra that
is generated by the
subsets that are elements
in A.
And of course we have to
land again in our
interval 0 to infinity,
where we include infinity.
Hence the claim of the theorem
is if you have these
things, you get out an
actual measure.
And extension now just
means that if you look at
the original subsets in
A, it does not matter if
you measure it with mu or
mu tilde.
So the new measure is
indeed bigger or better
than the pre measure before,
but you don't change the
original values.
Okay, so this was part
a, which tells you that
there is an extension.
So this is an existence
result.
However it would be also
Nice to have a uniqueness
result as well.
And this is what we will
have in part b.
Now however, we
need some additional condition
here.
This condition is often
called sigma
finite.
It means that you find a
sequence of subsets,
let's call them SJ
such that
SJ is in our
semi ring.
So in A
they should also cover the
whole set.
So the union
J starting with one
going to
infinity
is equal to
X.
And in addition, all the
sets should have
finite pre measure.
This means that if we put
the set into the function
mu, we get out a
finite number, so not
infinity here.
Now, if we have all these
things, then the
conclusion is that this
extension is also
unique.
Now this means that we can
summarize Carathéodory's
theorem in the following.
If we have a pre
measure that fulfills
this condition here,
then there is exactly
one extension
to the sigma
algebra that is generated
by this semi ring.
So exactly one
measure.
Moreover, this property
then also holds for
our mu tilde.
Mu tilde is also
sigma finite.
If you never heard this notion
sigma finite, that's not
a problem.
Definition is here and you
should recognize it's a
generalization of a finite
measure.
For a finite measure, the
measure of X would be
finite, and this then
still holds.
But if it's not finite,
then sigma finite
then tells you you can
approximate the whole
set with finite
measured sets
and you only need countable
many of them.
However, don't worry, you
will see in other videos
why this will be important
in future.
Well, there you have it.
This is Carathéodory's
extension theorem.
There may be other variants
of this theorem, but this
version is the one I
personally prefer.
Now, as promised, I give
you all the explanations
you need for the notions
here.
After this I give you
an example and also
an application of the
theorem.
But first, let's start with
the semi ring.
I called it a semi ring
of sets.
To remember you that we
consider a subset
in the power set of X.
Now we need three properties
such that we can call it
a semiring.
The first property is that
the empty set is in
all cases in the
collection.
If you remember the sigma
algebra, you recognize this
is the same thing we
want from a sigma algebra
at the beginning.
The second property is now
that we can form
intersections.
This means that the intersection
of two sets in A
lies also in
A.
Please also remember this
is indeed satisfied for sigma
algebras.
It's not in the definition,
but of course it follows
from the definition.
However, please note that
we don't say anything about
complements or unions
here.
So Indeed, we weaken the
notion of the sigma algebra
with the notion of a semi
ring.
But we have a third property
where you will see a little
bit of the unions and
complements.
It tells you that for arbitrary
elements AB
in A, you can
look at the difference
of the sets.
This one here is not the
complement because we don't
know if the set X is
inside our semi ring.
This does not follow from
the two properties here.
Nevertheless, we don't want
that this difference is again
in A.
We just want that we can
find a union of sets of
A that is given
as the difference here.
More concretely, this means
there are pairwise
disjoint
sets and let's call
them S1 till
SN, so finitely
many.
And they should lie in our
semi ring A such
that we can write this
difference as the
union of these
pairwise disjoint
sets.
And this is then what we
call a semi ring of
sets.
When you see this for the
first time, it may look a
little bit strange, but you
will see later that this
is exactly what we need
for getting some intuition
behind.
Maybe.
Let's look at an example
and I call this one the
most important example.
This one is an example in
R.
So the real number line
and we look at the finite
intervals given by
ab, where A
is inside the interval but
B is not.
And for having a good interval
I want A less or
equal than B.
Obviously this is not
a sigma algebra.
You can see this immediately
because only the finite
intervals are A.
In particular, R
itself is not in
A.
But we have to note
that A generates a
well known sigma algebra
and this one is the Borel
sigma algebra.
So we can write in short,
sigma of A
is equal to
Borel sigma algebra
of R.
This means that if we want
to describe the Borel sigma
algebra, it is sufficient
to use these finite
intervals.
And the beautiful thing now
is they form a semi
ring, which
means they can help us with
Carathéodory's extension
theorem.
Ok, then let's check that.
So let's check the three
properties.
Of course the empty set
is not a problem, it's
formally given in this
definition, but of course
we always could put it in.
But here, for a equals b,
we have the empty set here
because there's no point
in the interval.
So let's look at the second
property here.
It's about the intersection.
So let's choose two intervals,
maybe ab
and also
cd.
Then it's easy to see what
the intersection is if you
just do a short
drawing.
So here's the first interval
a to b.
And maybe the second one
is now here.
So c to
d.
Hence if this is the positions
of the intervals, then we
immediately get out the empty
set.
And then you see, this is
in the case when
b is less or equal than
c.
Or the other way around,
if d is less
or equal than a.
Of course this is not so
exciting.
So maybe more
interesting would be if
the interval is
inside the other interval.
So maybe we shift
that around.
So there we
have it.
Now what comes out here is
the interval that starts
with c and ends with
b.
So let's put that in here.
So I have c to
b exactly in the
case when my c
lies inside
interval ab,
but d not.
So I could write it in this
way.
Now you believe me that you
get out the same or a similar
result if you look at the
symmetric case, so where
the blue interval is on the
right and the green intervals
on the left, so no problem
there.
And that you also get such
an interval out if the interval
lies completely inside the
other one.
Therefore I don't write this
down.
You note that we
always get out
such an interval.
So an interval in A.
So also this property
holds and
one holds.
This means that we now have
to check property three,
the difference property.
Here we look now at
ab
without the set
cd.
Again here let's look at
some cases.
So maybe the first one from
before, where there's no
intersection.
Okay, then the difference
is clear.
We don't subtract anything.
The ab interval
remains.
Now in this case
from here, you see, this
is the intersection.
So what remains is the
interval from a to
c.
So let's write this down
a to c, but c
is not included.
Okay, maybe we can ignore
the other symmetric case.
So when the blue interval
is on the right, then of
course this interval would
remain the right hand side.
More interesting would be
now another case
where cd is
inside ab.
Of course for the intersection
this was very boring.
But now something happens
here.
Hence we subtract the middle
part here.
So what remains
is this part
and this part.
In other words, this is a
union of two
intervals, namely
a to c
union with the
interval d
to b.
But this is okay for a
semi ring.
We know we can have a union
out of elements out
of A.
Okay, ignoring
renaming of the letters
here, we know these are all
the cases that can happen
and therefore we are safe.
This is a semi ring.
Okay, I hope this helped
you a little bit about semi
rings.
And now we can talk about
the next notion, which is
the pre measure
a premeasure is almost
a measure.
That's the idea.
But it's not defined on a
sigma algebra, but just
on such a semi ring
A.
Ignoring this fact, the
definition looks almost the
same, which means we have
two conditions.
And the first one is that
the pre measure of the empty
set as
the measure of the empty
set should always be
zero.
And the second property
was the sigma
additivity.
This is what we can write
as mu
of a union,
a countable union.
So J from 1
to infinity of
sets AJ is
equal to a
series which starts
also with 1 and goes
to infinity, where we have
inside the three measures
of AJ.
Now what we need are
sets AJ
from our curved
A.
So from our semi ring.
Of course, otherwise this
does not make sense
and there should be disjoint,
which means
AI intersected
with aj
is the empty set
for
I not equal
j.
Okay, so this was the definition
or the sigma additivity for
an ordinary measure.
However, here it can't be
true, because we
have here the union
of sets out of
A.
For sigma algebra this is
not a problem, because in
the definition of a sigma
algebra we already know
this is also in A.
However, for semi ring we
don't know this.
We don't know if this union
is inside A as well.
But we need this if we want
to put this one into the
map mu and
therefore we have to add
this condition here.
So we add that
the union here
is also
in A.
This means you should read
(b) in this way for all
sets AJ where this
one and this one is
fulfilled, this one
here is also
satisfied.
And then we can call the
map mu a pre
measure.
Now, for the end of this
video, I want to give you
an important application
of Carathéodory's
extension theorem.
We have already seen
that the finite
intervals defined
as ab
where b is
excluded form
a semi ring of
sets.
Now we have no problem
defining a pre measure,
namely one that is defined
on this finite
intervals.
What we can do is look at
the length of the interval,
which means our pre measure
is defined as the
difference between b
and a.
Now, it's not hard to see
that this is indeed a pre
measure.
By this definition, you can
immediately check these two
properties here.
And now we can apply
Carathéodory's
extension theorem
and know that there is
exactly one
extension for this
premeasure.
And this measure now
lives on the sigma
algebra that is generated
by A, so generated by
the finite intervals here.
And we already know the sigma
algebra.
It's the Borel sigma
Indeed, this is the measure
that one knows as the
Lebesgue measure.
And here you see why
Carathéodory's
theorem is so
important.
Because the Lebesgue measure
is so important.
And now by proving this
extension theorem, we prove
the existence and the uniqueness
of the Lebesgue measure.
Okay, there we have
it.
This was
Carathéodory's extension
theorem.
I really hope that this
helped you a little bit understanding
it.
Of course, in other videos
in future
applications for this
theorem will follow.
And maybe we also talk about
the proof later
then thank you very much
for listening and see you
next time.
Bye.