Hello and welcome back to
a new video about measure
theory.
And first, I want to thank
all the nice supporters on
Steady
extending the last video.
I want to show you here an
example of Cavalieri's
principle.
This should be a comprehensible
example.
And therefore we focus on
the normal volume in
R three.
The typical example can look
like this, calculate the
volume of the pyramid with
the following corners.
The word volume here
means the Lebesgue measure
on R³.
And what you also learned
in the last video is that
you get this Lebesgue measure
in R three by a
product measure construction
starting with the Lebesgue measure
in R.
However, before we talk about
this, let's start by
visualizing the pyramid with
a short sketch
Here,
it's not hard to see that
exactly this point
(0,0,1) is
the top of the pyramid and
all the other points
form the base, the
square of the pyramid.
In a formal way, the pyramid
is given as a subset.
And let's call it K
in R three.
By looking at our sketch,
we are able to write
down a formal definition
of this set K.
It's the set of all the points
xyz in
R three with the
following conditions.
The first thing we see immediately
is that Z lies
between zero and one.
So we can write
zero less or equal
than Z less or equal
than one.
You can also see that the
possible values for X and
Y depend
on this X.
Now, if you think about it,
which functions describe
these planes here, then you
find that the short
formulation is given by the
absolute value is less or
equal than one minus set.
And the same for
Y
OK.
I think here also another
visualization is appropriate.
Let's look at the pyramid
from the top.
Then we can see what happens
to the X and Y values.
And for the Z value, we use
different colours.
For example, here we have
the square of the bottom
which corresponds to the
Z value equals to
zero.
This is what we call a level
curve.
However, if you look at an
actual mountain and a map,
you would call it a contour
line.
Now we can do this for different
levels.
For example, z
equals
1/4 would be
this line here or this
square and Z
equals to one half
would be this square.
And in this picture at the
top of the pyramid is
just this point which
corresponds to Z equals
one, this
nice picture now
shows us what to do
because we know how to
calculate the measure of
these squares here, which
means the area of the
squares.
And then Cavalieri's
principle tells us that
we have to integrate
all these
measures to get
the volume of the permit
here.
Or in other words, if we
call our Lebesgue measure
in our three mu,
then we can use our product
measure construction to
write it as the product measure
of MU one and mu
two.
Here mu one is the,
the Lebesgue measure on R
which means the z
coordinate.
And mu two is still a back
measure on R two, which
means the X and Y
coordinate together.
At this point, we can use
Cavalieri's principle
which tells us that the
volume of the pyramid, which
means mu of
K is
equal to the
integral over
R.
This is the space where Mu
one lives on.
So we will integrate with
respect to Mu one
and we integrate the measures
of these squares, which
means mu
two of the
squares and we call them
M with index Z
zero.
And therefore we integrate
over the variable Z
zero.
Now, if you go back to the
last video where I explained
Cavalieri's principle, you
see that MZ
zero are sets
that are defined in the
space where mu two lives.
In this means
in this case, we only have
now points with two
variables X and
Y in R two.
These are the sections through
the pyramid where z is
fixed as z zero.
Therefore, we only have these
two conditions here with
z zero on the right.
And this defines, then
our MZ zero.
Now, you should recognize
these are exactly the
squares from before.
Hence, it's no problem for
us to calculate the area
of such a square,
the length of one side is
given by two times
one minus z zero.
This is exactly the length
we have in the X direction.
And of course, it's the same
in the Y direction.
Therefore, we can write this
as a square.
Obviously, this only makes
sense if our z
zero is chosen
between zero and one.
So it lies in interval
0 to 1.
Of course, this is given
in the definition of the
pyramid.
A point lies only in the
pyramid if the Z value
lies between zero and one.
And this is also how we should
read this equality
here.
It only makes sense for Z
between zero and one.
Otherwise we should define
M zero Z zero as
the empty set.
OK.
So no confusion here.
What you usually would do
is just write down
the integral restricted to
the interval
01.
And then we can copy the
function here which is
four times one
minus Z zero
squared
and here d mu 1
Z zero.
Because this is just a
normal one dimensional
integral with respect to
the Lebesgue measure, we can
use a shorter notation.
We write the integral from
0 to 1 copy
again the function.
And then we omit the measure
D mu one and just write
DZ zero
to calculate this integral.
You just need an antiderivative,
which means here four
times.
And here we have
minus
1/3
and one minus
zero to the power of
three.
And the limits are
zero and one,
the upper part gives you
zero.
And the lower part here zero
here gives you
minus and minus.
So plus
4/3.
And that's how you apply
Cavalieri's principle.
To calculate the volume
of some body,
you just look at it and then
you think about how to
section it such that you
get out an integral that
you can solve a
good exercise would be now
to do exactly the same
thing and to
calculate the volume of
the sphere in R³.
So please try this and
after that, you are prepared
to use Cavalieri's principle
also in other
situations.
Well then thanks for
listening and see you next
time.
Bye.