Hello and welcome back to
new video about measure
theory.
And as always, I want to
thank all the nice people
that support this channel
on Steady.
In this,
and in the next videos I
want to talk about so called
outer measures.
And with this topic, we come
back to the foundations of
measure theory.
In fact, after using Carathéodory
extension theorem, many
times, I now want to
actually prove it. In
order to do that,
we need some suitable tools
and we find out that the
outer measures are indeed
these important tools.
For this reason, I can tell
you that for understanding
the idea of measure theory,
you don't really need the
outer measures at all.
But if you want to go into
the technical details and
maybe prove such an important
theorem here, then you can't
avoid the outer measures.
The name comes from the circumstance
that one wants to approximate
a set from the outside.
But we will talk about this
later.
However, in this context,
I should emphasize that both
words here are connected.
Outer measure is indeed a
new notion.
What I want to tell you here
is that "outer" is
not an attribute for
measure. In
particular,
it's important to note that
outer measures don't have
to be measures in the
usual sense.
With this heads up at the
beginning, I can however
reassure you that the
construction of such outer
measures is not so complicated
at all.
Basically, I would say it's
even easier than for the
usual measures we had before
because we don't need a Sigma
algebra at the beginning.
OK.
I don't want to keep you
in suspense any longer,
and therefore I present now
the definition.
Not so surprising,
also an outer measure is
first of all just a
map defined
on some subsets
of a chosen fixed set
X.
Indeed admissible are now
all subsets of X,
and, therefore, we can choose
the power set.
And for the values we are
already used to choose the
non-negative numbers where
we include the symbol
infinity.
Now, such a map which I
now denote by Phi
to distinguish it from a
normal measure, which we
would denote by mu is
called an outer measure if
the following three conditions
are fulfilled.
So please don't forget that
we always want to generalize
or abstract how the
normal measuring of volumes
in space would work.
Therefore, we would never
demand any crazy
properties from this function
phi here.
Hence the first property
you already know if we put
in the empty set in the map,
we must get out zero.
The empty set should not
have any volume.
Also the next property makes
sense
in this picture. If we look
at a subset A of
another set B
and maybe we visualize that
first here in the picture.
So we have to set X, we have
a subset B inside of the
set and there are
also a subset A
inside of B.
What does this mean for the
volumes?
Of course, the volume of
A should be smaller or in
the best case, the same as
the volume of B.
So we have here less or
equal.
And that is what we call
the monotonicity of the outer
measure.
Please note this property
we also had for an ordinary
measure.
It was just something we
didn't demand in the definition
because it followed from
the other properties.
And now the third property
is something you might also
recognize.
Let's take a sequence of
subsets,
so let's call them A
one, A two and so on
from the power set
of X.
And for this sequence then
holds that the union
measured with our map
phi
is smaller or equal
than when we add up
all the volumes
separately.
This is now something that
we also can easily
visualize in this picture
here.
So if we form the union
of both A one and A
two, well, we
calculate the area here
which is of course
smaller than
adding the volume or the
area here for A one
plus the area of A
two simply because
we add this intersection
two times.
You see, we don't need
disjoint sets here, which means
we can have intersections
and they occur on the right
hand side.
So in general, we will
have an inequality in
general here.
And because we have it for
countable many subsets,
you see, we have an index
in the natural numbers N.
here, we call it the
sigma-subadditivity.
And that is all we need to
get an outer measure.
When you see these properties,
you might think this is
indeed a good substitution
or abstraction for
measuring normal volumes.
However, you already know
that this can't work for
the whole power set if you
consider the important Lebesgue
measure.
And you also see here in
part C that we don't have
the equality if we consider
pairwise disjoint sets
something we usually call
Sigma additivity.
Hence a natural question
here is if I start
with an outer measure, Phi,
how do I get an ordinary
measure mu?
Or in other words, how do
I get also for the map
Phi the Sigma additivity?
And we already know this
won't work for the whole
power set.
Therefore, the first thing
we should do is to
restrict the sets we
consider.
And this leads us to our
next definition,
we only want to look at some
good sets that we
can measure.
And in the end, they will
form a Sigma algebra again.
And the name for such a
good set
is phi-
measurable.
And we use that name
if for all other
subsets.
And now I choose to letter
Q for another subset,
we have the following add
activity rule.
The best thing is again to
visualize that in a picture.
So there's a set A and
here's another set Q.
Now the set A splits
this set Q into two
parts, the one
inside A and the
other one outside
A.
Or by using formulas, here
we have the inner part and
here we have the part outside
A and now we
measure both sets by
using our map phi
and add them up.
And now we would say this
measurement is meaningful
if we get out the measure
of Q.
Again, this
means that we call a set
a phi-
measurable if it's so
good that it divides
every other set Q
into two parts such
that there our map
phi is indeed additive.
Obviously, this is the first
step to the Sigma additivity
we want.
Now, what I really should
add here is that in some
books, you might find the
definition as
greater and equal.
The reason for that is that
it does not make any difference
at all because for an outer
measure, you have the other
inequality here in the
definition.
Hence, you could define it
in this weaker sense.
But still, it means the same
thing.
Well, let's end this video
with some cliffhanger.
But of course, I will go
into more detail in the next
video.
The important proposition
here is written in the following
way, if we have an
outer measure on the
set X,
then the collection of all
these good sets here.
And let's call them A
with index Phi
forms a Sigma
algebra.
Of course, that makes our
good sets even better
because this is the first
part we need for our measure.
In fact, if we define a map
mu on the
Sigma algebra A phi
and how can we define it
very easily?
We just use our Phi
from before.
So we have mu
of A is the same
thing as putting A into
phi and what
comes out is a beautiful
measure.
So you see this is
indeed a very nice
result.
And then in the next video,
I will show you some examples
of outer measures and then
you will see that it's not
hard at all to construct
them.
In addition, this proposition
then will help us to get
out an ordinary measure as
we want.
And of course, if you're
interested, we will also
prove this proposition.
OK.
Thank you for listening and
see you next time.
Bye.