Hello and welcome back to
measure theory.
And as always, first, I want
to thank all the nice supporters
on Steady or paypal.
Now, in today's part three
about outer measures, we
will fill in some details
of a proof.
From the first video
there, please recall,
we've discussed an important
proposition.
The proposition tells us
that each outer measure
phi can be transformed
into an ordinary measure.
More concretely, we have
two parts.
The first part A tells
us what the corresponding
Sigma algebra A Phi
is.
In fact, it turns out when
we consider all subsets
A in X that are phi
measurable, we get a Sigma
algebra.
Of course, you know this
is the first ingredient we
need for an ordinary measure.
And exactly this one we call
mu in part B.
Now the domain of mu is given
by our new Sigma algebra.
And the definition is given
by the outer measure Phi.
In other words, Mu of
A is given by Phi of
A.
And then the claim is this
is now a normal measure.
OK.
There you see this is a nice
proposition we already
introduced in part one.
Therefore, now in this part
I want to give you the ideas
for the proof.
This means that for the first
part, we have to verify all
the properties of a Sigma
algebra.
These are essentially three
things.
First, the empty
set and X should be in
a phi.
Then the collection of sets
should be closed under the
complement and
closed under countable
unions.
Hence, I would suggest we
start with the simplest one
checking if the empty set
is in a Phi.
So by definition, this means
is the empty set phi
measurable.
So I think this is a good
point, refreshing your memory.
What phi measurable actually
means a subset
A is called phi
measurable.
If it fulfills the following
relation, namely
if a decomposes every
other set Q into two
parts such that we have this
additive for Phi.
Now, in the case that A is
the empty set, we see this
relation immediately
because the first part is
just the empty set again.
And the second part is just
Q.
Of course, you see these
intersections are not hard
at all.
And then we just need the
fact that an outer measure
sends the empty set to zero.
Hence, the whole first part
is just zero.
And the relation holds
and there you see one property
for the Sigma algebra is
already satisfied.
Then the next question would
be, can we do the same for
the whole space X?
So again, we have the question
is the whole space X phi
measurable.
And to answer that we have
to take the relation again
for every set Q.
But now we put in X
and there you see this looks
very similarly because the
complement of the whole space
is of course the empty set
again.
So you see this is exactly
the same as before.
Just the two terms in the
sum have switched roles.
Hence, we can also conclude
X is phi measurable.
OK.
With this, let's go to the
next property of a Sigma
algebra, namely the
question is, is the whole
collection of subsets closed
under complements.
Hence, we start with one
subset A that is phi
measurable.
Then in the end of course,
we want to conclude that
the complement of A lies
also in a phi
indeed how this proof works.
You might have already seen
above when we considered the
empty set.
And the complement X
of course, we need to do
it in a similar way because
we only have this relation
to work with here.
Please always keep in mind
I don't write it down this
relation holds for every
subset Q OK.
Then let's do what we have
done above.
Let's exchange the two terms
in the sum.
In fact, this is almost what
we want to have for the relation
of AC.
In the first part, we already
have AC.
And in the second part, we
need the complement of AC.
However, this is already
given simply because the
complement of the complement
is the original set again.
OK.
Now here when you look at
the left hand side and the
right hand side, you see
this is exactly the definition
for ac being phi
measurable.
Hence, we see the second
part for the Sigma algebra
is also fulfilled.
So only the hardest one
remains to show.
And here is as you can see
the property that the Sigma
algebra is close under
countable unions.
And we know this is related
to the Sigma additive of
the corresponding measure
mu.
Therefore, both things in
the proof will go hand in
hand.
However, before we do this,
we first should show that
our A phi is
indeed closed under a
finite union,
which means we have to consider
two sets.
So we choose a one and a
two from our A Phi.
And then we show that the
union of both sets lies
also in a phi
as before.
This simply means we have
to show that this property
here holds for every set
Q.
Therefore, we already know
our goal here.
So let's put this to the
bottom.
Then here, please
also recall it's
sufficient by the definition
of an outer measure to show
the one inequality here.
OK.
Then I would say let's start
bringing the two properties
for a one and a two together.
First, let's apply it
to a one.
Then in order to bring a
two in, let's call the second
part here Q tilde.
Hence, there, we now can
apply the property for A
two.
But now instead of Q for
Q tilde, which means we
don't change the first part.
But then we have two more
terms which look
like Phi of Q tilde
intersected with a two
plus the same with the
complement.
However, remember in
the end, we only want two
terms.
Hence the overall idea now
is that we put the first
two terms here together.
And in fact, we are allowed
to do this using the Sigma
sub additive of the
outer measure Phi.
However, this now means
we get an inequality in
this is simply the sub in
subadditivity.
And the rest of the property
tells us that instead of
the plus we have a union
inside of Phi,
OK.
Here you can see our result,
we have two terms for Phi.
Now in the one, we
find a one and a two
and in the other one, we
find the complement of both
sets.
So it seems like this is
almost the thing we
want.
Indeed.
The second part we immediately
recognize as the correct
one simply because Q
tilde was defined as
Q intersected with a
one complement.
In other words, we can write
it like this.
And then when we pull out
the complement, we find the
union, OK?
Very good.
This is exactly the term
we wanted.
Now looking at the first
part, it looks more complicated.
However, we can also transform
it to this.
And maybe we just verify
this with a Venn diagram.
This works because we have
exactly three sets involved
Q A one and A two.
OK.
Then let's start with Q
intersected A one.
This intersection you see
we simply find here
and now the other intersection
is an intersection with three
sets.
First we have Q
then a one complement and
then a two and
then it's not hard to see
that this is exactly this
small part here.
OK.
And then you see this Venn
diagram explains exactly
this intersection here.
Hence the proof of the unit
with two sets is indeed
finished.
The union A one with a
two is also in a
phi.
OK.
Then we can go to the next
part where we have to consider
countably many sets.
Hence here we need the whole
sequence of subsets A
one A two and so on.
They all should come from
a Phi.
And then the question is,
is the union from J is
equal to one to
infinity or it's an
element in a phi
for this, we want to find
a positive answer.
Hence, for the rest of the
proof, it might be helpful
to give this union a shorter
name.
So let's simply call it a.
Now, I can tell you instead
of taking an arbitrary sequence
of sets here, we can take
a pairwise disjoint one.
This is possible because
we have already proven the
closeness with respect to
the normal union and also
the closeness with respect
to the complement.
Therefore, we can simply
do this.
But it also has the big
advantage that we immediately
get this sigma additivity
for the measure mu in the
end.
Because in order to show
this, you know, we need to
consider pairwise disjoint
sets.
Hence, in summary, it's indeed
helpful to do the proof like
this.
Of course, here at the start
of the proof, it might not
surprise you that again,
we use the property, the
outer measure gives us.
However, here I want to put
in a special set
Q first, we could
have any set.
So let's simply call it Q
hat.
And then we put in the
intersection of a
one in the union with a
two.
And here please keep in mind
a one and A two are
disjoint.
This fact will help us on
the right hand side when
we put in the same set for
the set Q.
For example, in the first
part, you see the intersection
with a one here will completely
cancel out A two.
Therefore, the first part
is just Q head intersected
with a one.
Then in the second part,
because we have the complement
of a one, this will completely
cancel out a one itself.
So we simply have phi of
Q head intersected with A
two.
OK.
So you should see this is
a nice trick to get the union
on the left hand side.
And the sum on the right
hand side, hence, the
next step would be to do
an induction to get
finitely many sets in.
So the induction shows we
have Phi of Q hat
intersected with a
finite union.
So you see this whole thing
here is simply the left hand
side and then the
right hand side is given
by a sum.
Of course, also from J is
equal to one to N.
And inside we have Phi of
Q hat intersected with
AJ.
OK.
So this is a nice result
which holds for every N.
So we should give it a name,
let's call it star.
Now let's go one step back
and recall what we already
know.
Namely, we know that this
unit here is by our proof
above all
element in A five.
So we don't have the infinite
union yet in a Phi but
we are getting closer
because when we know that
this is an API we can use
the property as always the
proper for the outer measure.
So this works as before.
But now instead of Q, we
use Q hat and instead of
our A, we have here the union
of the AJ.
Now, for the first part,
you should see we can use
our star property to
rewrite that as a sum.
So you see with each step,
we are getting closer and
closer to the Sigma
additivity.
OK.
Then for the second part
here we use something we
didn't use before.
But where we know it holds
for an outer measure,
indeed, it's the second
property and outer measure
has the monotonicity.
We can use that here because
when we increase the index
and here this whole set
here would get smaller.
Therefore, we can also do
it for end to infinity,
then we have the infinite
union, which we simply called
A.
So the second part is greater
or equal than Phi of
Q hat intersected with
AC OK.
With this, we now have something
where there is no index and
in a union anymore.
Indeed, we have here an
inequality that holds for
all natural numbers.
And therefore this
inequality also holds the
limit and to infinity.
Hence, Phi of Q head
is create or equal.
Then the infinite sum
of Phi of Q hat
intersected with AJ
plus the second term Phi
of Q hat intersected with
AC.
So here you see we have an
infinite sum and remember
we want to show the Sigma
additivity but
also don't forget for
Phi, we already have the
Sigma subadditivityv.
And indeed, this is what
we should use here, which
means we get an inequality
when we substitute the infinite
sum with an infinite union
inside Phi.
However, this infinite union
already has a name.
We called it A at the beginning.
And in fact, with this last
step, the inequality now
looks very short and
we can make it even shorter
by using the Sigma sub edit
tity again, which
means the sum here now
goes to a union inside
Phi.
However, because we have
a and the complement of a,
just Q hat remains.
And now, maybe surprisingly,
on the right hand side, we
have the same thing as on
the left hand side, which
means for all the inequalities
here that we actually have
equalities in
particular we get because
this whole equality holds
no matter which subset Q
had we choose the defining
property for a being an
A Phi.
Please recall this was our
goal all along because
it shows now that a Phi
is indeed a Sigma algebra.
In fact, we have also proven
part B in the proposition
because this equality
gives us the sigma additivity
for our measure.
You see this because Q hat
can be any set in
particular, it could be a
itself and then we
have measure of the infinite
union is equal to the
infinite sum.
OK.
So here you see we have everything
this closes the proof.
Now with this nice proven
result, we are way closer
to be able to prove the
famous Carathéodory's
extension theorem.
And maybe we do this
in the next video.
Therefore, I hope I see you
there and have a nice day.
Bye.