Hello and welcome to this
video about linear algebra.
And as always many, many
thanks to all the nice people
that support me on Steady
or paypal.
If you want a PDF version
of this video, the link is
in the description. Today's
topic is the so-called
plu decomposition
for matrices.
You can see this as a supplemental
video if you have already
watched my video about the
LU decomposition.
In other words, this is just
a generalization.
However, L still stands for
a lower triangular matrix.
Hence it's always a square
matrix but
U in general is not a
square matrix because it
always needs to be of the
same size as the original
matrix we want to decompose.
So what we want to get out
here is this so-called row
echelon form.
Please note for a square
matrix, this would be an
upper triangular matrix.
So we still denote it by
U.
And the last ingredient we
have here is the matrix P
which saves all the row
exchanges we have to do.
Therefore, this is what we
call a permutation matrix.
OK.
Now you know the three parts
of the decomposition.
So let's calculate them for
an example, I want the
matrix A to be a four times
five matrix
there we have it.
This is the matrix I have
chosen for today.
Now, if you want to start
here with your common LU
decomposition, you immediately
find the problem.
You can't use the zero as
a pivot to eliminate all
the other numbers in the
first column.
Hence, the first step you
need to do is to go through
the column to find a nonzero
element to use as a pivot.
OK.
We find it in the *second* row.
Therefore, we need to exchange
the first and the second
row.
Now a permutation matrix
that exchanges row one with
row two looks like this.
It's simply a four times
four identity matrix where
we flip the two rows, we're
interested in an important
property is now if we square
that matrix, we get out our
identity matrix.
Hence, this is our first
step.
We just apply the identity
matrix on the left.
Then in the next step, we
multiply one of the two
matrices to the right, which
means we exchange the two
rows here.
Afterwards, we have our pivot
at the correct position.
This means that we now can
put the L matrix into the
game.
It should be a four times
four matrix.
So we start as usual with
the identity matrix.
And now we have to do the
Gaussian elimination in the
first column.
So we want to generate zeros
below the pivot which means
that we are already finished
here.
In other words, second row
minus zero (times) the first
row. And the zero
then goes into the L matrix.
So this was easy.
So let's go to the next number
which is two.
So third row minus
two times the first row
and the multiple we subtract
is the number that goes into
the L matrix.
Also not so hard.
The only number that changes
is the five that gets to
a three.
And the last number in the
column is the one.
So we subtract one.
And as before, this is the
number that goes into the
L matrix.
And with that, we are finished
with the first Gaussian elimination.
Then in the next step, we
go to the next column and
choose the next pivot.
And we see it's nonzero.
So we don't need any row
exchanges here.
Otherwise we do the same
as before we generate
zeros below the pivot.
In the first step, we just
have to subtract one.
And as before this one goes
immediately to our L matrix.
On the other side, we get
a lot of zeros and one
here.
And then in the next step,
we have to subtract two times
the second row.
This too then goes as
always into the L matrix.
And with that calculation,
we are finished with the
second column, let's go to
the third column.
OK.
So this is not a pivot,
but this is also not a pivot.
So there are no pivots in
the third column.
This means that this column
is finished, we have to go
to the next column.
However, there we also find
a zero which is not a pivot,
but there is another pivot
below.
And with that, we know what
to do, we have to do a row
exchange.
In order to do that, we will
insert the identity matrix
again.
So this is again a permutation
matrix squared where we have
now the permutation matrix,
third row to
fourth row, of
course, one of them, we can
apply to the right hand side
again to get our row exchange.
Indeed, there we get what
we want.
Now we have to pivot at the
correct position.
However, the permutation
matrix is not at the correct
position yet.
We need that on the left
hand side.
Therefore, in the next step,
we will also add the identity
matrix on the left hand side.
So here again, we have the
permutation matrix squared.
Now, you know, when we apply
this matrix to the right,
we will exchange these two
rows here.
However, if we apply this
matrix to the left, we will
exchange the corresponding
columns.
Nevertheless, this is exactly
what we do in the next step.
First exchanging the
rows looks like this.
And afterwards, we exchanged
the columns which
results in this
matrix.
The good thing is you see
we get again a lower
triangular matrix
but don't oversee that this
really changes the matrix
L from before.
The good thing is you can
remember the whole operation
by just doing the row
exchange in the blue part
here.
However, of course, now you
have seen where it really
comes from.
OK.
Now that everything is in
the right order, we can continue
our procedure.
This means that we want to
generate a zero here, but
it's already there, which
means that we are finished
with this column in the
next column, we then find
the pivot which is here,
but we don't have to generate
zeros anymore.
Indeed, this was our last
step in the whole calculation.
We have found the row echelon
form here on the right hand
side.
OK.
So there we have our matrix
U.
And this is our matrix
L and the
last part is what we still
can multiply.
But then we get our matrix
P.
We've reached our goal.
Our matrix A from the beginning
is given as P times
L times U and
therefore we call this the
PLU decomposition.
OK?
I think that's good enough
for this example.
I hope you can now apply
the whole procedure to another
matrix A and with
that, thanks for listening
and see you next time.
Bye.