Hello and welcome back to
start learning logic.
Now with part two.
And first, I want to thank
all the nice people on Steady
or paypal who support this
channel.
Now to refresh your memory.
Last time we learned the
meaning of logical statements
and we used the names A and
B to denote them.
And then we have seen that
we can formulate new logical
statements with the negation
and the conjunction.
These two new symbols, we
called logical operations.
And this one was the not
operation and this one, the
and operation.
Now, if you have such a formula
with logical operations,
the original statements A
and B are often just
called logical variables
in this case.
So you see we have a lot
of vocabulary which is in
the end, maybe not so
important.
The important thing will
be that you understand all
the symbols we use.
OK.
Then let's continue introducing
more symbols with logical
operations.
The next one is the so called
disjunction also defined
for two logical statements
A and B.
And it's similar to the end
operation here because it's
the or operation,
the symbol we use here is
the flipped one.
So just a V
as in the last video, we
can define the symbol by
writing down the truth table.
The disjunction should be
two when at least one of
the two constituents is two.
So we have two here, two
here.
And also the first line because
both of them are two and
we don't have an exclusive
or here.
However, when both of them
are false, we have a false
similar to the conjunction.
You can also visualize this
with a circuit and a lamp.
In this case, the two switches
just have to be parallel.
Now having these logical
operations, we can combine
them in a lot of ways to
get out new logical statements.
Therefore, the natural thing
to do is writing down a truth
table for such a new
combination.
So let's consider a simple
example here.
What about not A
or a?
You see what we usually assume
is that the NOT operator
binds closest.
Therefore, we don't need
any parentheses here.
Now, in this example, our
combination just has one
logic variable which means
our truth table just needs
two rows.
OK?
So let's fill that in.
We know that not just flips
the truth values and
now the or just needs one
true.
So we have the true here and
the true here.
Now you see this
combination always gets you
a true statement out no
matter what the truth value
of the input A was.
In logic, we call such a
thing a tautology.
So it's a combination of
logical operations and logical
variables that is always
true no matter what the truth
values are of the logical
variables that are contained
in the formula.
Of course, this was a simple
example.
You could have many different
logical variables in the
formula.
But then the truth table
would be much bigger.
Of course, knowing which
combinations are tautologies is
very helpful because you
always can substitute this
combination.
Then with just a true
now related to that is the
notion of logical
equivalence.
It also tells you when you
can substitute one formula
with another, we
call two logical statements.
So combinations as we had
before, logically
equivalent, if the truth
table looks the same for
both more
concretely, you have to look
at all possible assignments
of truth values for the logical
variables that are included
in both formulas.
And if you get the same output
for both formulas, we call
them logically equivalent.
OK?
So it looks like a reasonable
term.
But to understand it, I think
we should look at an example
here.
I want to consider A or
B with a NOT in
front and
also not A
and not B.
So please keep in mind we
need parentheses here, but
not here.
But of course, if you want,
you are allowed to use them
here.
OK, then let's do a large
truth table.
Of course, we need here our
inputs A and B
and the outputs on the right
hand side.
Then in the next step, we
can fill in all possible
combinations of the truth
values of the logical
variables.
Afterwards, we have to think
what are good intermediate
steps to reach our result.
On the right hand side here.
For example, I would say
we calculate first A or
B for this, we
already know the truth table.
We have true true true
false.
And then we just have to
use the negation which
switches all the truth values.
So we have False False False
true.
So now we finish with the
first one.
And for the second one, I
would say we first write
down not A and afterwards
we write down not B
OK.
Filling this in was not so
hard because we already know
how to do this.
And now for the last step,
we have to use the and operator
in the first line, we have
false and false.
So this is false, then we
have false and two still
false.
Then we have two and false
still false.
And in the last line, we
have two and two, which is
two.
And there we have our result,
the truth values for both
combinations match
completely.
In other words, they are
logically equivalent.
And the symbol we use for
this is this double
arrow for
you.
This means if you have a
large formula as a logical
statement where you have
this part inside,
you can easily substitute
this with this one without
changing the truth value
and also the other way around.
So the logical equivalence
is what you can use to
simplify a complicated
expression step by step.
Of course, we will see examples
of this.
But first, I want to use
the next video to show you
more logical operations.
So I hope I see you there
and have a nice day.
Bye.