Hello and welcome to
start learning logic.
And as always, many thanks
to all the nice people that
support this channel on Steady
or paypal.
This is part one where I
want to show you the basic
stuff you need to know about
logic to understand
mathematics.
Therefore, we don't need
to go into the details of
the wide field of logic and
formal logic.
For us, it would be sufficient
to understand logical
statements and logical operations.
Since a lot of people can
correctly deal with the everyday
logic on an intuitive level,
this is often skipped when
you start with mathematics.
However, I think it's important
to see that we have the logic
as the foundation because
we need to define everything
in an unambiguous way in
mathematics.
Hence, for us, our starting
point would be logical
statements also called
propositions.
Now, such a proposition is
just a statement which means
a meaningful declarative
sentence that has a
well-defined truth value.
So it can be either a true
or a false statement.
Therefore, when you take
examples outside the
mathematical world, you have
to be careful what really
satisfies this condition
here.
So you can't take any opinions
or questions because a
question does not have a
well-defined truth value.
OK.
Then let's look at some examples
where you should always keep
in mind that we first have
to agree on some definitions
such that the examples make
sense.
So here Mars is a planet
is a logical statement.
When we know what object
we call Mars and what a
planet is by definition.
Then this logical statement
is indeed true.
In this way, we can also
formulate the sentence Pluto
is a planet which is by the
same agreement also a logical
statement.
However, this one now has
the truth value false.
So you see such real world
examples can really help
to understand the concepts.
But of course, they can lead
to some discussions.
Therefore, I prefer examples
in mathematics because they
are all definitions are given.
For example, we could choose
the sentence one plus
one is equal to two.
Of course, here you also
have to know what the numbers
mean, what the plus sign
means and what the equality
sign means.
But if you know these things,
you know, this is a true
logical statement.
Of course, such logical statements
coming from mathematics can
also be formulated with English
words.
For example, we could say
the number five is smaller
than the number two.
So here we need only knowledge
of the natural numbers and
how they are ordered.
Then you can say yes, this
is also a logical statement,
but it is false.
OK.
Then let's go to a counterexample.
What about good morning?
Of course, this seems very
nice, but we can't associate
a well-defined truth value
to it.
It simply does not make sense
to say that this one here
is true or that it is false.
So it's clearly not a logical
statement.
Another example now in the
mathematical world would
be to say I have a variable
X plus one and
this is equal to one.
So this might be a tricky
one because it's not a logical
statement.
Despite looking like one.
The reason for this is that
the variable X here is not
fixed.
So we can't give the statement
a well defined truth value
because it would depend what
X really is.
This means that in the moment
that X gets a value,
this statement becomes a
logical statement.
Of course, such constructions
are all over mathematics.
Therefore, they will be important
later and we call such a
thing a pretty kit.
Now, the next step is when
we have such logical statements,
we also want to combine them,
they are just called logical
operations and they give
us new logical statements.
For example, the negation
is defined for given
logical statement A which
could be, for example, one
plus one is equal to two.
Then the new logical statement,
the negation of A is denoted
by this line.
In front of A, you should
read it as not A and it
simply switches the truth
value.
Therefore, the best thing
to define such a logic operation
is to use a so called truth
table where we put in all
possible inputs and the
corresponding outcomes.
Of course, here we only have
two inputs.
A could be either true or
false.
So the truth value should
be switched.
So not a should be false
when A is true and the other
way around.
OK.
Also here let's look at some
examples to get an idea what
we are talking about.
So let's take the logical
statement A given by the
English sentence, the wine
bottle is full.
Then the negation of A is
simply given by putting in
the word not into the
sentence.
Of course, here we assume
that you know which wine
bottle we talk about and
what full means.
But then you see negation
is very easy just putting
in not at the correct position.
An important thing to note
here is that this is not
the same as saying the wine
bottle is empty.
In other words, negation
does not mean the complete
opposite.
It just means switching it
to values.
As another example, let's
consider the logical statement
A S two plus two
is equal to five,
then not A is of course two
plus two is not equal
to five.
Now, what you might think
is we just have to look at
the second line here because
we already know A is
false.
So not A should be just a
true statement.
However, that's not what
the negation does.
It considers both cases at
the same time.
This means that if we live
in a strange world where
this logical statement is
true, then the negation
here should also be
false.
Therefore, please always
consider these two possible
worlds, which means these
two lines here.
Then if you get the correct
truth table, you've found
the correct negation.
Besides the negation, we
have another fundamental
logic operation, which is
called the conjunction.
It combines two logical statements,
let's call them A and
B.
And then the conjunction
is defined by this wedge
symbol in between.
You should read it as A and
B because it's the end
operation, which means this
one is only true.
If A and B are
true simultaneously
with this information, you
are already able to write
down the whole truth table
which you would see as the
correct definition.
Now, instead of two rows,
we have four rows because
we have four possible combinations
of the two values of A and
B.
Now from bottom to top, you
know, this one is false because
we have at least one false
here, the same here
and the same here.
Everything's false except
the first row.
This one is true because
both are true.
A good visualization for
the and operation would be
to consider a circuit
with a lamp and a battery.
Now, what we can do is to
put A and B as
switches into the circuit.
In this picture, false should
mean off and true should
mean on and the
lamp we see is our output.
So here you see, we need
both switches to be on to
get an on output.
So true means true,
otherwise we are false.
OK.
In the next video I show
you other logical operations
that are also very important
in mathematics.
So I hope I see you there
and have a nice day.
Bye.