Hello and welcome to new
video series where I want
to show you an introduction
into the theory of
distributions
Here,
In part one, I want to start
with the motivation for this
new topic.
When you start with real
analysis, then you learn
a lot of important concepts.
For example, you learn what
a function is, you learn
what a limit is.
And most importantly, you
learn what a derivative is
with these objects, you can
already do a lot of
mathematics.
But in the end, you will
reach other fields for
example, differential
equations
for Fourier series
and even the Fourier
transform.
And now here the problems
begin because
for differential equations
also some solutions
with sharp turns are
interesting and important.
And there you already know
that the notion of a
derivative is in some
sense, too strong to
consider functions with sharp
turns because at a
sharp turn, the function
is not differentiable.
Therefore, we need something
new that can also deal with
such solutions.
So we would say we need
something that can deal with
more general solutions.
OK.
We will talk about this later
Here,
I want to start with an
example and indeed, it's
a very famous example.
It goes back to the year
and to Paul Dirac,
what he wanted was a derivative
of a function.
And we used letter H
because this function is
most of the time known as
the Heaviside function.
In spite of having this fancy
name, the function is indeed
very simple.
It is just zero on the
negative axis and
one on the positive
axis.
And now Dirac wanted
to have a derivative of this
function.
And you see this is no
problem at all outside
of zero.
But in zero, there is a
jump.
Hence, in the classical way,
we have a problem at this
one point.
Now Dirac wanted a more
general derivative and he
called this one the delta
function.
Now more general here means
of course, it is a
generalization of the
classical notion of a
derivative.
Hence, we can conclude that
this new delta function
has to be zero
outside of this
critical point X equals to
zero.
However, Dirac also
wanted that the fundamental
theorem of calculus still
holds for this new function
more concretely.
This means we can write
down for an arbitrarily
small epsilon
the following integral
which is just an
integration around zero
for a delta function.
But now we know this is the
derivative of the Heaviside
function.
So we can put in
the derivative of H here.
And now if the fundamental
theorem of calculus holds
for these functions here
we have of
epsilon
minus
H of minus epsilon.
Now, looking at the graph,
we recognize that this is
always one on the right hand
side and always zero
on the other side.
So we have one minus zero
or in other words, always
one.
Now this may look
nice, but we
already know that if we
have these two things together,
this delta can't be an
ordinary function.
Please recall.
This first part tells
us that delta
is zero
except for one
point.
So in our language, this
would mean delta
is zero almost
everywhere.
To be more concrete, I would
say this holds with
respect to the Lebesgue measure.
And from this, we can conclude
that every integral for
this function has to be
zero.
In particular, the integral
from before.
So minus epsilon to
epsilon of delta
X is also
zero for all epsilon,
which means it can't be
one as we wanted
before.
So here's our contradiction.
Now it gets even worse
because Dirac does not stop
there.
Dirac
also wants to calculate with
the derivatives of this new
delta function.
And now we see at this point,
we have to put a
meaning into the symbols
here.
In order to do this, we
will define a new
object and call this a
distribution.
And in the end, delta
will be such a distribution.
For the reasons you have
seen above, we want to
calculate as we have
ordinary functions, this
new notion distribution is
also often called a
generalized function.
The overall idea for
distributions is that we
see these objects as
densities.
So here you should
visualize a one
dimensional rode or
one dimensional bar
where we have a mass
density.
Now, in this picture, the
delta distribution or the
delta function would be a
singular density.
So a density where
all the mass is one
point.
OK.
So let's do a picture for
this visualization.
The curve of an ordinary
function may look like this.
Now you should see this as
the mass distribution
on this one dimensional rode
here.
And this means here
we have a high density
and at this point, we have
a low density.
Now for finding the
density in the real world,
you would use a measurement
device in
mathematics, we then use
so called test functions.
So functions phi that
should be nice enough.
So at least continuous and
localized in some sense
for me, that means they are
zero except for one
small bump.
And that's the region you
measure in.
Now, in order to find the
mass in that region, we have
to calculate an integral.
So an integral over
R function
f and function
Phi
here we get out a real number
which describes
our density
here in that region.
Yeah, roughly in that way.
And now the idea is that
we use a lot of these
small bumps.
So we get out a lot of real
numbers.
In other words, we have a
map that maps
all the phis to
these real numbers given
by the integral.
Or in other words, instead
of looking at the function
F itself, we can
just look at the collection
of all these real
numbers here.
Indeed, that is what we will
do in the next videos, we
will substitute the function
F with this linear
map.
Now, the big advantage of
this is of course, that
now we can also deal with
this strange delta function.
Obviously, we can't draw
a graph for this delta
function because it's not
an ordinary function.
However, we have our
visualization that it is
a point mass.
So this means it is zero
except for one point
and we have put that point
in zero.
So here we have a jump
and this jump should be
infinitely high.
So what does this mean?
Yeah, it means if you want
to measure with our test
functions, you get
out the value of the test
function at this one
point.
So this makes sense for our
measurement devices here.
And also for the integral
we have seen before for the
delta function.
Indeed, we generalize this
integral here.
So now we want to put in
a new function, delta
function instead of f
but we learn we can't see
that as a real integral.
What we have indeed is a
generalization of this
concept to this linear
map.
Well, I think that's good
enough for today.
So now you see the
motivation for
distributions.
And in the next video, I
will give the exact
definition of such a
distribution.
This means that we will learn
what the test functions are
actually and also
what this linear map then
is
then thank you very much
for listening and see you
next time.
Bye.