Hello and welcome back to
distributions.
And as always many, many
thanks to all the nice people
that support this channel
on Steady or paypal.
This is part five.
And today I want to talk
about so called regular
distributions.
However, before we do this,
I first want to show you
a useful characterization
for distributions.
Of course, you already know
a distribution is a linear
map T from the space of
test functions
to the real or complex numbers.
And you also know it has
to be continuous in the
sense as we define it.
In the last video, we
use sequences for this.
But there are also a lot
of other equivalent
characterizations for it.
Hence, we can write it in
the following way T is a
distribution if and only
if for all
compact sets in RN,
there exists a natural number
M which could be zero
and there exists a positive
constant C
such that for all test
functions, Phi
we have that if the
support of Phi
lies in the compact set
K, then this
implies that the value
T of Phi is
bounded from above,
namely we have the constant
C times the sum
over all multi indices
with degree less or equal
than the constant M.
And then we look at all the
derivatives of Phi in the
supremum norm.
Please note this means that
whenever you can write down
such an estimate, you immediately
have the continuity and therefore
you have a distribution T
since at first, it looks
complicated, we really should
write down a proof for it.
So let's start with this
direction.
So when we have the estimate,
what can we say about
continuity in
order to show this, let's
choose test functions Phi
K and Phi such that we have
our D convergence for the
sequence Phi K to
Phi, then we know by
definition there is a compact
or bounded set K in
RN such that the
support of all phi K
lies in this compact set
K.
And we also know that for
all multi indices alpha,
we have that the divers
D alpha Phi K
converge in the suprema
norm.
Please keep in mind this
was just the explanation
what the D-convergence here
means.
OK.
And now we just have to check
if T of Phi K is
convergent to T of Phi.
In other words, we want that
this term goes to zero.
When K goes to infinity.
By using the linearity, we
can rewrite that as T of
Phi K minus Phi.
Of course, we know this is
again a test function with
support at K.
So we know they exist in
M and in C such that this
estimate holds.
And there you see, we have
what we want because this
term goes to zero when K
goes to infinity.
And please don't forget we
have a finite sum here.
So this is all we needed
to show for the first part.
Now let's go from the left
hand side to the right hand
side.
Here, I want to do a proof
by contraposition.
So we start with the negation
of the right hand side.
This means that we just have
to exchange the quantifier.
So here we have, there exists
a compact set such that for
all M and all
C there exists a
test function phi
and the negation of the implication
is just that the support
is still in K.
But the inequality goes the
other way around this
means that we have a greater
sign here.
So this is our assumption
and where we want to get
to is that T is
not continuous.
Now, we call this whole thing
means there is a compact
set but then no matter
which M and C we choose,
we always find a corresponding
Phi.
Therefore, let's go through
all the natural numbers K
for C and M and take the
corresponding phi k.
This means that we have T
phi K greater than K
times the sum where we have
here.
The maximum order for the
derivatives as k
please don't forget the absolute
value around a multi
index just means that you
add up all the components.
So no matter how you combine
all the partial derivatives,
the maximum order you get
out is always key.
Also important to note is
that we have the zero multi
index as well in the sum,
which means we have the supremum
norm of Phi K here.
Now, the key idea of the
proof is that we define a
new test function Phi
K by scaling the
Phi case.
And of course, the correct
scaling factor is exactly
one over the absolute value
of T of Phi k
because we know it's increasing
with K and it increases
faster than the supremum
norm of Phi K.
Therefore, by this definition,
the psi K go
uniformly to the zero function
when K tends to infinity.
In fact, the whole argument
works for every multi index
which means we have the uniform
convergence for every
derivative
combining this with the supports
being all in K.
We have indeed the D
convergence.
However, now you might already
see the images under
T don't converge to
zero to see this.
Just look at the absolute
value of T of Phi
K
which is by the linearity
just one over the absolute
value of T of Phi
K times the absolute
K, which is of
course always one.
In other words, it does not
converge to zero.
Now this simply means the
linear map T is not
continuous and that
is what we wanted to show
from the beginning.
So our proof is finished
with this technical proposition.
Out of the way we can go
to the definition of a regular
distribution.
For this, we first need a
notion of a locally
integrable function.
Let's call the function F
and it can have values in
R or in C
and we call it locally
integral if the function
is integrable, when we
restrict it to any compact
set.
So you can put it in the
way that the integral over
compact set K of the
function F with the absolute
value makes
sense and is
finite.
When you know how to deal
with Lebesgue integrals, it
will make your life much
easier here because you
know, you need a measurable
function F and the
integral should be finite.
However, it's also possible
to think of a normal Riemann
integral here and do everything
with the Riemann integral.
But then of course, we don't
get out the full general
result.
Therefore, I would say knowing
some measure theory and the
Lebesgue integral is indeed
helpful here in the theory
of distributions.
Now, for such locally integrable
functions, we use a common
notation, namely we
write a curved L
with one and lo
and often we put in the domain
which is here
and please
note of course, all
integrable functions are also
locally integrable.
We just have more functions
here.
For example, if you consider
the function F which sends
R to R
and X to X squared, then
this function is not
integrable because the integral
over the whole domain are
would be infinity.
However, it's locally
integrable because it's a
continuous function.
And when we integrate over
a bounded set here, we don't
have any problem, we get
out a finite integral.
Nevertheless, please note
that we don't need the continuity
for a locally integrable
function.
We have much more functions
here than just the continuous
ones.
Now, the nice thing we want
to do now with such a function
is to define a distribution
for such a function F I want
to use the notation TF
for the corresponding distribution.
And it is defined for test
function Phi.
And you might already know
this because we did it for
continuous functions in the
last video by the
integral
FX phi
XDX.
This is a well defined
distribution because the
integral is actually
just an integral over a compact
set, namely the support of
Phi, it's also
linear and it fulfills our
estimate from the beginning.
This one we really should
write down.
So we have the absolute value
of T f phi, we can
pull in the absolute value
into the integral and we
can also easily split
it up.
Now instead of RN, we can
just write the support of
Phi simply because
outside of function, Phi
is zero, which has no
contribution to the integral.
Also we know we can estimate
this one with the suprema
norm of Phi,
hence, we have the integral
of F in the absolute
value
times the sup norm of
Phi.
Of course, we can integrate
here over any compact set
K as long as it is a
superset of the support of
Phi.
Now please remember what
the estimate is we want to
show.
So I put it here in a
box as a reminder.
And there you see the
integral here is the constant
C here.
And the sum is just the sum
where M is zero.
So we just have the suprema
number Phi in
other words, we have indeed
a distribution.
So you see this is similar
to what we had in the last
video where we considered
continuous functions.
The distribution here is
essentially given by a
normal function F.
And therefore, these
distributions are just called
regular distributions.
To put this into a definition,
you would say a distribution
T is called regular
if there is a locally
integrable function F
such that T is the
same as TF
so the linear map T can
actually be written as an
integral in this sense.
So you could say these are
the distributions that behave
like normal functions as
we already know it.
But we also know there are
much more distributions than
that.
Indeed, the delta distribution
is not regular.
And we can show this in the
next video.
Therefore, I hope I see you
there and have a nice day.
Bye.