Hello and welcome back
to distributions.
And first, as always, I want
to thank all the nice people
that support this channel
on Steady or paypal.
In today's part six, we will
show that the delta
distribution is not a
regular distribution.
So usually we say it's a
singular distribution
more concretely, this means
there's no locally
integrable function F
defined on RN with
values in R or C as
always with the
property that delta of
Phi is the same as
TF of Phi.
And of course, this property
should hold for all test
functions Phi, OK.
Now, as a reminder TF of
Phi was defined by the
integral.
So we integrate FX
times Phi X and
we already showed in the
last video that for locally
integral with function F,
this always defines a
distribution.
On the other hand, if we
put Phi into the delta
distribution, we get out
the value of Phi at
zero.
Now, our claim here is for
no F this equality is
possible.
Indeed, this is a standard
exercise.
And here I want to show you
the proof of it.
Let's do it with a proof
by contradiction.
Therefore, let's assume that
we find such a function
F.
So it's a locally integrable
function where we usually
use this symbol here.
And now this property here
will lead to a contradiction.
OK.
Now, in the first step, I
just want to integrate the
function F itself.
So we already know this gives
us a finite number by
assumption when we integrate
over a compact set.
And for this, let's simply
choose the unit ball.
One possibility to describe
this would be simply to write
that the Euclidean norm of
X is less or equal than
one.
And in order to get a positive
number out here, we also
use the absolute value inside.
Then we know we get out a
number A which is a
finite positive number.
Now to get an idea of what
we do here, let's sketch
the region where we integrate
over in the case that the
dimension is two
there, we just have this
circle where we integrate
over the whole disc.
Now, what I want to do is
to go closer to the
0.0 to the origin
because this is the one we
are interested in.
Therefore, we can take smaller
and smaller circles here
and can split up the whole
region.
Of course, we do this with
infinitely many circles
where we choose one over
K as the radius.
So we start with 1/1, then
comes 1/2
1/3 and so on.
And then our idea is that
we can simply take the union
of all these rings here.
And then this infinite union
is again the whole disc.
OK.
I don't think we need to
formalize this even more
because the idea should be
clear.
The important thing we get
is that here at the
integral, we have a countable
union.
And now when you know some
measure theory or integration
theory, you immediately know
what to do because here
we have a disjoint union,
we can simply write the whole
integral as an infinite sum
over the single integrals
over the rings.
Of course, this whole procedure
here is very natural.
But it's the thing we have
to put in for the integrals.
In the case, you want to
learn more about the details
here, you can simply watch
my measure theory videos.
Now the result we get here
is an infinite sum a series
which has a finite value.
Therefore, we can conclude
that the sequence given by
these integrals here is a
sequence that converges to
zero.
And we know even more if
we shift the starting point
here, we can make this series
as small as we want.
For example, we could make
it smaller than one half
and I take one half because
it's a number that is smaller
than one.
And this is what we need
for the contradiction.
OK.
And now we can just summarize
the whole thing.
I only did it to show
you that we find an epsilon
greater than zero.
Such that the integral
over the epsilon ball is
a number B which is smaller
than one half.
So the whole explanation
told you if we make the
epsilon ball small enough,
we can make the whole integral
as small as we want.
Of course, this makes totally
sense if you just think of
some ordinary functions.
However, it also holds for
a locally integrable function.
Now, this was just a rough
idea, but I don't think you
will have any problems filling
in the details.
For example, one detail I
skipped here is that in this
union, we will not
include zero as a point.
However, since the whole
integral here does not care
about a single point, the
whole calculation is still
correct.
OK.
Now, with this result from
the first step, we are ready
to finish the proof
because we look at the delta
distribution, it would be
good to have test functions
that are concentrated at
zero.
Indeed, we already know a
nice one from part two of
the video series, it was
set to zero outside of
the unit ball and
inside the unit ball, it
was given by an exponential
function.
This is a nice test function
and the one dimensional visualization
would be just such a bump
where the maximum is
exactly at zero.
OK.
Now you already know from
the first part, the unit
ball might be not small
enough.
Therefore, we should take
this epsilon ball here.
Therefore, I would say let's
change the function phi a
little bit with this epsilon,
it should be zero outside
of the epsilon ball and
inside it should be the same
exponential function.
Therefore, also inside the
exponential function we have
to divide by epsilon.
And then you see this was
just scaling the whole test
function.
Everything looks exactly
the same just zoom to
the epsilon ball instead of
the unit ball.
OK.
Then let's calculate with
this test function
by assumption this integral
here is given by the delta
distribution which means
it gives us the value of
the test function at zero.
It's a positive number.
Hence, we don't change anything
when we use absolute values
here, it makes everything
easier because we can just
apply the triangle inequality
for integrals.
So now we have the absolute
value inside the
integral.
This means that we can just
pull out the supreme norm
of the test function.
However, before we do that,
we should change the region
where we integrate over to
the epsilon ball.
Because outside of the epsilon
ball, everything is zero
by the test function.
And maybe now you already
see why we care so much about
the epsilon ball.
First, let's pull out the
supremum norm of the test
function.
And then you see only this
integral here remains
first, the supremum here
we already know it's the
value at zero more
concretely the same as the
left hand side.
And the second part here
is equal to B
however, B was smaller
than one half, which
means we have an inequality
which can't be satisfied.
So we have a positive number
which does not get smaller
when we multiply it with
one half.
And such a positive real
number does not exist.
And this is indeed our wanted
contradiction in
conclusion such a locally
integral function F for the
delta distribution does not
exist.
Therefore, the delta distribution
is not a regular
distribution.
OK.
Then in the next video, I
will show you what we can
really do with distributions
and how to calculate with
them.
Therefore, I hope I see you
there and have a nice day.
Bye.