Hello and welcome to linear algebra
A whole video course I designed for everyone
who wants to start with the basics in mathematics
and in the end wants to master vectors,
vector spaces, matrices and so on.
However, before we start I really
want to thank the nice supporters
that make this course possible.
Each small contribution on Steady or
PayPal makes it easier for me to spend
to create these videos here.
Therefore, on Steady you find quizzes and
the pdf versions for all the videos here.
Okay, now you might know I already have
some calculation videos in linear algebra.
But with this course here, you
finally get the whole structure
and should be able to learn linear algebra,
by watching the videos in the right order.
Indeed, linear algebra as a whole is
a very important topic in mathematics,
and it has a lot of different applications.
One application, I can visualise
immediately with a short drawing here.
Just imagine in the problem you want to
solve, a lot of variables are involved.
For example, we could have some
fixed quantities, we just call
a, b, c, d and so on.
And on the other hand,
we also could have some variables
where we don't know the value yet.
Therefore, we call them unknowns,
and here we denote them by x,y,z.
Hence, in order to solve your problem.
You want to find possible values for x,y,z.
And exactly there, linear algebra can help
when we know the relations between the quantities.
However, it turns out, we need simply
relations between our variables.
Then, when we have this, we can use linear algebra
to find all possible solutions for the unknowns
Therefore, linear algebra is the important
tool which helps us solving our problem.
So, you could say:
Giving calculation rules for solutions
is one part of linear algebra.
Indeed, this is important.
But in order to understand the topic in a whole,
we need to go abstract.
Therefore, this abstract level is something,
we also will discuss in this course.
For example, on this abstract level,
we will find a fundamental concept
we call a vector space.
Then, in this space, we will
find objects, we call vectors.
And we will find out, we can
do a lot with these vectors,
which leads us to a new concept, we call
a linear map.
Hence, there we have now something
that can transform vectors.
Now, please don't be deterred here because
we don't start at the abstract level.
First, we will consider we will
consider a very concrete level.
This means, instead of an abstract vector space,
we start with something, we can call Rn.
Then, on this level, a linear
map just corresponds to
something we can put into a table.
And such a table, we just call a matrix.
Okay, now we now:
In this course,
we first discuss the concrete level here
and then we go to the abstract level afterwards.
Of course, there are some
prerequisites for this course
you should know.
However, the good thing is,
I have a whole series about
start learning mathematics
that should help you there.
Now, you don't have know all the topics there
but it would be helpful if you
gather a basic knowledge about
logical symbols, set operations and maps.
In particular, working with maps,
will be important immediately.
Then, with this knowledge,
I would say, you are ready
to start with linear algebra here.
Therefore, in the next video,
we can immediately talk about
vectors and how to calculate with them.
So I really hope that I see you there.
Have a nice day and bye!