Hello and welcome.
This is a quick video about a table you really should remember.
In the first row I give you an angle and we start with 0°, go to 30°, then to 45°, 60° and 90°.
Of course we can also do this in radians. So we have 0, pi/6, pi/4, pi/3 and pi/2.
Now, let's take the function sine and calculate the values of these angles.
The sin(0) is 0, but let's write it as 1/2 times sqrt(0).
The next value then reads 1/2 times the root of 1
and then we can continue to 1/2 * sqrt(2),
1/2 * sqrt(3) and 1/2 * sqrt(4).
Of course we could simplify these values here and obviously in calculations we should really do this,
but here it's much easier to remember the table in this way.
Now then the next nice thing is, it works for the cosine as well. Just the other way around.
We have 1/2*sqrt(4) for 0 and for pi/6 we have 1/2*sqrt(3),
then 1/2*sqrt(2). The same as for the sine
and 1/2*sqrt(1) for 60° and 1/2*sqrt(0) for 90°
and there we have it. This is the table you should remember and never forget.
Essentially you just have to remember these 5 angles here, because then you can fill out this whole table in your mind.
I hope this helps and see you next time. Bye!