Hello and welcome to the video series about unbounded operators.
This is a video course in the field of functional analysis and I would say it's already very special and advanced.
Therefore in order to understand this course in the best way, you should already have good knowledge in linear algebra and real analysis
and of course you can always refresh your memory by watching my videos about these topics
and moreover if you watched my functional analysis course, you already learned a lot about bounded operators.
This means this course here expands the functional analysis course by so called unbounded operators.
Now indeed it turns out that these operators are not easy to describe, but they occur a lot in applications.
However, before I start with the motivation here,
first I really want to thank all the nice people who support this channel on Steady, that made this video course possible.
Since this is such a special topic, which will not generate many views on YouTube.
I can only do it, because of your support on Steady or Patreon
and as a thank you, you will always find the PDF versions and quizzes for the videos on my Webpage.
Ok, then let's start with the topic and let's clear up why unbounded operators are so important.
In fact we immediately have a mathematical reason,
because when we deal with partial differential equations we immediately see unbounded operators.
So the whole theory about partial differential equations is much easier to understand when you know what unbounded operators are
and obviously we will explain these connections in this course.
Now, historically the next one might be the biggest motivation after all,
because you need unbounded operators to describe quantum mechanics.
So you might already know that in this physical theory you need operators.
So you definitely need functional analysis, but it turns out that you can't avoid unbounded operators.
Indeed, one needs 2 special objects as operators and we call them X and P.
So for example for one particle the one measures the position of the particle and the other operator measures the momentum of the particle
and now the physical reality tells us that the order of these two measurements matters.
This means XP is different from PX
and of course by using functional analysis we can describe this as a composition of operators.
However now the order of the composition matters in the sense that the difference is proportional to the identity operator.
More precisely we also have the imaginary unit here, but this is not the important part now.
The crucial thing here is that we can not satisfy this equation with just bounded operators.
This means we have to extend the notion of a linear operator to do quantum mechanics
and in fact we will see that with unbounded operators this works.
However together with the unbounded operators we get other technical difficulties into the theory
and we will immediately see this with the first definition here,
but let's first start with some objects we should already know.
Namely the first things we need are two normed spaces we call X and Y.
So we have 2 vector spaces over the same field and they also carry a norm
and you might know we either have real vector spaces or complex ones.
Therefore if we call the field F it's either the real number line or the complex plane
and I can already tell you, most of the time you can just thing of complex vector spaces here.
Ok, but now immediately something new arises. Namely we need a domain for our operator
and this will be a subspace in X and we call it D.
Hence, now the map we consider and call T is a linear one
and you can put in elements from the subspace D and you get out elements from Y
and now in this course we keep it simple. Such a linear map, we always call an operator.
So please keep that in mind. If we talk about unbounded operators, we implicitly mean linear operators.
Ok and now it's a good time to also talk about other notations people use to denote such an operator.
Now, the first one is very similar. Some people just use the subset relation here, in the definition of the operator again.
This makes sense, because often the space X is the important normed space here.
However, some other people abuse this notation a little bit by omitting the actual domain here
and if they are nice, they at least say somewhere, that this T has the domain D.
So you can recognize with this that some people see an operator as a pair of 2 things.
First they say they have an action defined by T and then a restriction to a domain D.
So this keeps it very short, but you also often see that in some books.
Or similarly instead of a pair, one writes T with domain D,
but instead of the word domain, one also often uses D(T).
Ok, maybe that's good enough for the different notations you could stumble upon, but let's go back to the actual definition here.
Now for this course a very important term will be given by so called densely defined operators
and you might already expect that these will be the operators we will discuss in the next videos
and the definition should be very clear. T is called densely defined, if domain D is dense.
More precisely this means if you take the closure in the space X, then you get the full space X out.
So maybe the domain of the operator is not the whole space, but it's very close to that in this sense
and here please note, this thing here is only interesting in infinite dimensions, because D is still a linear subspace.
So only in infinite dimensions, we could have smaller subspaces that are still dense in the whole space.
Ok by knowing that we can also write down 2 important subspaces we use all the time
and of course I mean range and kernel for the operator T.
So the explicit definitions you might already know, but because we have to consider a domain here, I want to write them down.
Now first the range of T is given by all the elements we hit on the right-hand side.
This means we have to go through all lower case x in D
and what we get is a subspace in Y.
So please remember that. It's still a linear subspace.
Ok and now for the kernel we have to take all the points x that are sent to 0.
Therefore what we get here is a linear subspace in X.
Ok and with that we have it. We have the range of the operator T and the kernel of T
and now in the next step we can finally recall the definition of boundedness
and then of course if you know what bounded means, you also know what unbounded means.
So now bounded means we find a constant c. Which we could choose greater than 0, but it should be a finite number
and now for every point x in the domain we can calculate Tx in the norm of Y
and now this one should always be bounded by the constant c.
More precisely it's c times the norm of x in the space X
and here you should recognize if you calculate the operator norm you have learned in the functional analysis course,
you see this operator norm is bounded by the constant c
and therefore the operator T is called bounded
and now if the operator norm is infinite, we call the operator unbounded
or more precisely we can do the negation here.
Which means for all constants we find at least one point x such that Tx in the norm is greater than c times x in the norm.
This means the ratio Tx to x exceeds every bound
and therefore the operator norm as a number would give infinity in this case.
Indeed this can definitely happen and we will see some important examples in the next video.
However here I first want to recall an important equivalence from the functional analysis course.
Namely a linear map is bounded if and only if it's continuous at all the points in the domain.
So you see for operators the terms boundedness and continuity are connected in this way.
Therefore unbounded operators as we want to consider them in this course are not continuous at all.
Indeed, an unbounded operator has to be discontinuous at all points.
So this is important to remember. Unbounded means not continuous at all
and there we see again, This is definitely something that can only happen in infinite dimensions.
Of course in finite dimensions every linear map has to be a continuous map.
However in infinite dimensions we have so many directions that the continuity property can fail
and at this point we already know we can not ignore such operators, because they occur in a lot of applications
and therefore I would say let's look at some examples in the next video and let's discuss it more.
So have a nice day and bye bye!