Hello and welcome back to unbounded operators.
The video series, where we tackle some more topics of functional analysis
and now in today's part 2 we will look at some examples for unbounded operators.
However, as always before we start I first want to thank all the nice people who support this channel on Steady, here on YouTube or on Patreon.
Ok, then let's start by recalling what we mean by an operator.
So you should know, it's just the linear map between 2 normed spaces, X and Y.
Moreover, we also say it has a domain D(T) given by a subspace D.
This actually means that we only have a map from D into Y
and please don't forget it's always a linear map.
Ok and now such operators here could be either bounded or unbounded
and this we can measure wit the operator norm.
So this we already know. So let's state some other important fact.
Namely we can consider the case that the kernel of our operator is trivial.
This means it's equal to the smallest possible subspace, which is the zero vector.
In particular this means that the linear map T is injective
and from that we now can conclude that we can write down an inverse map T to the power -1.
Now of course here we change the direction. So now we map Y into X
and we can do that because we can write down a suitable domain
and indeed in general the domain is not equal to the whole space Y, but only equal to the range of T.
This makes sense because with this restriction here on the right-hand side we would get the surjectivity for our linear map.
So in short what we have learned here is if the kernel of T is trivial, the inverse T^-1 is always defined as an operator.
However please note this operator here can be unbounded even in the case that the original operator T was bounded.
Nevertheless you see this makes our lives a little bit simpler for defining operators
and with that I would say we are ready for discussing examples
and for the start I want to keep it simple. So let's say that X and Y represent the same normed space
and this one should be the space of continuous functions
and maybe let's say the continuous functions are only defined on the unit interval 0 to 1
and you might know, the common norm one chooses for this space is the uniform norm, also called the supremum norm
and one just uses an infinity symbol to denote this norm.
Ok, then let's define an operator that maps X to Y.
So as before we write T from X to Y, but what we actually mean is that T has a domain as a subspace in X
and for this case here, I want to choose the domain as the continuous functions that are also continuously differentiable.
So in short I just want to write C^1 as a subspace in C.
Because then I can simply write that T applied to an element from the domain is defined as the derivative
and if we call the function x we have Tx is equal to x prime.
Now, obviously this is a well defined map and by the properties of the derivative it's also a linear map.
In other words it's an operator and now we can show, it's an unbounded one
and this is not hard at all, because we can just look at some pictures.
So maybe imagine that we have some nice smooth functions here, where the maximum is at 1.
Now, this fact helps for calculating the supremum norm of T.
So I think it's very helpful to write down the definition of the supremum norm again.
So one possibility is to take the supremum over all possible inputs that have norm 1
and please note all these possible x elements have to come from the chosen domain here
and then we can just take the supremum of the norm Tx.
Ok so this is the general definition of the supremum norm if we just filled in the chosen norm of the two spaces
and then in the next step here we can use the definition of our T.
So you see what goes in here is now the maximal value of the absolute value of the derivative of the function x.
Hence by going back to our picture here, we see that we can define a new function with a higher maximal derivative there.
So you should see the slope here is simply higher than that from the function before
and then you should see we can do that again and again to increase the slope as much as we want
and the important part by doing that is that we don't increase the supremum norm of the function x.
Ok and then we have to conclude that the supremum of the derivative here is not bounded.
In other words the operator norm of T is equal to infinity.
So indeed we have an unbounded operator here
and you should note this was not a complicated operator at all.
Ok then I would say let's use this example to define another unbounded operator
and let's use this same space as X and Y and let's call the operator S.
Indeed we can also use the same definition as before with the derivative, but now I want to change the domain.
Now, I only want to use some particular continuously differentiable functions for the domain.
So we could write: let's choose functions x in C^1 that are fixed on the left boundary.
Namely x(0) = 0.
This means now we have a new subspace of continuous functions which is definitely smaller than the one before.
Otherwise you see everything is the same as we had it for the operator T.
Therefore there are some special notations one uses usually for this fact
and this is a little bit strange, because we use an inclusion symbol for operators,
but it makes literally sense if you put in the corresponding domains.
Hence the subset notation here actually means that S in T are essentially the same operator, but S has a smaller domain
and for this reason one says that T is an extension of S.
So this is definitely something you should remember in this context
and on the other hand the operator S is called a restriction for the operator T.
So you see the names make sense and they are always used if we talk about domains.
Indeed, we will see that changing the domain, making it smaller or larger, can change a lot.
For example in this case here the inverse operator changes.
In fact the operator T does not have an inverse, because it's not injective.
Simply because any constant function has derivative 0.
However this doesn't happen to S, because the only constant function is the 0 function.
Hence we conclude that S is an injective operator
and as explained before we can write down S^-1.
So this is a well defined operator in the sense of our definition.
Ok, but I can tell you this nice fact here comes with a price.
Namely the domain of the restriction S is much smaller than the original domain.
More precisely the continuously differentiable functions lie dense in the continuous functions
or more precisely the closer of C^1 with respect to the supremum norm is equal to C.
Indeed this is a very nice fact from the continuously differentiable functions.
However with the restriction here on the left-hand side this doesn't hold anymore.
We immediately see that we can't approximate any constant function that is not the 0 function
and therefore the operator S is not densely defined
and you might already expect that in most cases we want to have a densely defined operator,
because otherwise we are just too far away from the original space.
Of course in general it would be the best thing to have the whole space as a domain,
but we have already seen this is not possible for a lot of operators
and in fact for most unbounded operators we are interested in it's not possible to define them on the whole space.
So we always have to weaken that to densely defined operators,
but I would say let's see how this works out with the next videos.
So I really hope that I see you there and have a nice day. Bye-bye