Hello and welcome back to unbounded operators.
The video series in the field of functional analysis
and in today's part 3 we will define so called closed operators.
Indeed it will turn out that these closed operators are related to the continuity property that bounded operators have.
So in some sense this is the generalization we want now.
However, you already know before we start
I first want to thank all the nice people who support this channel on Steady, here on YouTube or via Patreon
and please don't forget, you can also download quizzes and PDF versions for all the videos with the link in the description.
Ok, then let's start again by telling what we mean by an operator.
So an operator T is just a linear map between two normed spaces X and Y, but we can have a domain
and usually what we do is that we call this domain D(T).
So in general T is not defined on the whole normed space X,
but still, it has to be a linear mapping between the two spaces.
Ok and now since this is a well defined map, we can identify it with its graph
and this you might know. It's just a special subset in the Cartesian product X times Y.
This means we can simply sketch it into a coordinate system.
Hence in general you would sketch a graph like that.
However since we have a linear mapping here, we should also make it clear that we have a linear relation as a graph.
Moreover since we work in infinite dimensions,
in reality we would expect that the picture looks much more complicated than this line,
but still the general idea here of this set given by this graph of T still holds.
Ok, then let's give this set a short name. Let's call it G index T
and now we can define it as a subset of X times Y.
This means we just have to write down what one point (x,y) has to fulfill.
First that x lies in the domain of T and second we need that Tx is equal to y.
So the image of our x is exactly the point y.
So not so surprising this is how in general we would define the graph of a map.
However here we have a little bit more, because this Cartesian product here is a normed space again.
Hence it's not just a set. It's a whole vector space, where we can also measure lengths
and at this point you should ask what is the corresponding norm here.
In other words what is the correct length of the pair (x,y)?
Indeed there are different possibilities to do that, but the common one is just to add two norms we already know.
So first take the norm of x and then add the norm of y
and now it's not hard to check at all, that this here defines a norm again.
Hence we always have a normed space with the Cartesian product, with X and Y are normed spaces from the beginning
and therefore you can say now in the graph of T we can also measure distances
or more precisely we can use all the topological terms we have for the graph of T.
In particular we can also check if the graph of T is a closed set
and that's exactly what we do now in order to define so called closed operators.
So you see we call T a closed operator if its graph is a closed set in the normed space X times Y.
So not a complicated definition at all, we just have to know what closed sets in normed spaces are
and the good thing is, we can assume that we already know a lot.
In particular we know that we can also work with sequences to define closed sets
and this means we immediately get an equivalent definition for a closed operator.
More precisely instead of working with a closed set, we can also work with sequences.
So, what we have to do is to take arbitrary sequence x_n inside the domain
and this one has to fulfill 2 properties.
So first it should be a convergent sequence in the normed space X.
This means it has a limit that lies in the space X.
So we don't have to assume that the limit lies in the domain
and second we assume that the sequence of the images is also convergent.
So Tx_n converges inside the space Y to a limit y
and now the claim is that for each sequence with these two properties we can conclude 2 other properties.
The first one is indeed this limit x lies in the domain of T
and this immediately implies that we are allowed to apply T to this x as well
and then we get the second property. This image is indeed equal to y.
So this sounds not so strange, but maybe at this point you can immediately compare this definition to the continuity definition.
Indeed, this is what I mentioned before. We want to use this definition as a substitute for the continuity.
This is because we already know, unbounded operators are not continuous.
Ok, now I thing we can also write down the proof for this statement from before.
So we want to improve the equivalence stated here
and in fact I already gave you the hint. Closed sets can be equivalently described by sequences.
So you should know, this works in general, in metric spaces. So in particular here in normed spaces.
So what you have to do is to take a sequence from the set and you have to assume that this one is convergent.
So please don't forget this means the sequence is convergent in our normed space X times Y.
So maybe here let's call the limit also z and the important thing is, it lies in X times Y,
because now the important conclusion here is that this z also lies in G_T.
So you should see, this is the general thing. Closed means you can not leave this set with sequence from inside
and this is indeed equivalent. All the boundary points already lie inside the set itself.
Ok, so this should not be a surprise and now we want to put this into the context of an operator.
So first instead of z_n we can already write what we know about the graph.
Namely that it always consists of a pair. (x_n, Tx_n).
So a sequence inside the graph of T always has this form.
Ok and now this sequence should converge to a point in our Cartesian product
and this limit we can just call (x,y).
Ok, but now this claim here tells us that this pair (x,y) also lies in the graph of T
and by the definition of the graph, this exactly means 2 things.
First our point x lies in the domain
and second Tx is exactly y
and there you should already see, this is exactly the conclusion in the claim above
and now the only difference here is the assumption from before.
However, now we can conclude by the definition of the norm in the Cartesian product
that this convergence here is nothing else then this convergence.
Indeed, you could say here, if you want to converge to the pair, you have to converge in each component
and converging with the two components is exactly what we have written here
and with that I would say the proof is good enough. We have this equivalence here
and I would say this sequence definition here is what you should always have in mind when you talk about closed operators
and then it's also no problem at all for you to show the following.
Namely let's consider a bounded operator.
In addition the domain of T should also be the whole space X.
So this is an operator like we had it in our functional analysis course before
and in fact the conclusion here is that such a standard bounded operator is a closed one.
So you should see, this closed operator notion is so important,
because it's our generalization from the bounded operators to the unbounded operators, as we wanted.
More precisely closed operators still have some nice properties the bounded operators had.
However the details for that is something for the next videos.
In particular we will look at examples,
we will talk about closable operators
and we will have a look at the so called closed graph theorem.
So I really hope we meet again and have a nice day. Bye-bye!