Hello and welcome back to unbounded operators.
The video series in the topic of functional analysis
and in today's part 4 we will talk about so called closable operators.
However, before we start with the content
I first want to thank all the nice people who support this channel on Steady, here on YouTube or on Patreon
and as a reward for supporting me, you get additional material which you can find with the link in the description.
Ok, then let's start going into the topic by recalling what a closed operator is.
The common name is just T and we need two normed spaces X and Y
and now it's important to note that we also have a domain for the operator called D(T).
Indeed, this is a well defined linear subspace in the normed space X
and please don't forget, for us an operator is always a linear map
and now we speak of a closed operator if the graph of this linear map is a closed set.
More precisely we call the graph G_T and it should be a closed set inside the normed space X times Y.
Ok and now if you know some topology or if you know how to deal with closed sets in the metric space,
then you know each set is a subset of a closed set.
In other words if this set is not closed, we can always replace that with the closure of the set
and this fact leads us to so called closable operators.
So this is a more general term. Meaning that each closed operator is always also a closable operator.
However it's still a requirement. Not every operator is indeed a closable operator
and of course we immediately see that in the definition.
So what we do is that we take the graph G_T as before and then we form the closure of it
and please note in the case of a closed operator this doesn't change anything
and now what we want for a closable operator is that this new set here is also the graph of an operator.
This means by doing the closure in the space X times Y, we don't destroy the structure of a graph
and now in the case that this is a well defined graph, we call the operator T with an overline
and moreover we also call this operator the closure of the operator T
and of course by definition the closure of T is a closed operator.
Hence you can remember an operator is called closable, if the closure of the graph defines an operator as well.
So indeed, this is what we have here as the definition for the notion closable
and in the next step I want to reformulate that with the help of sequences.
In fact this is a similar thing we have already done for closed operators in the last video
and I can already tell you, this is a very helpful description you can use in proofs and examples.
You will see that very soon when we will discuss the first example of a closable operator,
but first let's see how we can use sequences to describe this property for describing the graph of T.
Therefore let's think what it means that the closure of T is a graph again.
So for example it's not possible that the pair (0,0) and the pair (0,y), both lie in this set
and of course what we mean is, it's not possible for a y that is not 0.
Indeed, you should see this is not possible for a well defined map, because one input gets two different outputs.
Moreover this description here already explains everything that could happen with the closure here, because T is a linear map.
Hence we already know that (0,0) lies in this set here and we could also choose any other point then 0 for the input,
because of the linearity or in other words, if we have this double problem here at any other point,
we can just translate it back to the input 0.
Therefore now we can write that being a graph here is equivalent to the fact:
if (0,y) lies in the closure of this graph, then y has to be 0 as well
and exactly this statement we can now describe with sequences.
So what you need to know is, that all the points in the closure we can approximate with points from G_T.
Therefore we would take any sequence x_n from the domain D(T) that converges to 0
Which already means that we want to approximate this 0 here and moreover we also want to approximate this y.
Hence Tx_n should converge to a fixed y in Y.
Ok, so this is the premise. We approximate this point from the inside and now the conclusion is that y has to be 0.
So this is exactly the same thing as before just written with sequences.
Ok and this is what you should remember. A closable operator is exactly characterized with this sequence property here.
Indeed, how you can check that, I will show you in an example soon.
However before we do that I first want to show you how we can define the closure as an operator now
and of course this now only works for a closable operator T
and for this definition we need 2 ingredients. First the domain and then the actual definition of T-bar.
Ok and now the domain consists all the points x in X that fulfill:
that first we can approximate them with points from D(T).
This means the sequence x_n here converges to the point x and in addition we also want that the images converge
and now we know by the property above that this limit here does not depend on which sequence we choose.
More precisely this limit here is uniquely given by the chosen x.
Hence this already explains how we can define the value T-bar_x.
So we just say, this is given by the limit from the right-hand side
and please don't forget, this is only possible because T was a closable operator.
Ok, so now what you see here is, we have a well defined operator called the closure of T
and moreover, you should see it's an extension of the original operator T
and you already know, the usual notation for that is with this subset notation.
This is not hard to see, because we just extend the domain here and increase the definition.
However the result here is that this T-bar is indeed the smallest possible extension with a closed operator.
So you could say this is another possible definition for the closure of a closable operator.
Ok, so now we know a lot about closable operators and we can look at an example.
However, I would say let's put that into the next video.
So I really hope we meet there again and have a nice day. Bye-bye