Hello and welcome back
to unbounded operators,
the video series where we
talk a lot about some nice
topics of functional analysis.
And indeed, in today's part 5 we will continue with
the closable operators by
looking at an example.
But you might already know
before we can do that,
I first want to thank all
the nice people who support
the channel on Steady here
on YouTube or on Patreon.
And please don't forget on
these platforms
you find PDF versions,
quizzes and early access to all new videos.
OK.
Then let's start this video
here by considering a
closable operator T
and there you already know
for the definition, we need
two normed spaces X and Y.
And at this point, I can
already tell you in order
to get nice theorems
out, we have to assume that
X and Y are Banach
spaces.
So complete normed
In fact, also in this example
today, we will take Banach
spaces.
But let's first write down
the general sequence
characterization for a
closable operator.
There, we just have to look
at sequences that
converge to the origin
and they have to have the
property that the
images also
converge and
then the conclusion is that
only the zero vector in
Y is possible for this
limit.
Therefore, please remember
here, if we have this
implication, we know that
the operator T is closable.
And this is exactly what
we now apply to the
following example.
And in order to make it very
concrete, let's choose a
very nice Banach space for
X. Namely
X should be given as lower
case l^2.
So you know this is a space
of sequences with
index set N and
entries in C.
And please recall from the
functional analysis series
that this is a well defined
Banach space.
Moreover, it's even a Hilbert
space, but this is not so
important right now.
OK.
In addition, let's also fix
the canonical unit vectors
denoted by e_1, e_2, e_3 and so on.
Now, if you don't know them,
then maybe very quickly,
e_2 is given as the
sequence
and so on.
In other words, everything
is 0 in the sequence
except the second position,
which is a 1.
So you see this is exactly
the same as you would have
it in a finite dimensional
vector space, but now in
infinite dimensions.
OK.
And now I want the operator
T going from X to
C and
obviously C is also a normed
space, even a Banach
space.
Then in the next step, I
want to define the domain
of T and this
should be given as the span
of the canonical unit
vectors.
This means all the linear
combinations of the canonical
unit vectors lie in the
domain of T.
And here please note this
is not equal to the whole
space X, but it's a
dense subset in it.
OK.
And now this domain makes
it very easy to write
down a nice definition for
an operator T.
Namely we just have to say
what D does to a canonical
unit vector.
And for example, we could
just say take the
corresponding index of the
unit vector.
Therefore T would
send e_2 to the number 2
and now, since we want a
linear map, the extension
to the whole span here is
uniquely given.
But for the sake of completeness,
let's write it down.
So let's say we have a finite
linear combination lambda_j times e_j.
So please note this here
is always a finite sum,
because this is what the
span means.
It means the set of the finite
linear combinations of these
vectors.
And therefore the mapping
here is totally clear, we
just add up lambda_j times j
This gives us a complex number
which is the output of T.
OK.
And the first question from
my side would be is
this an unbounded or a
bounded operator?
To answer that we can just
calculate the operator norm
of T.
By definition, this is the
supremum over all
inputs X with norm 1.
And then we look at the norm
of the images.
Which in this case is the
norm of C.
But of course, the norm in
C is just the absolute
value of complex numbers.
And now let's say instead
of every vector x, we just
put in the canonical unit
vectors. Then the
whole supremum cannot get
bigger.
Then everything is much simpler.
We just have to calculate
the absolute value of
Te_j.
But by the definition of
the operator T, we already
know this is just the number j.
And at this point, we already
see the supremum over
j is not finite.
Therefore, the operator norm
of T can also not be
finite.
So the first conclusion here
is we have an unbounded
operator.
Therefore my next question
would be, is it at least a
closable operator?
And in order to answer this
question, we will use our
sequence property for closable
operators from before.
And we can combine that with
the fact that we have an
operator which is not
continuous at the
origin.
So please never forget for
linear maps, boundedness
and continuity are
connected.
OK.
Then let's use this fact
here for a sequence that
converges to zero.
So what we can do is to choose
a sequence inside the
domain of T that converges
to the origin.
And now we know that we have
at least one sequence with
the property, that the
images don't converge to
zero.
The operator T is not continuous
at zero.
So this is possible
however, still it could
happen that the images here
accumulate at zero.
But we also know that for
infinitely many sequence
members that does not happen.
So it's possible to choose
a safety distant epsilon
from zero
and a subsequence
x_nk
such that the images
stay away from zero
with distance epsilon.
So the absolute value is
greater or equal than our
epsilon.
Therefore, now we can
conclude it's allowed to
divide by this number.
Hence, we can define a new
sequence and let's call it
z_k.
So we take x_nk and then
we divide this by the number
Tx_nk.
So this one is definitely
a well-defined element in
the domain of T.
And moreover, if we increase
k, we also see that
this sequence tends to zero.
So in this regard, it works
the same as our original
sequence x_n.
However, for the images,
something different happens,
namely, we immediately
see that we divide 1 by 1.
So the outcome is always
1. No matter which
k from N we choose.
And with that, we now have
our counter example for the
characterization for a closable
operator with
sequences.
In fact, we can immediately
compare it here.
Now we have a sequence in
the domain of T which
converges to zero
and the images also
converge to a y,
in particular, the y in
our case is given by 1
and that's already the contradiction
because y has to be equal
to zero if the operator
T is closable.
And with that, we can make
our conclusion T is not
a closable operator.
And this also includes that
T is not a closed operator
as well.
Therefore, this is important
to remember in infinite
dimensions, we can easily
define unbounded
operators that are not even
closable.
But I can already tell you
in this course, we will also
see a lot of closed
operators.
So a lot of positive examples.
OK.
Then I really hope we meet
again and have a nice day.
Bye bye.