Hello and welcome back to real analysis
and of course many, many thanks to all the nice people that support this channel on Steady or Paypal.
In today's part 12 we talk again about the limit superior and the limit inferior.
Here please recall, for any sequence of real numbers this lim sup and lim inf always exist.
Namely they are either a real number or the symbol - or + infinity.
Also I can tell you, some people write this set as an interval.
There we use brackets to say that the symbols -infinity and infinity are included in the set.
Ok, since you already know this, let's look at an example.
So here i take the sequence a_n given as (-1) to the power n times n.
Hence the sequence starts with -1, then comes 2, then -3, then 4, -5 and so on.
Obviously this sequence is not convergent.
However we find a subsequence that is divergent to infinity.
Hence the lim sup has to be infinity.
Then in the same way we find a subsequence that is divergent to -infinity.
Hence the lim inf has to be -infinity.
So you see this is a simple example,
but it tells us that all the elements in this set are possible values for the limit superior and limit inferior.
With this in mind let's formulate some properties.
First let's discuss what we have for convergent sequences.
Here please recall, the lim sup is the largest accumulation value and the lim inf the smallest one.
Therefore a sequence is convergent if and only if the lim sup and the lim inf are actually the same
and of course they should be real numbers.
This is not hard to see, if the sequence is convergent lim sup and lim inf are actually the limit.
On the other hand if they are the same, there is only one accumulation value, therefore the sequence has to converge to this value.
Ok, now we can extend this result and talk about the case when the limit is infinity.
So we say the sequence is divergent to infinity.
Then lim sup and lim inf have to be the same again, but now they should be infinity.
Please compare this to the example, because there it's different. They are not real numbers, but they are not the same.
Ok, another thing i can tell you is that the lim sup is always the largest accumulation value. So always larger than lim inf.
Therefore we can just ignore this part here.
This immediately follows if you know that the lim inf is infinity.
Now next, maybe not so surprising, we can do the same for the limit -infinity
and this holds if and only if the lim sup is -infinity.
Now, all the things here are easy to show, when you know the definitions we discussed in the last video.
A little bit more complicated is the next property, where we combine 2 different sequences.
Ok, now for a sequence a_n and b_n you could ask: "What is the lim sup of the sum?"
So lim sup (a_n + b_n).
In general this is not equal to the sum of the two limit superiors,
but only less or equal.
However please keep in mind, this only makes sense if the right-hand side here, is well defined.
For example infinity + (-infinity) would be not defined.
Now, this is the only exception of this inequality. For example you could have infinity + 5 and this would be infinity again.
Ok, now in the same way, for 2 sequences you could ask: "What is about the product?"
and it turns out, it's the same thing. The lim sup of (a_n times b_n) is less or equal than the product of the 2 limit superiors.
However, in general this is not correct, because we could have different signs for the sequences, which would flip the inequality.
Therefore let's formulate and remember this property for non-negative sequences.
However also here we have an exception, for example 0 times infinity is not defined.
This is important to know, whenever you calculate with the symbols - and + infinity.
Ok, i would say proving these two inequalities is a very good exercise for you,
because when you do this, you immediately see that we have a similar inequality for the limit inferior.
So it's the same in green here. The only thing that changed is the direction of the inequality.
So the lim inf on the left-hand side could get bigger than the right-hand side.
To see that this is in general really an inequality let's look at an example.
So here we need two sequences of real numbers.
I want a_n to be 1, -1, 1, -1 and so on
and b_n to be 0, 2, 0, 2 and so on.
With this information we can immediately calculate the sum of the two sequences.
Which is simply the constant sequence with value 1.
Hence simply a convergent sequence.
Therefore the lim sup and the lim inf of the sum are simply 1
and now we know from the properties above that we have inequalities here.
Indeed, here in this case they are actually strict,
because here on the right-hand side we have 1 + 2, which is 3.
Which is strictly greater than 1
and for the lim inf, we have -1 + 0. So also here strictly less than 1.
Ok, now of course we can do the same for the product.
However, for this we should take non-negative sequences.
Therefore let's formulate this with a new example.
So we can take the same sequence for b_n, but for a_n we have to substitute -1 with 0.
Then the product sequence is just the constant sequence, now with 0 as the value.
Of course then the lim sup is 0 as well.
On the other hand the lim sup of a_n is 1 and the lim sup of b_n is 2.
So we have 2 on the right-hand side.
Therefore also here, we see in this example we have the strict inequality.
Ok, after all this the important things you really should remember are the 4 inequalities we have for lim sup and lim inf
and when you have time, maybe you also find an example, where we have the strict inequality for lim inf.
Later you will see, we can use these inequalities a lot in calculations.
Ok, I think that's good enough for today and I hope I see you next time.
Bye!