Hello and welcome back to real analysis.
Of course as always I want to thank all the nice people that support this channel on Steady or Paypal.
In today's part 13 we will talk about open, closed and compact sets.
First please recall that for any point x on the number line, we have the epsilon-neighbourhoods.
They are defined for positive epsilons as intervals.
Namely we start at (x - epsilon) and go to (x + epsilon)
and then they are simply called the epsilon-neighbourhood of x
and a common notation one uses is B with index epsilon of x.
The important thing you should remember here is that all the points that are close to x, are inside this B_epsilon(x)
and this closeness is just quantified with this value epsilon.
Which gives us the maximum distance the points can have from x.
However if you don't want or need to quantify the closeness, there is another notion one uses.
Namely we simply call it a neighbourhood of x
and this could be any subset of the real numbers, as long as we find the B_epsilon(x) inside
or in other words: we need to find a positive number epsilon, such that the epsilon-neighbourhood of x, B_epsilon(x), is a subset of M.
So you see the notion of neighbourhood of x is very general, but the crucial thing is that we find a normal epsilon-neighbourhood of x inside of it.
Ok, maybe we should start with a simple example.
If you have the number line in mind, we immediately get a lot of subsets.
For example the interval that starts with the number -2 and goes to the number 2.
This set is the neighbourhood of the point x = 0.
However, also it's a neighbourhood of the point x = 1.
The only important thing here is that we find an epsilon, that does not matter how large it is.
It only needs to be positive.
So maybe here in the second case we have to choose a smaller epsilon, than before.
However still, the only thing we need is that we find such an epsilon
and we do not find such a number, if the point x is given by 2.
Of course 2 is an element of this set, but an epsilon-neighbourhood around it lies not in the set.
No matter how small the epsilon is, we always find a part of the epsilon-neighbourhood that lies outside.
In summary, here we have an example of a set that is a neighbourhood of some elements of it, but for others it's not
and now a nice set, that is for all its members a neighbourhood, we call an open set.
So these nice sets will get a special name.
Later we will see, it's much better to work with open sets, than just with sets.
Ok, now any subset of the real numbers is called open or more precisely open in R,
if for each point x in M, M is a neighbourhood of this point.
Hence such boundary points like this one, are not in the set M itself.
Equivalently for the definition you could avoid the notion neighbourhood and just use the epsilon-neighbourhoods.
So this means for all x in M, there exists an epsilon greater than 0, such that B_epsilon(x) is a subset of M.
Of course we can also visualize that on the number line.
So for example here, these 4 parts could be our set M
and then you can just pick any x from this set and then in the case that M is open, you find a small interval around this point
that is completely inside the set M.
Hence in this picture, these boundary points here can't be a part of the set M.
Otherwise it would not be an open set.
Now on the other hand a set that contains all these possible boundary points gets also a special name.
Such a set A we call closed or more concretely closed in R.
The definition just reads that the complement of A, A^c is an open set.
For example the interval from before as a closed set, because the complement outside is an open set.
Now one important thing you should really note here is that open is not the opposite of closed.
For example a set could be neither open nor closed
or the other way around, it could be open and closed at the same time.
Ok, maybe that's a good time to look at some examples.
Let's start with the simplest subsets you can imagine.
Namely the empty set and R itself.
Of course they are both open, because the condition we have here for openness is immediately fulfilled.
For example for the empty set we don't have any problem, because there are no elements in the set at all
and on the other hand for the real numbers we don't have any problem, because all intervals are subsets of the real number line.
However now we also know, they are both closed.
Simply, because the empty set is the complement of the real numbers and vice versa.
Ok, the next example we have already discussed. An interval of this form is closed, but not open.
Therefore we often call such intervals, closed intervals.
Of course then the next example would be an open interval.
So that's good to know. When we use parentheses here we get an open set.
However in this case it's not a closed set, which you can prove.
Ok and in the last example here I want to mix the brackets
and in this case we don't have any of the 2 properties.
It's neither open nor closed.
Ok, so you see these 2 definitions here are not so complicated at all.
But please keep in mind, a subset of the real numbers could be much more complicated than just an interval.
In order to deal with such sets the next fact is very helpful.
It gives us a criterion to check closeness with the help of sequences.
Namely a set A is closed if and only if for all convergent sequences a_n with the property that all the sequence members lie inside the set A,
we have that the limit lies also in A.
To put this in other words it's not possible to leave the set with sequences from the inside.
Also here it might be helpful to look at an example.
Here on the the number line let's take the interval that starts with 0 and ends with 2.
Here the number 2 lies inside the interval, but 0 does not.
Hence we are not able to leave the interval from the inside to the right.
For example we could take such a sequence, which is convergent, but then it would have the limit 2.
It's not possible to get the limit outside.
However on the left-hand side it's indeed possible.
For example we could take the sequence 1 over n.
It's a convergent sequence, where all the sequence members lie inside A.
However, the limit here is 0. Which is not an element of A.
Hence the conclusion is: this set is not closed.
Ok, now you should know the definition of open sets and closed sets.
Therefore you are ready for the next definition about compact sets.
It's a little bit more complicated, but because you already know sequences, we can use them to describe the definition.
So we call a subset of the real numbers A, compact.
If for all sequences a_n, again all the members should lie inside a set A,
we find a convergent subsequence, where the limit lies in A.
So you should see, this is different to the property of closeness from before.
Indeed here you could say a compact set enforces clustering inside it.
Each sequence inside the set needs to have a cluster point, an accumulation value inside the set.
Now, if you compare this definition to the property of a closed set from before, with the sequences you see, this here requires much more.
Hence you can already keep in mind, a compact set is necessarily closed.
However not the other way around.
Maybe you can immediately find a set that is closed by our definition, but not compact with this definition.
Ok, then in the next video I will show you how we can describe these compact sets in simpler terms.
This is called the Heine-Borel theorem.
Therefore I hope I see you there and have a nice day. Bye!