Hello and welcome back to real analysis
and as always many, many to all the nice people that support this channel on Steady or Paypal.
In today's part 14 we will talk about the Heine-Borel theorem.
In order to understand this, we first have to recall what a compact set is.
Here I can tell you, the definition we use for a compact set other people call sequentially compact.
It just means that we use sequences to describe compactness.
Now please recall that any subset A of the real numbers is called a compact set,
if it forces any sequence to cluster.
So a sequence with members in A has at least one accumulation value.
However, the important thing is that this accumulation value also has to lie inside the set A.
Also please note here,
this is a short formulation for saying that we have a sequence of real numbers, where each member is an element of the set A.
Ok, so we know the definition, therefore we now can look at examples
and I would say we start with the simplest one.
The empty set does not have any elements. Therefore this claim here is trivially true.
Hence the set is compact.
Similarly we can take another small set, so a set with just one element.
This one is also compact, because there is only one possible sequence.
In this case we have the constant sequence 5 with accumulation value 5.
Ok, so this was not so hard.
Therefore now my question would be: "What is about the largest subset we can choose?"
there we have to look at all sequences of real numbers.
For example I can give you the sequence that increases with n.
So this sequence is divergent to infinity. Therefore there is no accumulation value as an element of R.
Hence we immediately have a set that is not compact.
Next let's look at a closed interval.
Such an interval with real numbers c and d is indeed a compact set.
Ok, so let's try to proof this.
For this let's assume we have a sequence with members inside this interval.
Hence we can immediately conclude that this sequence is bounded from above and bounded from below.
In short we say this sequence is bounded.
However now you know, we can apply a very famous theorem.
Namely the Bolzano-Weierstrass theorem for sequences.
It tells us that a bounded sequence has at least one accumulation value
and this one we can call "a" and we know, it's a real number.
Now the only information that is still missing is that "a" is actually an element of our set.
However this is guaranteed, because we already know that such an interval is a closed set.
Here please recall, closed means that we can't leave the set by using sequences from the inside
and with this we have proven that the set is indeed compact.
Hence all intervals of this form we know can just call compact intervals.
Ok, now we are ready for the Heine-Borel theorem.
It tells us that the two properties we used in this proof here, are actually exactly what we need for a compact set.
Hence it's a theorem that is not hard to remember at all.
So for any subset A of the real numbers, we have that it is compact if and only if A is bounded and closed.
It's essential that we have both things here together.
This theorem is a very good result for us, because it tells us that we can substitute the complicated notion of compactness
with the simpler notions of boundedness and closeness.
Ok, so this is the Heine-Borel theorem, which holds for the real numbers and you really should remember it.
For the rest of the video, I would say let's to the proof of it.
Indeed the direction from the right-hand side to the left-hand side, we have already proven.
Of course you remember the only things we needed for the argument above is that A is a bounded set, such that we can use Bolzano-Weierstrass
ans the other thing was that the set is closed.
Which guarantees us that the accumulation value is actually in A.
Therefore only the direction from left to right remains.
Hence assume that our set A is compact.
Now for showing the closeness we take any convergent sequence in the set A
and let's call the limit for the moment "a" tilde.
First we only know that the limit is a real number.
If we can show that it is also an element in A, we have shown that a set is closed.
Ok, so at this point we can use that A is compact,
because it tells us that the sequence a_n has an accumulation value
and as before let's call this accumulation value just "a"
and now we already know, a convergent sequence can only have one accumulation value.
Hence our limit "a" tilde is the same as "a"
and therefore also an element in our set A.
So the set A is closed.
Ok, so it remains to show that A is bounded as well
and in order to show this we use a proof by contra position.
More concretely this means that we assume that A is not bounded and want to show that A is not compact.
Now, whenever we have unbounded sets, we can construct the sequence in the set,
such that all sequence member fulfill that the absolute value of a_n is greater than n
and this should work for all natural numbers n
and because of this property such a sequence can't have any accumulation value.
This is not hard to show, but maybe it's a good exercise for you.
Of course the important thing is the result. We have a sequence that has no accumulation value, therefore the set can't be compact.
and that is the proof of the Heine-Borel theorem.
So you see, it's not so complicated, but still the important part is that you remember the theorem.
Ok, then I hope I see you in the next video, when we continue with another topic in real analysis.
Have a nice day! Bye!