Hello and welcome back to real analysis
and first I want to thank all the nice supporters on Steady or Paypal.
In today's part 15 we will talk about infinite sums, also called series.
Indeed this is such an important topic that we will use the next videos to talk about all the details.
Here we just start how we can define infinite sum in a rigorous way
and in the end you will see this is not so new. A series is just a special sequence
and how you deal with sequences, you have already learned here.
Ok, now in some problems it can occur that we need to add up infinitely many numbers.
For example we have the number a_1, then we add a_2, then a_3, a_4 and so on.
To make this shorter you could say, let's use the sum symbol, the capital Sigma, where we go from k = 1 to infinity.
This is then what we call a series. So just adding infinitely many numbers.
So you see this is not so complicated. So let's immediately look at an example.
The only thing we need here is a sequence a_k of real numbers.
Therefore let's take one we already know. Which is -1 to the power k.
So this is a well defined sequence. However not a convergent one.
Nevertheless we still could ask: "What is the infinite sum of this sequence?"
Here we know, we start wit -1 and then we add 1
and then afterwards we add -1 again
and then 1 again, then -1 again and so on.
Of course this is what we can easily calculate, because we can set parentheses here and here and then we see, we just add zeros.
Hence the result of this infinite sum should be 0 as well.
Ok, at this point you should ask: "Why do we set the parentheses in this way?"
Of course there are also other possible ways.
For example we could skip the first element -1 and set the parentheses here.
Then we still add zeros, but what remains is -1.
Ok, now we have 2 different possible results.
So we immediately see such infinite sums here make problems.
So we need to define them and they don't act like normal sums at all,
because in a normal sum we can set the parentheses as we want
and at the moment we don't know in which cases we are allowed to this for an infinite sum as well.
This might be a little bit confusing, because we use the same symbol, but we could have different calculation rules.
Therefore first let's define the symbol in a mathematical way.
So this will be our definition of a series.
For this let a_k be any sequence of real numbers
and then we define a new sequence s_n by setting s_n to be the sum of the first n members of the sequence a_k.
So this is just a normal finite sum.
Hence s_n is a real number as well.
Therefore the whole sequence given by s_n is what we call the series
and now you should see, in the case that this sequence is convergent we have a meaning for the infinite sum.
Therefore we are also able to define the symbol, where we have infinity at the sum here.
So this is simply the limit n to infinity of s_n
or without using a new name you would simply say it's the limit of these partial sums.
Ok, there we have the case that often leads to confusion.
Namely this symbol here is frequently used in 2 different meanings.
On the one hand you can use it for the whole sequence s_n,
because then you don't need to introduce a new name
and on the other hand it's also used for the limit, if it exists.
Therefore please be careful. Sometimes you are allowed to calculate with this symbol as a number,
but other times such a calculation can lead to contradictions.
Ok, so that's the definition and the introduction for a series and in the next video I will show you an example.
Namely the important geometric series.
Hence a good transition would be to rewrite our example from above.
Let's formulate this into the sequence of partial sums.
There a_k is -1 to the power k.
Now let's write the sum here as a sequence with index n.
There for calculating the first member we put in the index n = 1 and get out -1.
Then for the next member we have n = 2. Which means we have -1 + 1 and we get 0
and then for n = 3 we get -1 again.
Then this simply repeats with this pattern
and here you know, this sequence is not convergent.
Ok, maybe for closing this video also another example would be helpful.
Ok, here I want to ask the question: "What happens when we put in +1 instead of -1?"
Of course then the power k does not matter at all, because we always get out 1.
Therefore for our sequence of partial sums we get out 1, then 2, then 3 and so on.
Obviously this is also a sequence that is not convergent.
However we could say it's divergent to infinity.
Now I already told you that in the next video we will talk about the geometric series.
This will generalize these 2 examples, but then we will also get convergent series.
Therefore I hope I see you there and have a nice day! Bye!