Hello and welcome back to real analysis
and as always I want to thank all the nice people that support this channel on Steady or Paypal.
In today's part 16 we will still talk about series
and we have already learned, a series is just a special sequence.
Namely it's simply the sequence of partial sums for a given sequence a_k.
Hence the sum ends here with a new index n.
Now because you already know this definition, you see we don't have a problem when we start a sum with another number, which is not 1.
So depending on the sequence a_k, we can start here with 0, 2 or 3 or even a negative number if it makes sense.
I tell you that because in the next example we have a series that starts with 0.
It's the very important geometric series
and there we sum all the powers of a given number q.
Hence for us first q could be any real number.
However what we want to show now is that this series is convergent if and only if q is less than 1 in the absolute value.
Hence only in this case we get a finite number, when calculating this infinite sum.
Ok, then let's start the calculation.
The overall question is of course, what is our sequence s_n? The sequence of partial sums.
Because when we know this, we can calculate the limit n to infinity.
Indeed there is a nice calculation we can do with this sum, in the case that q is not equal to 1.
Of course this is not a restriction, because if q is equal to 1 we have a very simple sum here.
We just sum up 1's and therefore the series is divergent to infinity.
Ok, now in the case that q is not 1, we can multiply the whole sum with (1 - q).
So we just scale the sequence here with a non-zero number.
Now, the overall idea is that we can expand this expression here and get 2 sums.
The first sum is the same as before and the second has q to the power (k + 1)
and now what we can do is change the index here, such that we have again, q to the power k inside the sum.
This simply means that we start with k=1 and go to n+1
and then you should see, we go exactly through the same numbers.
Ok, such an index shift is very helpful, because now we can subtract the 2 sums here
and the only things that remain are for the first sum, the first index, so k=0
and for the second sum the last index, so k=n+1.
Hence we have q to the power 0, which is by definition 1 and q to the power n+1.
Ok, with this we have a very nice expression for our sequence s_n.
Namely we can just divide by 1-q, which is non-zero and get this nice formula here
and there you should immediately see in which cases s_n is a convergent sequence.
We just have to know if the sequence q to the power n is convergent.
This is what you might already know and it is not hard to show.
q to the power n is convergent if and only if the absolute value of q is less than 1
and in this case we also know the limit, which is 0.
Then this implies that we can actually calculate the limit of this sequence here and as you can see, this is 1 over 1-q.
Hence in summary the value of our series here is well defined for q in the absolute value less than 1 and it is 1/(1-q).
This is such an important formula, such that it gets its own name.
It's called the geometric series and you really should remember it.
Of course you can see that this formula is important, because it got a name.
Therefore I can now tell you there is another series that has a special name.
This one is the so called Harmonic series
and indeed it's an example of a divergent series.
It's constructed by summing up all fractions 1/k.
So we have 1 + 1/2 + 1/3 + 1/4 and so on
and now we will show that this is not convergent, but rather divergent to +infinity.
The first time you see this it might be a little bit surprising, because each number we add gets smaller and smaller.
However the whole sum increases as much as you want and this is exactly what we now want to show.
Therefore let's look again at the partial sums we call s_n.
Here you should see immediately that this is a sequence of positive real numbers, that is also monotonically increasing.
Hence the only thing that remains to show is that this sequence is not bounded.
In order to show this we have different possibilities, but I choose a very simple one.
We will only look at the Indices, where n is a power of 2.
There you will see, this makes everything easier.
In the first step you should see we can rewrite this number as differences.
This means that I can start with s_1 and then I go to s_2, but then I subtract s_1 again.
Hence this whole term is just s_2.
Then we go to s_4 and subtract s_2 again.
In other words this is just s_4 and please recall I just want to use the powers of 2 here.
Therefore in the next step I would use s_8 and subtract s_4 again
and then we continue the whole game until we reach our index 2 to the power m
and of course in this last step we have to subtract the predecessor.
In summary this is just a complicated way to write s with the index 2 to the power m.
However, still this is very helpful, because now we have differences here
and these differences are much easier to estimate.
Of course if you don't like the dots here, we can simply put the whole formula into a sum symbol here.
It has the same information, but now it is compact, but we have to use another index j.
Ok, at this point you should recall that s with an index stands for a partial sum.
So here we subtract 2 partial sums and of course what remains is the middle part of the partial sum.
Ok so let's write that into another line.
Ok, so we know we get out a partial sum, the only thing we have to think about is "what is the start index?" and "what is the end index?"
For this recall that this partial sum wants to the end index 2 to the power j and this end index is smaller than this.
Hence the final index has to be 2 to the power j.
Also we know all indices that are smaller than this or equal will vanish.
Hence the start index has to be 2 to the power (j - 1 + 1).
Of course this looks complicated, because of all the indices involved,
but actually it's not so complicated, because it's just a small part of this sum here.
Therefore maybe for the visualization just imagine that the sum stands for these three numbers here.
Then of course the sum gets smaller when we don't add 1/2 + 1/3 + 1/4, but rather 3 times 1/4 here.
Indeed that's what we can do in general when we put in here for the fraction the largest index.
Now we just have to count how many times we add this constant number here
and when you do this you see we have exactly 2 to the power j-1 terms.
Hence this is the only product we have to calculate now
and because we have chosen the powers of 2 this is not so complicated. It's exactly 1/2.
Now this is an important information, because it tells us that this term here is always greater than 1/2 no matter what j is.
So we have the factor 1/2 m-times. In conclusion here we have our estimate.
The partial sum as with index 2 to the power m is always greater than s_1 + m times 1/2
and of course this is not bounded at all, because when m increases this goes to infinity.
Hence we have shown that the whole sequence of partial sums is not bounded from above.
In combination with the monotonicity we have our divergence to infinity.
Hence there we have our harmonic series, which is a divergent series. So please remember also this important result.
Ok then in the next videos we will talk more about criteria we can use to show the convergence of series
and you will also see that the 2 examples we had here are also very helpful there.
So I hope I see you next time. Bye.