Hello and welcome back to real analysis
and as always first I want to thank all the nice people that support this channel on Steady or Paypal.
In today's part 17 we still talk about series.
More concretely we will use this video and the next ones to talk about criteria we have to check for convergence.
For this please recall that a series is just a sequence of partial sums
and in the case that this sequence is convergent we also use this symbol to denote the limit.
Therefore by applying the well known limit theorems we can write down some properties.
Therefore we take 2 series that need to be convergent
and then we can say something about the series that is given by the sequence a_k + b_k.
So here keep in mind we have a new sequence of partial sums.
Now the result, which is not so surprising, is that this series is also convergent.
We know even more. We can immediately calculate the limit. It's just given by the sum of the two limits.
Of course all of this is just an application of the limit theorems you already learned for sequences
However in this case, when we have convergent series, it tells us that we can pull the addition out of this symbol.
Of course for a normal sum this always works but please keep in mind this symbol here is not a normal sum.
Ok and another property we get from ordinary sums is given by the multiplication.
Namely we have the distributive law when we multiply all the terms in the sum with the same factor.
For a series this means, if the original series is convergent then also this one.
No matter which real number we choose for lambda. Also here this follows immediately from the limit theorems
and we get the calculation rule that we can pull out lambda.
Ok these two properties you really should remember and you should remember that they hold for convergent series.
Therefore a natural question would be: how can we check that a given series is indeed convergent?
In fact there are a lot of different criteria one can apply to answer this question.
The first one I want to show you just uses the completeness axiom of the real numbers.
Therefore it's called the Cauchy criterion.
Please recall in the real numbers being a convergent sequence is equivalent for being a Cauchy sequence
and there the important part was that for a Cauchy sequence we don't have to know the limit.
Therefore this criterion will check for convergence but it does not tell you the limit.
Of course often this is good enough. For example if you just want to justify that you are allowed to use these calculation rules here.
Hence the criterion tells us that the series is convergent if and only if
for all epsilon greater than 0 there exists a capital N,
such that for all indices n and m greater than this capital N, where also n is greater or equal than m,
we have that the absolute value of the partial sum, starting with m and ending with n is less than epsilon.
In other words, if you can show that this expression here is arbitrarily small eventually, then you know the series is convergent
and on the other hand, if you can show that this expression stays large or larger than a given constant,
then you know the series is not convergent.
Ok, before I show you an example let's do the proof of the statement here.
This is not so complicated, because we just have to use the completeness axiom.
First let's define the partial sums as always denoted by s_n.
Then we know the sequence s_n is convergent if and only if it is a Cauchy sequence.
That is exactly what we know as the completeness of the real numbers.
If you don't know anymore what a Cauchy sequence is, let's write down the definition.
It just means that for all epsilon greater 0 there exists a capital N such that for all indices afterwards we can calculate the difference
and then in the absolute value it should be less than epsilon.
Here you see the indices are called n-tilde and m-tilde, just because I want to redefine them in the next step.
You already know, what we want is an expression like this.
Hence now you can see n should be always the larger index here and m-tilde I want to shift by 1.
Hence here we get s_n - s_(m-1).
First you should see this is indeed a special case of the property we had here
and on the other hand you should see it's not a restriction at all, because the only case we really miss is when we have the same index here.
But of course in the case that we have the same index there we always get 0 out, which is always less than epsilon.
Therefore this reformulation for a Cauchy sequence is always allowed.
Ok, now we only have to see that this difference is exactly this sum here.
Hence this is the whole proof of the Cauchy criterion.
Now, as promised let's apply it to an example.
Ok, I would say let's look at the example we had at the beginning of this course.
Of course we already know it's not convergent, but the question would be how can we show it with the Cauchy criterion.
For this we have to calculate this partial sum here.
Now you already know we only need to calculate this for indices n, m that are greater or equal than some capital N.
Therefore maybe let's substitute the m with the capital N.
In other words we look at the special case for m and we can do the same for n.
For example it would be allowed to choose N+2. Therefore the sum consists of exactly three numbers and of course we can calculate them
We just have to distinguish two different cases. The first case would be N is even.
Then we have 1+(-1)+1. Therefore for an even N we get out 1 for the sum. Of course then the absolute value does not change anything
Ok, then the other case would be then an odd N, which means we start with -1, then comes 1 and then we add -1 again.
Hence the result is -1, but with the absolute value it's 1 as well. Hence no matter what N is this expression is always exactly 1.
Which is of course not less than epsilon, if we choose epsilon less than 1.
In conclusion this property here can't be fulfilled for all epsilon.
Indeed now this is all we have to do to show that this series is not convergent.
So here you see the Cauchy criterion as simple as it is, can be very helpful in calculations
and it is also very helpful for showing the next important fact.
Maybe in this example you have already seen, there is a necessary condition for being a convergent series.
Just take any sequence of real numbers a_k and look at the series
and if this is convergent you know the sequence a_k has to be a sequence that converges to 0.
Ok, here you see the contraposition to this is,
if you start with a sequence a_k that is not convergent to 0, the series we get out is divergent.
and of course here you see immediately one example where you can apply this fact.
-1 to the power k is not a convergent sequence at all.
However one important thing to note here is, this is not an equivalence.
Please remind yourself in the last video we have already seen a counter example for this.
Now I can tell you this proof works similarly to the things we did in the example above.
Therefore I think this is a good exercise for you. Try to prove this fact.
Afterwards, then you know every time someone asks you about series and the convergence of it, you should check this thing here first.
However of course most of the time you still don't know if the series is convergent then.
In this case you have to apply another criterion and such another one I show you in the next video.
Therefore I hope I see you there and have a nice day. Bye!