Hello and welcome back to real analysis
and as always first I want to thank all the nice people that support this channel on Steady or Paypal.
In today's part 19 we will talk about the so called comparison test for series.
It's a criterion we can use to decide if a given series is convergent,
but first we need a new definition about convergence.
Namely we call a series given by a sequence a_k, absolutely convergent
if the series given by the absolute value of a_k is simply convergent.
So what you see immediately is that for a series that has only positive a_k's, this is not a new definition at all.
However in general it's a stronger definition.
In other words being absolutely convergent implies being convergent.
Indeed this is not hard to show, we can just use the Cauchy criterion.
Applying this for our series here just means: For all epsilon there is an N, such that for all n, m we have
that this finite sum here is less than epsilon.
Now, in this special case here, we know that the sum is never negative. Therefore we can omit the absolute values around it.
Ok, but know we want to say something about the original series with a_k. So without the absolute value here inside.
Hence what we really want is that this sum with the absolute value outside is less than epsilon.
In order to get this we can just use the triangle inequality for the absolute value.
It just tells us that we can push the absolute value inside the sum, but then we have an inequality.
Now, here we already know from the line above that the right-hand side here is less than epsilon.
So this is our implication and we just get the Cauchy criterion for our original series with a_k.
Hence the series is convergent as well.
Ok, now please remember that we have always this implication here.
However it does not work the other way around.
Indeed that's what we already learned in the last video.
Namely this series here is convergent by the Leibniz criterion.
However it's not absolutely convergent.
We see that immediately, because when we take the absolute value here, we get out the harmonic series.
Ok, now in summary what we have is a stronger notion of convergence
and indeed this is exactly what we need for the comparison test.
Now in fact, this comparison test consists of 2 separate criteria.
The first one is the so called majorant criterion.
If we are able to apply this, we get the absolute convergence out for a series.
Ok, therefore let's fix a series and now I will tell you what we have to check.
We just need another sequence b_k that is larger than the sequence a_k
and of course we put a_k in the absolute value
and we don't need the inequality for all k, but we need it eventually.
Hence for all k after a given index n_0.
So the idea here is that we have another sequence b_k that is well behaved.
In the sense that corresponding series is convergent
and then we can conclude with this inequality that the series corresponding to the absolute value a_k is also convergent.
Therefore our premise is that we find an index n_0 and a convergent series and this series is then often called the majorant
and of course our inequality only makes sense if the corresponding b_k's are non-negative.
Ok and then our conclusion is that our series over a_k is absolutely convergent.
So the idea is here that we can control the whole sequence of partial sums. We simply keep the sequence members small enough.
Now, applications for this nice theorem I show you in the next video.
Here we first should convince ourselves that this is indeed correct and in fact this proof is very short.
We just have to apply our already known Cauchy criterion to the series over b_k.
So this is the same as before. We find epsilon and N and get that this sum is less than epsilon.
However of course we want to say something about this sum. Now you might already know, we can just apply our inequality here.
In other words if we substitute a_k here with b_k, we get a value that is larger or stays the same.
The only small restriction for this calculation is that we have to choose the capital N larger than n_0
and of course it's always possible to do that.
Ok and then on the right-hand side these 2 things here are obviously the same.
In summary now, this number is indeed less than epsilon.
This simply means that the Cauchy criterion holds for the series over the absolute value of a_k.
So we have a convergent series there or to put differently the series over a_k is absolutely convergent.
Ok and with this the whole proof is finished.
Ok, so this was the majorant criterion, but we also have the minorant criterion.
It works similarly, but now we don't check for convergence but for divergence.
Therefore we almost have the same assumptions, but now we only check for series that have a sequence a_k that is non-negative.
So now we can copy almost all things from above, but now we need a divergent series b_k
and then of course the inequality goes the other direction.
Hence now the sequence a_k is simply too large.
Therefore the idea here is, if this series has already the limit infinity,
then the series over a_k, which is larger, should also have the limit infinity.
In conclusion the series is divergent.
Ok, the proof for this theorem is also not so hard. You can just use the majorant criterion.
So you can do a proof by contraposition or if you want by contradiction.
Ok, because it's a very short proof, I think it's a good exercise for you
and then we can close this video with an example for the minorant criterion.
We will show that the series with 1 over square root of k is divergent.
The first thing you should note here is that the square root of k is indeed less or equal than k itself.
Hence the reciprocals fulfill the other inequality.
So 1 over the square root of k is greater or equal than 1 over k
and of course this holds for all natural numbers k
and at this point you see, here we have our minorant, the sequence b_k,
because this gives us the harmonic series and we already showed that this is a divergent series.
Hence if we are able to write down such an inequality, we immediately know that we have a divergent series as well.
The only problem this might give you is that you don't know at the beginning, which minorant or majorant you should choose.
Therefore in the next video I'll show you some criteria that help you exactly there,
but still if you know what to do, the minorant and the majorant criterion can be very helpful.
Ok, then I hope I see you in the next video. Bye!