Hello and welcome to
Real Analysis part
25.
And first, I want to thank
all the nice supporters on
Steady or paypal.
In this video.
Today, we will talk about
the uniform convergence of
a sequence of functions.
In order to understand this,
please first recall that
we call a sequence of functions
pointwisely convergent to
another function F
if for all points X tilde,
we have the convergence of
the values at this point.
This means that in this
formulation with the quantifiers,
you are allowed to choose
different capital NS depending
on X tilde.
And indeed, this is the only
thing we will change to get
the uniform convergence.
So we call a sequence of
functions uniformly
convergent to F
if for all epsilon
greater than zero, there
exists a capital N such that
for all indices N
greater or equal than N
and for all points x tilde
in I, we have that
the distance between the
values is less than
epsilon.
So you see this quantifier
from before is pushed to
the right, of course.
Therefore, this looks similar.
But now this capital
N works uniformly
for all points X tilde.
Of course.
Therefore, this looks similarly.
But now this capital N
here works uniformly
for all points X tilde in
I that's different from
before because here you
could choose capital N
depending on X tilde.
So there could be different
capital Ns here.
However, for the uniform
convergence, this N here
has to work for all x tilde
at the same time.
And exactly this is the reason
we call it the uniform
convergence.
And please keep in mind this
new order for the quantifier
changes a lot.
Let's visualize that in a
picture.
So here you see the graph
of the function F which is
our limit function.
Now if you fix one point
X tilde on the X axis,
this inequality here tells
us that the, value f_n(x tilde)
lies somewhere in this
region.
So we have our epsilon here
and here.
However, we also know this
inequality here should hold
for all X tilde.
Hence we have to move this
region here through all the
points.
In other words, what we get
is such an epsilon tube
around the graph of the
function F.
So the graph of the function
FN needs to lie
inside this epsilon tube.
And of course, also the graphs
of the functions in the sequence
that come after this capital
N.
This is exactly what the
uniform convergence tells
us.
So you immediately see this
is more than we had for the
pointwise convergence.
And also this picture tells
us that it should be possible
to measure a distance between
two functions.
By having this distance.
You can see that the uniform
convergence is indeed very
natural for this,
we first should look at the
picture again, let's
take two functions and their
graphs.
Now the question is how can
we measure a suitable distance
between both functions?
Or in other words, when would
you say that the functions
are close to each other?
Of course, what you already
know is that for each point
X tilde, we can measure the
distance of the values.
So what you have to calculate
is the absolute value as
before.
So if we call the point,
just X, we have F of X
minus G of X and then
the absolute value.
And of course, as before,
we could do that for all
the points X form the domain
I there, you see,
we find small distances
but also larger ones.
And indeed the largest one
we would find if we take
the maximum of these numbers
here.
However, because we don't
know if the maximum really
exists, we should take the
supremum.
Hence this number here tells
us in fact how close
the two graphs are.
So we have a distance measure
for two functions
and usually we just call
it the supremum norm.
The common short notation
for this would be two bars
left and right, and the
infinity symbol as an
index.
And then we have F minus
G inside.
So this is the supremum norm
of F minus G.
Now, as promised with this,
we can rewrite the uniform
convergence definition.
It simply means that the
supremum norm gives us a
sequence that goes to zero.
So FN minus the limit
function F measured in the
supremum norm goes to
zero when N goes to
infinity.
So we started with a sequence
of functions.
But what we got here is an
ordinary sequence of
numbers.
Therefore, this is also the
ordinary convergence for
a sequence of real numbers.
OK.
Now, after all these
definitions, let's look at
an example.
So maybe we should take one,
we already discussed in the
last video there we had
some simple functions that
got steeper and steeper here
until the pointwise limit
was this function.
We want to calculate a little
bit.
Therefore, let's say this
value here is minus
one and the one above is
one.
What we will see now is that
we have the pointwise convergence
but not the uniform
convergence.
Therefore, what we should
look at is the distance between
FN and F in the
supremum norm.
Indeed, this is what we can
immediately calculate when
we look at the jump.
So here we have the jump
of our limit function F.
Now it does not matter which
of the functions from our
sequence we choose
because all of them are
connected from bottom to
top.
Hence, you can always just
take the middle point here
and measure the distance
to the limit function,
which is by our given values
here, always one.
Hence, we don't need to calculate
anything.
We immediately know the supremum
norm is always greater or
equal than one.
And we don't need anything
more because we immediately
know we can't have this
converted to zero
because this distance does
not get smaller than one.
Now, this simple example,
without much calculation
directly gives us the following
result.
Having the pointwise convergence
does not tell us that we
also have the uniform
convergence.
However, it's also a nice
result and not hard to show
that we have the other implication.
Hence, the uniform convergence
is indeed stronger than the
pointwise convergence.
And for us, the uniform
convergence will be very
important later because it
conserves nice properties
of functions.
For example, it conserves
continuity we will
define later.
That's something that just
a pointwise convergence can't
do.
However, one property you
already know is the bounded
of functions.
And the uniform convergence
also conserves this
property.
This means if you have a
sequence of bounded functions
and they converge
uniformly, then the
limit function is also
bounded.
OK.
All details about these
properties we will discuss
in the next videos.
Therefore, I hope I see you
there and have a nice day.
Bye.