Hello and welcome to real
analysis.
And as always, first, I really
want to thank all the nice
people that support this
channel on study or pay pal.
And now in today's part
32 we will talk about the
intermediate value theorem
there.
As before what we will need
is a continuous function.
F as usual
we call the domain of the
function here just by eye.
However, now
actually we need an
interval.
So let's write it as A B
where A and B are included
in the domain.
In this case, we can draw
a very nice compact picture
for the graph of the function.
For example, the grave could
look like this where we have
the interval A B on the X
axis.
And now you should see on
the Y axis, we also
find an interval.
In this case, we find F of
A at the bottom and F of
B at the top.
However, of course, it could
be the other way around.
Now, the intermediate value
theorem tells us that for
all values Y in this
interval, we find a
corresponding X.
So you could say all intermediate
values are hit by the
function, the function
simply cannot escape here
if it starts here and ends
there because it's
continuous and it cannot
make any jumps.
Therefore, the intermediate
value theorem gives a meaning
to the sentence that the
graph of a continuous
function can be drawn in
one stroke.
OK.
Then let's formulate this
nice theorem
here.
I can tell you the intermediate
value theorem is one of the
most important theorems you
learn in analysis.
Now what we have to put in,
we already know we
only need two assumptions.
Firstly, F should be a
continuous function defined
on the interval A B.
And secondly, we take any
number Y on the Y axis in
this interval.
OK.
If we want to be precise,
we write down both intervals.
The one where we start with
F of A and the other one
where we start with F of
B just depending which
of the two numbers is the
smaller one.
For example, in our picture,
we can set why through this
point.
And then the intermediate
value theorem tells us there
is a corresponding X, we
call X tilda.
It's an element of the interval
A B and it is sent to
Y by F.
So F of X tilde is
equal to Y.
OK.
So this is the intermediate
value theorem we'll prove
today.
But before we do that, I
present you kolo you really
should remember.
It tells us that the image
of the interval A B
where we denote the image
with the square pockets as
well is also an
interval.
More concretely it's the
interval that starts with
the minimum of the function
F and goes to the maximum
of the function F.
Therefore, you see it's the
same claim as before.
All the intermediate values
are also hi.
OK.
Then I would say we can start
with the proof of the intermediate
value theorem.
In fact, as we will see the
proof is not so complicated,
the first step will be to
normalize the problem in
some sense.
In order to understand this,
let's visualize the curve
of a function again,
this is similar as before
where now, for example, we
have our Y here.
Now when I say we want to
normalize the problem, it
means it would be nice to
have this Y at zero.
And of course, we could just
do that.
So we take the whole function
and shift it to zero.
So simply as that we get
a new function, we could
call G.
Now, what you should see
is that the problem for searching
such next tilde stays
exactly the same.
But now we search for
zeros.
In summary, this is our idea,
we simply define a new
function G and
this is simply F minus
the value Y.
Now, the next normalization
we could do is that it would
be nice if the value at the
right is larger than
the value on the left.
So what we could do is just
mirror the whole graph.
And then we have a new
function which has exactly
this property and
this function we now can
call F tilde.
However, please note here,
we only mirror the graph
if it's needed.
So in the formula, this would
mean F tilde is defined
as minus G.
However, only in the case
that G of A is greater than
zero.
If G of A is less or equal
than zero, we don't have
to do anything.
We can just set F tilde to
G.
OK.
Now let's summarize what
we have here.
First F tilda is of
course, still a continuous
function.
And our value we search for,
we could call why tilda is
just zero.
Moreover, we also know that
we have a minus sign or zero
on the left hand side and
the plus sign or zero on
the right hand side.
Therefore, the activity we
have thrown before is the
correct example we should
have in mind.
OK.
Now, the proof that we follow
will look similar to the
proof we already did for
the Bolzano Vasta theorem,
namely we cut the interval
A B in the middle
and then choose one of the
two intervals here.
And after this, this
projection, we will do
repeatedly.
In conclusion in the end,
we will get a limit here.
The only thing we have to
do in each step is to check
the value F tilt of C
if this one is greater than
zero.
Then our C could be the new
B.
In other words, we will choose
the left interval.
In this case, in the other
case, we would choose the
right interval.
Of course, the overall idea
of this definition is that
we still have the same assumption,
we still have the sign change
from left to right.
This means then that nothing
really changes here, we can
do the same thing again.
Then of course, we would
define B two and A two.
Then afterwards we would
define B three and A three
and so on.
Therefore, in the end, we
get two sequences out.
So we have A and BN.
And by construction, we know
they are called she sequences.
Moreover, we also know that
the intervals get smaller
and smaller.
And indeed, we know that
the length converges to zero,
hence the completeness axiom
and the limit theorems get
us to the result that we
have exactly one limit here.
Now, you might already know
this is exactly the point
we want to call X tilda.
And by construction it's
an element of the interval
A B.
Hence the only question that
remains is what happens with
X tilda when we put it into
the function F tilda.
In order to see this, please
note that the sign change
for the function F tilde
holds for the whole sequence
A and BN.
Therefore, and by the monotonicity
of the limit, we also know
that this property still
holds when we put the limit
in front.
And there you see, we can
use the continuity of the
function of tilda and push
the limit inside.
Then you see, it looks like
this and we can substitute
this limit with X tilde.
So what we get out is a number
F tilt of X tilde which
is less or equal than zero
and greater or equal than
zero.
Hence, the only possibility
is that this number is
exactly zero.
And there you see indeed
we have solved the problem
for our function F tilde.
Also, you should see it's
not a problem at all to go
back to our original function
F because you
immediately see the X tilda
we found is also a
zero for the function G.
This simply holds by the
definition of the function
F tilde as a flip when we
need it.
However, the function G was
defined by F minus
Y and because this
is now zero, this
implies F
of X tilde is
indeed Y
and that's exactly what we
wanted to show.
So the intermediate value
theorem is proven.
OK.
Then I would say please remember
this important the om and
then I see you in the next
video.
Have a nice day and bye.