Hello and welcome back to
real analysis.
And first many, many thanks
to all the nice supporters
on steady or paypal.
Now, in this video today,
you will get to know some
important continuous
functions.
Some of them are so important
that they are often called
elementary functions.
Indeed, all of them we will
consider again later when
we differentiate and
integrate.
Hence, let's immediately
start with the most important
one.
The exponential function
we shorten the name with
X and the domain is the whole
real number line.
And we have already learned
in the former video that
it is defined by a series,
namely we have X to the power
K divided by K
factorial.
And now you might already
know at the point X is equal
to one, we find the
so-called Euler number.
Also it's possible to show
that this number can be defined
by another sequence
namely by the limit one
plus one over N to the
power N which is
roughly
2.718.
Now this exponential function
shouldn't be new to you because
we have already discussed
it in part 22
there, we have shown the
fundamental multiplicative
identity for the exponential
function which
translates the addition
inside into a
multiplication outside.
And because we have this
property, we can immediately
explain the name
exponential for this function.
For example, if we have X
of two, we can
write this as X of one
plus one
which is by our fundamental
multiplicative identity here
exactly X of one
times X of one.
So it's Euler number
squared.
So you see the left here
and the right hand side are
the same.
And indeed, we can show that
in general, the exponential
function X of X is
exactly Euler number to the
power X.
Therefore, the name makes
sense because we can rewrite
a function such that we have
the exponent here.
And of course, we can show
even more properties of this
important function here.
The first part might not
surprise you.
The exponential function
is a continuous function.
So it's continuous at all
points in R.
Then the next property is
that this function is at
all points increasing
more concretely, we would
say the exponential function
is strictly monotonically
increasing, which simply
means if we look at two points
X and Y where Y is
greater than X, then also
the values fulfill the same
inequality.
So X of Y is greater
than X of X.
In addition, we can also
say what happens in the limits
X to infinity and X
to minus infinity
for plus infinity, we
exceed all bounds.
Therefore, we go to plus
infinity.
However, for minus infinity,
it's different because we
stay positive the whole time
we reach zero in the limit.
OK.
So these are the important
properties you really should
remember for the exponential
function.
Now, one important conclusion
here is what we will need
for the next example.
Namely now you are able to
show if we change the codomain
to zero
infinity.
So the interval of the positive
numbers, then we
get a bijective map.
Indeed, that's not hard to
show when you know all the
other things here.
And of course, now you already
know a bijective map has
an inverse map.
And this inverse is what
we usually call the logarithm
function.
So you see this is a simple
definition and then we can
ask the question, what are
the properties of the logarithm
function?
And of course, not so surprising,
we can deduce a lot of
properties from the exponential
function.
So maybe let's look at the
graphs to see what we already
have.
So in blue, you see the graph
of the exponential function
and then we reflect it where
the mirror line is this
diagonal here.
Please recall this reflecting
follows immediately by the
definition of the graph and
the inverse function
HC.
And we, you find the graph
of the logarithm function.
Now what we see is that the
logarithm function is also
strictly monotonically
increasing and it should
still be continuous.
Indeed showing these two
things is a very good exercise.
First, you show the increasing
part and then you use the
epsilon delta criterion to
show the continuity.
OK.
However, the most important
property for the logarithm
function follows immediately
from the fundamental multiplicative
identity for the exponential
function.
OK.
Now, because the logarithm
function is the inverse function,
this identity goes the other
way around.
So the product inside gets
translated to the sum
outside.
OK?
I can tell you this identity
is very important.
So please remember it.
Now, with this, we go to
our next examples which are
polynomials
for them.
I don't have to tell you
a lot because you already
know them.
The important part here is
the domain of a polynomial
is the whole real number
line and defined as it by
giving finitely many coefficients
A.
And in the case that the
last one am here is
nonzero.
We say that the polynomial
has to create M as a
reminder, we have already
showed that the polynomials
are continuous functions.
So nothing new here.
But we need to know the polynomials
to define the next class
of examples
here.
Please recall for a
polynomial and important
ingredient was that we have
a highest power M here.
If we don't want to have
that, we get something we
call a power series.
In fact, this is a very general
term where we already know
one example,
namely the exponential function
from above was defined using
a power series.
Now, in general a power series
does not need to be defined
on the whole real number
line.
So we could have a smaller
domain D.
However, otherwise it looks
like a polynomial where we
have coefficients A K here.
But now we could have infinitely
many.
In other words, for each
sequence A K, we get out
a function we call a power
series.
In this case, the domain
of definition is given by
all the points X in
R that satisfy
that this series is indeed
a convergent one.
And of course, you already
know a lot of criteria you
can use here to check for
convergence.
OK.
Let's immediately discuss
a very famous example here
which means we fix a special
sequence.
A K let's start a
sequence with the zeroth
member which should be
zero.
And then I want one, but
let's write it as one divided
by one factorial,
then afterwards comes zero
again and then
minus one divided by
three factorial.
Then not surprising we have
zero again and then one
divided by five factorial,
then zero and then
minus one divided by
seven factorial.
OK.
With this, I think you see
what the whole wall is and
that you can continue it.
And now this sequence gives
us a power series we usually
call sine of X.
Also, it's not hard to check
that the whole real number
line is the domain D
indeed, a lot of common functions
can be defined with such
a power series.
And for this reason, I give
you here a general result.
Now, for any power series,
given the coefficients A
K, you find the
maximum radius R
where also infinity as a
symbol is possible,
which indeed would be the
best case scenario.
Now, this maximum radius
fulfills that the open interval
from minus R to R lies
completely in the domain
D.
Now I can also tell you we
immediately get that the
power series is a continuous
function on this interval.
So in the best case scenario
like for the sine function,
we have a continuous function
defined on the whole real
number line.
Now even better for the theorem,
we have a formula to calculate
this number R.
Indeed this comes out of
the root criterion for the.
Therefore, we can calculate
the lim sup of the cave
root of the
absolute value of A K.
And this gives us the number
one over R.
And here in this case for
zero and infinity, we
use this symbolic calculation
using this, we have this
formula in general.
OK.
Now this nice formula is
often called the Cauchy Hadamard
theorem.
With this, I would say we've
learned a lot today and we
can start with derivatives
in the next video.
Therefore, I hope I see you
there and have a nice day.
Bye.