Hello and welcome back to
real analysis.
And obviously, as always
first, I want to thank all
the nice people that support
this channel on study or
paypal.
Now we've almost reached
a point in the series where
we can talk about the famous
mean value theorem.
However, before we are able
to prove it, we first have
to talk about local extrema
and the theorem of Rolle.
Hence today, we will do the
whole ground work we will
need for the mean value theorem.
So let's immediately start
with the definition of a
local maximum for
this.
Let's fix an interval I and
a function F.
Now, in order to understand
what we want to define let's
visualize the graph.
So maybe we have something
like this and the
point like this, we want
to call a local maximum
or more concretely, we are
interested in the point X
zero at the X axis.
In this case, you would say
the function F has a local
maximum at this point.
OK.
And now of course, we should
think about what this should
essentially mean.
Now, the value of the function
at this point does not have
to be the maximum of the
function.
However, it should be
maximal when we only consider
a neighborhood around this
point.
Or to be more precise, we
only consider a neighborhood
around the point X zero on
the X axis.
And this one we simply call
you.
So we just need a neighborhood
in the real numbers.
And if you want, you can
choose an epsilon neighborhood.
And of course, it just have
to be small enough such that
our condition here holds.
Hence, in the formula, this
would mean that F of X
zero is equal to the
maximum of the function when
we only consider points from
the neighborhood.
Hence, we have X in U
intersected with I
with this intersection, we
also include points that
lie on the boundary of the
interval.
Otherwise it's exactly the
same thing we explained here
in the graph.
And there, you also see we
can do the same thing for
a local minimum.
Therefore, I would say let's
add this to our definition.
So we say the function F
has a local minimum at the
point X zero.
If there is a neighborhood
of X zero also called
U such that F of X
zero is the minimum of the
function when we restrict
it to the neighborhood U.
So you see it's exactly the
same definition as before,
just with a minimum.
Then finally, we have the
last part of the definition
which is about local
extrema.
In fact, this is just a name
to combine both maximum and
minimum from before.
Hence we say F has a local
extrem at X zero, if
F has a local maximum or
a local minimum at X zero.
So you see this is not complicated
at all, but maybe I still
show you some sketches.
Therefore, here in the coordinate
system, we have our interval
I as a bounded one.
Then for example, the graph
of F could look like this.
And they, you see on the
left boundary we have a local
maximum.
And on the right hand boundary,
we have a local minimum.
Moreover, another local
maximum, we also find here
also another local minimum
we find here.
So please don't forget a
local maximum could look
like this.
But of course, when we deal
with differentiable functions,
something like this cannot
happen.
In fact, for differential
functions, we have a very
nice necessary condition
for local extrema.
So let's put this into a
proposition.
However, we don't have this
condition for boundary points.
Therefore, I immediately
choose an open interval as
the domain.
Now our assumption here is
that at the point X zero,
we are interested in the
function is differentiable.
And then we have the following
implication if
F has a local extremum at
x zero, so a local maximum
or minimum, then
F prime of X zero
is equal to zero.
So the derivative has to
vanish at this point.
Now please immediately note
here, this does not work
the other way around.
Now, both things we can immediately
explain in a picture.
For example, if we have a
local maximum here, the
slope at the point if it
exists needs to be zero.
So we have a tangent that
is horizontal.
However, this horizontal
tangent can't be sufficient
for a local extremum
because we also have it at
this point for such a curve.
And there at this point,
we don't have a local minimum
and also not a local
maximum.
Therefore, please always
have this direction here
in mind.
OK.
Then I guess we are ready
for the proof of this statement.
And there we will distinguish
two cases,
namely, we first consider
that F has a local maximum
at X zero.
And then obviously the second
case will be that F has a
local minimum at X zero.
OK.
Then by the definition of
a local maximum, we can
conclude that there is a
neighborhood of X zero.
We call you
here.
Very importantly, to note
is because we have an inner
point, we can choose the
neighborhood inside the interval.
AB otherwise we have the
same property here, namely
F of X zero is the maximum
of the function when we only
consider points from the
neighborhood.
Now, in the next step, what
we can put in is that the
function F is differentiable
at our point X zero.
This means we have a
linearization around this
point in general.
This means we can write F
of X as F of
X zero plus X minus X
zero times our slope function
delta.
And here please recall the
important property for differentiability
is that this function
here is continuous at the
point X zero.
This is not what we can use
to show that the slope at
X zero is zero.
Intuitively.
It makes sense that we have
it because if we would have
a tangent with a positive
slope, then we cannot have
a local maximum here because
the value will increase when
we go to the right.
Therefore, let's try to
prove this.
So we assume that at the
point X zero, the function
delta which is the
derivative is greater than
zero.
Now, since we have continuity,
we also know the function
is greater than zero in a
small neighborhood around
X zero, let's call the
neighborhood V.
And of course, we can choose
it as a subset of U.
Now, this is the important
property we can use to construct
the contradiction as a
reminder.
Another way to interpret
this property here is to think
of secants.
If the slope of the tangent
is positive, then you also
find a small neighborhood
around X zero such that the
slopes of the secants is
positive as well.
However, now if we have this,
we cannot have a maximum
at X zero, you immediately
see this in the picture because
on the right hand side of
X zero, we find larger
values than at the point
X zero.
We can also show this when
we use our identity here
because here, if X is in
the neighborhood V we
have a positive number.
And if we choose X on the
right hand side of X zero,
this is also positive number.
In summary, all points X
in the neighborhood fulfill
that F of X is greater
than F of X zero, which
simply means that F of X
zero is not a local
maximum.
OK.
Then let's look at the second
possibility here that F prime
of X zero is less than
zero.
There, you see we can just
flip the picture from before
and do the same argumentation
again.
So we can take a neighborhood
V in you such that we have
the negative slope in the
whole neighborhood.
Now, the only thing we have
to change from before is
that we now look at the left
hand side because then
both factors in the product
on the right hand side are
less than zero.
Hence, the product itself
is positive again,
which gives us exactly the
same contradiction as before.
Therefore, in summary, we
know these two cases here
are not possible at all.
So the only possibility that
remains is that F prime is
exactly zero,
which is exactly what we
wanted to prove.
Now, to finish the proof,
we just have to do this second
case, which means now instead
of a maximum, we consider
that F has a local minimum
at X zero.
However, I don't think I
have to write this down because
now we have all the ideas
and you can do a similar
proof as before.
In fact, what I want to do
in the next minutes is to
show you the important theorem
of Rolle this one is
applicable if we have a differentiable
function on a compact interval.
Now it's important that we
have these two boundary points
A and B because we
need the assumption that
F of A is equal to F of
B.
Now in a picture in a graph,
this would mean we start
here at a given value and
then the function can do
a lot of things, but we end
at the same value again,
then the claim will be that
we find at least one point
where we have a horizontal
tangent and this point
on the X axis we will call
X hat.
In other words, we find X
hat in the interval such
that F prime of X hat is
equal to 01
important part here is that
X hat is not a boundary
point.
So we have an inner point
of the interval.
OK.
I would say Rolle's theorem
here seems very natural.
If we have such a function
like this, there should be
a local minimum or a local
maximum somewhere.
Therefore, let's immediately
try to prove it.
Let's again, start with a
simple case namely that the
function F is constant.
Then of course, it's differentiable
and fulfills the condition
that F of A is equal to F
of B.
But also the derivative is
equal to zero.
And this holds for all X
in the whole interval.
So we can simply choose any
point for X hat and we are
finished.
Hence, the only interesting
case is that F is not a
constant function.
OK.
And now we can use that F
is defined on a compact set.
And by assumption differentiable
which in particular means
it's a continuous function.
And for these, we know the
image of a compact set is
also a compact set.
This is what we have proven
in part 30.
In particular, we have proven
that we always find the point
X minus where the minimum
occurs and the point X
plus where the maximum occurs.
Now, of course, one of the
points could lie on the
boundary.
However, because the function
is not constant, the other
one cannot.
And exactly this one, we
can choose as x hat.
Therefore, this means we
have the maximum or the
minimum in the middle somewhere.
In fact, it's the global
maximum or minimum,
which is of course also a
local one.
Hence, we can simply use
the proposition from before
which tells us that the derivative
vanishes at the local
extremum.
And with this, the proof
is finished.
In fact, this nice theorem
of Rolle we can use in the
next video because
there we will prove the famous
mean value theorem.
Therefore, I hope I see you
there and have a nice day.
Bye.