Hello and welcome back to
real analysis.
And first many, many thanks
to all the nice people that
support this channel on Steady
or paypal.
Now today, in part 41 we
will finally talk about the
famous mean value
theorem.
Indeed, this theorem we can
immediately visualize in
a nice way.
Now I can already tell you
the mean value theorem applies
to all functions that are
defined on a compact interval
and differentiable.
Therefore, let's call the
interval on the X axis
simply A B.
OK.
And now we look at the mean
slope of the function
which is the slope of this
second.
And of course, we can immediately
calculate this by F of B
minus F of A divided by
B minus A.
Now, the claim of the mean
value theorem is that we
also find a tangent with
the same slope.
So in the picture, this would
mean we can push this
sequence until we find the
correct slope
and the corresponding point
in the interval A B we call
X hat all in
all this is already the
whole mean value theorem.
In other words, at this point,
we are ready to formulate
it the only assumption we
need here is a differentiable
function FF should be
defined on a compact interval.
So we choose it as a B.
And of course, the whole
thing only makes sense if
A is strictly less than B,
then the claim is there exists
a point x hat in the
open interval.
So indeed, we find an inner
point and for this
point, we have the property
that F prime of X hat
is exactly the mean
slope.
So you see the whole theorem
is very easy to formulate.
And therefore also to
remember, you can simply
say the second slope is
given by some tangent slope
in the middle.
However, please note here,
the statement of the theorem
is the existence not the
uniqueness.
So it's definitely possible
that you could have many
X hats with this property.
For example, for constant
function F you immediately
see this.
OK.
Then let's use the next minutes
to prove the mean value
theorem.
And of course, we will need
Rolle's theorem from the last
video.
Indeed, we can immediately
apply it in the case that
F of A is equal to F of
B.
Because in this case, Rolle's
theorem tells us there is
an X set in the open interval
A B such that the derivative
at this point is exactly
zero.
However zero is in this
case, the mean slope.
Hence, in this case, we have
already proven the mean value
theorem.
Therefore, the idea for the
proof would be to formulate
the general case such that
we can use this special case
here.
Indeed, this is not hard
at all when we have the picture
in mind.
So in dark blue, we have
the function F and light
blue gives us the second.
And now we want to push this
value here to the same level
as this value.
Therefore, in the picture,
this point should go down
exactly by the amount given
by the second.
So you see the overall idea
is simply to subtract the
sequence from the function.
Then the result is that both
points lie at zero
and we have a new function
we can call G.
Now, the important thing
here is that the new function
G is still differentiable
because it's a difference
of two differential functions.
And moreover, it's still
defined on the interval.
Ab Now the definition we
described in the picture
is here given in this formula
which is exactly what we
wanted.
The function F minus the
second.
So here we have the constant
slope times X minus a
point A plus F at
this point A.
And of course, here A is
the left bound of the interval.
OK.
Here because G is still
differentiable, we can calculate
the relative, of course,
you can apply the sum rule.
So we have F prime minus
the slope of the second.
So here you see we are already
very close to the mean value
theorem.
Now the only thing that is
left to do here is to apply
Rolle's theorem.
Please recall before we could
use it in the case that the
left value is equal to the
right value.
And then we found a middle
point such that the derivative
is zero there.
However, now we are in the
case that F of A is not
equal to F of B,
but we shifted the whole
problem such that G
fulfills what we want.
If you don't believe it,
put A and B into the
definition and you see it
hence, now we can apply Rolle's
theorem and find a point
X hat where the derivative
is zero.
However, vanishing the relative
for G means that this
expression is equal to zero.
So we simply bring F prime
to the other side.
So not so surprising we found
our mean value theorem.
And indeed this is the whole
proof.
OK.
Then for the end of the video,
let's look at an application
of this nice theorem.
Again, let's take a function
F defined on a compact
interval.
And of course, it should
be differential.
Now assume that we know that
the derivative is positive
no matter which point X we
put in.
Then we can look at two arbitrarily
chosen points X one and X
two, where X two is greater
than X one, then we
can apply the mean value
theorem where we shrink the
domain to the interval X
one X two.
This means that we find our
point X hat in the open
interval X one X two.
And as before, at this point,
we find the mean slope,
then we can just multiply
X two minus X one on both
sides and get this
equality.
Now, we can put in our two
assumptions.
First, we know the derivative
is positive.
And secondly, we know X two
minus X one is positive as
well.
Hence, we can conclude the
left hand side of the equality
is also positive,
which means the value
FX two is greater than the
value FX one.
And since the numbers X one
X two were arbitrarily chosen,
we conclude that the function
F is increasing or
more concretely, we would
say F is strictly
monotonically increasing.
Now, indeed, this is a nice
result.
We merely get out of the
mean value theorem.
So in short, we can simply
say if the derivative is
always positive, we get out
a function that is at all
points increasing strictly
monotonically.
And of course, with a similar
proof, we can also look at
cases with a negative derivative.
This case might not surprise
you.
We simply get out that the
function is strictly monotonically
decreasing.
Then in addition, we can
also look at the cases where
we don't have the strict
inequality.
This means if you look at
the proof, we will also lose
the strict inequality here.
Otherwise the proof works
exactly the same.
However, since we lose the
strict inequality.
We just have functions that
are monotonically increasing
or decreasing.
OK.
With this, we now have a
common application for
derivatives when we want to analyze
functions.
And of course, this will
come in handy a lot later.
Therefore, I really hope
I see you in later videos.
Have a nice day and bye.