Hello and welcome back to
real analysis.
And you already know as always
first, I want to thank all
the nice people that support
this channel on study or
paypal.
Now, in today's part 45
we will talk about a very
famous theorem namely
Taylor's theorem.
This one is very important
for a lot of applications
and you might have already
heard the term Taylor
polynomial.
In fact, the overall idea
here is not hard to understand
because it's about an
approximation method.
Therefore, what you should
imagine here is the graph
of a function that is a few
times differentiable.
And then one will fix one
point in the domain.
And as often it's called
X zero.
Now around this 0.1
wants a local approximation
for the function.
And for this reason, this
point X zero is often called
the expansion point.
OK.
Now I already told you we
want an approximation around
this point and this should
be given by a polynomial.
In fact, you already know
the simplest one given by
the tangent.
Please recall this is the
linear approximation we
introduced in the definition
of the derivative.
In other words, here we have
a polynomial with decree
one.
Indeed.
Now Taylor's theorem
generalizes this fact to
polynomials with higher decrease.
Hence, in the picture, with
the next step, we would have
a parabola.
And in the same way as the
tangent was the best linear
approximation, this
parabola should be the best
quadratic approximation.
Now what this exactly
means we have to describe
with a formula.
Therefore, let's first recall
the best linear approximation
we defined with the derivative.
In order to do this, we will
introduce a new variable,
we call h, should be
a small number we add to
X zero.
In this sense, the point
X zero plus H will be
our point X.
Indeed often this h makes
the whole formulation a little
bit simpler.
Now, what we find by the
definition of the derivative
is that F of X
zero plus h
given by F of X zero
plus F prime of X
zero times h
plus a remainder term
R of h times h.
Now here when you compare
to our original definition
of the derivative, you see that
h now plays the role of
X minus X zero.
Hence, in this formulation,
the linear term here is
easy to recognize.
OK.
Now, one important property
missing here is that R of
H goes to zero
when H goes to zero.
In fact, this is the proper,
that makes the tangent the
best linear approximation.
OK.
Now, maybe not so surprising
in a similar way, we can
write down a quadratic
approximation.
Of course, the linear term
here should not change.
But now we want to add a
term with squared.
And as we will see soon,
the best quadratic
approximation is then given
with one half times F
prime prime of X
zero times H squared.
And in a similar way as before,
we have a remainder term,
which is not the same, but
we still call it r.
But now we have it here
with h squared.
Moreover, please don't forget
that.
Speaking of an approximation,
this still means that this
function r goes to
zero when h goes to
zero.
OK.
And now it might not surprise
you that we can generalize
this approximation to
polynomials with higher degree
when we have enough derivatives.
And exactly this idea
leads to Taylor's theorem.
Therefore, let's formulate
it.
So the only thing we need
is a function defined on
an interval.
I hence,
let's call it F as
before.
Now, we already know we need
enough derivatives.
Therefore, let's assume that
the function F is N plus
one times different.
The reason why this plus
one is helpful you will see
in a minute.
OK.
And as before we also fix
an expansion point X zero.
Now, the claim here is that
for any number H we have
such an approximation formula,
namely this means that we
take any from the real number
line such that X zero plus
H still lies in I,
this is important because
only then we can put this
number into the function
F.
Hence, in this case, F of
X zero plus H is given
as a whole sum
of all the derives of the
function F at the point
X zero.
So please keep in mind this
is a real number and we divide
it by K factorial.
OK.
So here you should see we
start with case equal to
zero, which is just a
function F at the point X
zero.
And then we go through all
the derivatives until we
reach the nth one.
Also, you should note that
we don't see the K factorial
at the first two terms here
because for K is equal to
zero and K is equal to
one, we just get the factor
one.
However, at K is equal to
two, we see one half
and this means the next factor
will be 1/6.
OK?
Now you might ask how this
factor comes in and I can
tell you we will see it in
the proof soon.
However, more importantly,
here, I should tell you that
we also have our variable
in namely with H to the
power K.
Hence what we get here is
indeed a polynomial with
degree at most N.
And as we have seen before,
we also have a remainder
term at the end.
And this one, I just want
to denote with a capital
R and in
addition, it gets an index
N, of course, the
whole remainder term also
depends on X zero.
But for us, mainly the functional
relation to h is important.
Therefore, you see, we often
just say ah and of H
for the whole remainder term.
However, the more important
part is the front part.
So the whole polynomial,
in fact, this one is called
the Taylor polynomial or
more concretely the nth
order Taylor polynomial.
OK.
Now, the whole claim here
is not finished yet
because of course, as
before, we can say
something about the remainder
term here.
Indeed, the remainder term
gets better when we have
one derivative more than
we need for the Taylor polynomial.
From this.
It follows that we find an
intermediate point we call
C, this is a
lower case Greek letter
also often called Xi.
Now, the important part is
that this number lies in
between X zero and X
zero plus H.
This means that if we want
to write this as an interval,
we have to distinguish two
cases.
It just depends which of
the two numbers here is bigger
than the other one.
So we don't know the exact
value of the number C here,
but we know the range of
it.
However often this is
enough for an estimate of
the remainder term are and
of h.
And in fact, the formula
for the remainder term is
so easy to remember
because it looks exactly
like the last term in the
Taylor polynomial.
More concretely, the number
of the derivative is N plus
one and we divide by
N plus one factorial.
In addition, at the end,
we have to the power N
plus one.
However, we find the
difference and this is the
only one we don't
evaluate the function at
the point X zero.
But now at the point
C OK,
there we have it.
This whole thing is the famous
Taylor formula which holds
for every function F
which is often enough
differentiable.
And maybe I should tell you
sometimes you also see it
in a different form.
This happens when one is
interested in a Taylor polynomial
but not in the explicit
calculation for the remainder
term.
Then one just writes
plus big O of
h to the power and plus
one, it just
reminds us that here in the
remainder term
occurs with the power N plus
one.
But we don't care how big
the constant here is.
Now, this curved O here is
what we call a Landau symbol.
And at the moment, we just
use it as a shortcut for
the whole remainder term
here.
However, later, I will tell
you a little bit more about
this symbol and related
ones.
OK.
Now, for the end of the theorem,
let me show you once again
another formulation for this
formula here.
This happens if you don't
want to use the variable,
but rather just to point
X in the interval I,
then of course, all the
constants are the same.
But now we have the factor
X minus X zero.
And obviously we also need
the power K here.
So now you see there is no
difference at all.
It just depends which variables
you want to use in your problem.
However, here please note
both things, either with
variable H or with variable
X are called the nth order
Taylor polynomial.
OK.
Then I would say in the next
videos we can discuss
examples applications
and also the proof of this
nice theorem here.
Therefore, I hope I see you
there and have a nice day.
Bye.