Hello and welcome back
to real analysis.
And as always, first, I want
to thank all the nice people
that support this channel
on study or paypal.
Now, as you can see, we've
reached part 48 in the
series.
And now we will start talking
about the Riemann integral.
Indeed, this will be the
last chapter we will cover
in this series about real
analysis.
You will see this notion
of an integral is as
important as the one we
already introduced.
Also this idea can be
nicely visualized with the
graph of a function.
So here you see the graph
of the function F which should
be defined on the interval
A
OK.
Now you might already know
the integral of the function
F is the orientated
area between the
graph and the X axis.
We say orientated
because there could be a
sign involved
more precisely.
This means that the parts
that are above the X axis
are positive and the parts
that are below the X axis
are negative.
Hence, at the moment for
this picture, it does not
matter because everything
here is above the X axis.
So we have a positive area.
OK.
But then the question is
how can we calculate this
area?
Then now I can
already tell you the overall
idea is that we approximate
it with rectangles.
Indeed, the procedure for
the Riemann integral is that
one chooses points on the
X axis and then draws
rectangles above them.
So you should see if we look
at one rectangle here, we
already have the width and
the height is then given
by one value of the function
F inside this
interval.
For example, the picture
then could look like this
where we have six rectangles.
And of course, the area of
a rectangle can be
calculated in a simple way.
It's just the width times
the height.
And then we just have to
sum up all the areas of the
rectangles to get an
approximation of the area
we are interested in.
Hence, when we give the points
here a name on the X axis.
So maybe it's simply X one
X two and so on.
Then the width of this
rectangle here is simply
X three minus X two.
So in general, we can just
write xj minus xj-1
.
And then in order to get
the area of the rectangle,
we have to multiply with
the height
for this the point, we choose
an interval to get the value
of the function we call
cj.
Therefore, here you see this
is the area of one
rectangle.
So in the last step, we simply
have the sum of all
these areas.
And in general, we can say
we have N rectangles that
are involved here.
OK.
Then soon we will see how
we can do a limit process
and to infinity to get the
actual area.
In fact, instead of the sum,
we will use this long as
as a symbol.
Otherwise, it looks similarly
because F is involved.
And instead of this difference
here, we write DX.
So this is the symbol for
the Riemann integral.
And often we put the bounds
of the interval A and
B at the symbol.
OK.
What you really should remember
here is that for the Riemann
integral, we always start
with a partition of the X
axis.
And then with some procedure
I explain, soon we get to
the definition of the Riemann
integral of a function F
I always specify the name
Riemann here because there
is another important notion
a more modern one which is
called the integral.
Of course, in the end, both
definitions will describe
the same thing, namely the
orientated area between the
graph and the X axis.
However, it turns out that
the la back integral works
more generally, which means
you can apply to more functions.
But since the Riemann is
not hard to explain, it's
good to start with it.
If you are interested in
the Lebesgue integral, I have
a whole other series about
it.
OK.
However, here we will explain
the Riemann integral which
means we have to start with
the partition of the X axis.
More precisely, we will define
the name partition of the
compact interval A B.
Now you have already seen
above it's simply a set that
consists of points we choose
inside the interval.
Indeed, what one often does
is to include the boundary
points A and B as well.
Therefore, we start at the
point X zero, then comes
X one X two and
so on.
And the last point should
be XN.
So you see it should be a
finite set
and the defining property
of the set you also see
above.
So we have an order of the
points.
Hence X zero is the smallest
one, then comes X one and
so on.
So we have strict inequalities
here and
also X zero should also
be A and XN
should be B
OK.
So this is the whole definition
of the notion partition
of an interval.
Now for such a partition
and a function F, we could
calculate this sum here.
However, because this could
be hard, we should first
start with functions F that
are not so complicated.
In fact, the functions we
now consider are usually
called step functions
to make everything simpler
to read.
I now use Greek letters
for the step functions.
So here we have a lower case
phi so the
function should be defined
on the interval A B and we
call it a step function if
it's piece wisely constant.
This means if we look at
the graph, we only see
horizontal lines.
Therefore maybe let's immediately
visualize this.
For example, maybe the function
starts with one, will you
hear then comes
another value here
and then the next one could
be here.
For example, so you
see it doesn't have to be
a complete constant function.
There could be jumps, there
could be a lot of jumps but
only finally many,
which means for example,
you could restrict it to
an interval maybe here.
And then you have a constant
function,
maybe it's also important
to note here that the
values at the jump points
don't matter at all.
For example, this is allowed
to happen.
And maybe you already know
why this is because the
area below this curve
to the x axis does not
care what this will is.
And of course, in the end,
we will be interested in
this area because it's the
integral.
OK.
Then let's describe this
definition of a piece wise
constant function in a formal
way.
And as you might guess we
can use a partition here for
the interval A B,
this means that the best
idea would be to set these
points X one X two and so
on at these jump
points because
then we have the corresponding
intervals where the function
is constant.
However, then it's also no
problem at all fixing these
constant values.
So let's call them C one
C two and so on.
Indeed, what could happen
is that some values
coincide.
So here we have that the
value in this interval is
the same as in this one.
This is not a problem.
The important thing is that
for each interval, we have
such a number CJ,
which means we have any of
them.
OK.
And now we can write down
the defining property we've
already discussed,
meaning that we can restrict
the function phi to an
interval.
Namely, we can do this for
each interval that starts
with XJ minus one and
ends with XJ.
Indeed, in order to avoid
these jump points here, we
need the open intervals.
OK.
And now we know restricted
to this interval, it's a
constant function
and the value is given by
CJ.
OK.
And of course, every time
you see something like this,
it means it should hold for
all possible values of J.
Well, now you know what we
call a step function when
we want to define the Riemann
integral.
So you see it's not
complicated at all.
Also the integral should
not be complicated because
we immediately see the rectangles
here we could use
and then these rectangles
exactly describe the
area between the graph and
the X axis.
Therefore, my question for
you would be, can we immediately
define the integral for
such a step function?
Please recall this is the
symbol that is a number
that represents the orientated
area.
This means in this case,
we just have to add
all the areas of the
rectangles here.
So we have a sum that starts
with one and goes to N
also we know the height is
given by CJ and
the width is given by the
difference of these two points
here.
So what we see here is in
this case, the integral
is given by this finite
sum.
However, what we need to
answer here is, is this a
correct definition?
Because at first, it seems
that there are a lot of possibilities
to choose the petition of
the interval and also to
choose the numbers CJ.
However, here on the left
hand side, neither the
partition nor the number
CJ occur.
In summary.
What we need to show is that
this here is well
defined.
OK, then please think about
it and then we can talk about
it together in the next video.
Therefore, I hope I see you
there and have a nice day.
Bye.