Hello and welcome back to
real analysis.
And first, I want to thank
all the nice people that
support this channel on Steady
or paypal.
Now, in today's part 49 we
will continue talking about
the Riemann integral.
In particular, we will show
that the integral for step
functions is well defined
for this.
Please recall as step function
phi is defined on a compact
interval and it is piece-
wisely constant.
So a typical graph looks
like this.
So we have constant parts
and some jumps involved.
Therefore, the important
thing for us is that we can
choose a partition for the
interval A B,
the explicit definition of
a partition I gave you in
the last video here.
Please recall it's a finite
set where the elements are
called X with an index.
Now corresponding to such
a partition, we can also choose
numbers, we call C one C
two and so on.
And these are simply the
important values the function
phi can have.
OK.
Then with this, we can
define the integral for the
step function phi
we just calculate the
orientated area of a
rectangle here and sum them
up and then
this finite sum is just
called the integral of Phi
denote it with this
symbol.
Now, the topic for this video
is this proposition here
and it tells us that this
symbol here is well
defined more
precisely, this means no
matter which partition we
choose with this property,
we still get out the same
number.
You see this because on the
left hand side, we don't
mention the partition at all.
Therefore, in the proof,
we just have to consider
two arbitrarily chosen
partitions.
So let's call the first one,
P one and the second
one, P two.
So for P one, let's call
the partition X zero X one
and so on until we reach
the last point XN.
Of course, for P two, we
need different symbols.
Therefore, I would suggest
we take X to the zero.
Otherwise it should look
the same.
So we have X to the one X
to the two and so on, but
the size could be different.
So let's call it m.
In other words, the number
of elements in the two partitions
could be different
here.
Please recall the whole thing
is a decomposition of the
X axis.
So for example, P one, you
could visualize like this.
On the other hand, P two,
you could visualize in the
same way it could look completely
differently.
But of course, it could also
look similarly
and maybe the first case
we should consider would
be that they are very
similar.
However, here, please don't
forget both partitions should
work for our chosen step
function Phi
for the first one, we call
the value CJ.
And for the second one, maybe
DJ.
Of course, in some sense,
the values should be the
same.
But in general, the indices
don't coincide.
The important thing you should
remember here is that the
step function phi is
always the same.
For example, the craft could
look like this.
And then you see one possibility
for a partition would be
X one and X two here.
However, of course, you can
also think of other
possibilities for a partition.
So maybe here on the right
hand side, you just see more
points on the X axis.
We still have points at the
jump points here.
But otherwise we have more
points.
So it's a finer partition
than on the left hand side.
But otherwise this property
here that is important is
still fulfilled.
OK.
As promised, this is exactly
the first case we want to
consider.
Now more
precisely it means that partition
two just adds more
points to partition one.
This means as a set P
two is a super set of P
one.
In words, we would say partition
two is finer than
partition one.
What this means in the picture
you can see above because
X one is exactly
the same point as X tilde
three.
Moreover X two is
the same point as X two,
the five.
Now on the left hand side,
there is no point between
the two.
But on the right hand side,
we find an additional one.
OK?
Maybe it's a good idea to
use exactly this example
to explain the general concept
here.
Hence, we can write this
equalities and
inequalities where we have
X one is equal to X to the
three and X to the five is
equal to X two.
And in the middle, we still
find X to the four.
Now, going back to the picture
on the left hand side, we
have our value, we would
call C two
because this is the value
of the second interval here.
However, on the right hand
side, this would be D
four and D
five.
However, the important thing
is this is still equal to
C two.
And of course, this is important
when we want to calculate
the area of the corresponding
rectangles
there.
Please keep in mind on the
right hand side, we have
two rectangles.
So we have to one area on
the left and the other one
on the right.
And maybe not so surprising.
In the end, this should be
the same area as we find
it on the left hand side.
However, the important thing
for us here is this comes
out of the calculation,
namely on the right hand
side, the first rectangle
is the four times the
length of the interval
which is X to the four
minus X to the
three
plus the second rectangle,
which is the five
times the length of the interval.
And this one here is X to
the five minus X to the
four.
And now I see because the
four and the five are the
same, we can factor it
out, then we
can just call it C two
because it's the same value.
And now we put all the X
tilde into the parentheses
and then you see X tilde
four will cancel out.
Moreover, we also know
X 25 is
exactly X two.
So we can substitute this
immediately.
And the same we can do for
X to the three which is X
one.
Hence, we find this whole
thing here is X two
times X two minus
X one which
is as you know the area
here on the left hand side.
OK.
Now with this calculation,
you should see this works
exactly the same for all
other points here.
In other words, splitting
up the rectangle into more
rectangles here does not
change the area.
Therefore, also summing up
all rectangles gives us the
same result.
So the left hand side here
is the area we calculate
with the first partition.
And on the right hand side,
you see the area we calculate
with the second partition.
And by the argument from
above the sum is the
same.
And this is what we want
to show that the sum does
not depend on the choice
of the partition.
However, please here keep
in mind this only worked
because one partition was
finer than the other.
Therefore, the second case
should be that we don't have
this.
So we don't have this subset
relation there.
So P one is not a subset
of P two
and of course, also not
the other way around because
then we would be in the first
case again, it would just
be renaming the partition.
However, in this case, we
still can use the first case
because we could define a
new partition P
three.
It just needs to include
all the points of both
partitions,
which means we have to union
P one with P two.
Now with this P three is
clearly a superset of P one
and P two.
Hence, here in both
cases, we can use the first
case.
Therefore, we immediately
get two results out.
First we get when we calculate
this sum for P one.
So let's write Sigma with
P one.
Then you know, I just mean
this sum with the correct
partition.
Then the first case tells
us now this is exactly the
same as calculating the sum
with the partition three.
OK.
And a similar result we get
when we apply this inclusion
for the first case
there we get that the sum
using P two is the
same as the sum using
P three.
However, of course, the sum
with P three is always the
same.
So here we see the sum with
P one is exactly the
same as the sum with P two.
Hence also here, the
result is the sum
does not depend on the choice
of the partition.
And this is exactly what
we wanted to prove.
The integral symbol is well
defined.
OK.
So you see this was a technical
proof but we had to do it.
However, now in the next
video, we can talk about
the important properties
the integral has for step
functions.
Therefore, I hope I see you
there and have a nice day.
Bye.