Hello and welcome back
to real
analysis.
And first, I want to thank
all the nice supporters on
Steady and paypal.
Now, in today's part 52 we
will talk about examples
for the Riemann integral
for this.
Let's quickly recall the
definition for Riemann
integrable functions.
What we need is a bounded
function defined on the
compact interval A B.
And we call this function
we man integral.
If the upper and the lower
integral are the same
there, the lower integral
is given when we approximate
the integral with step
functions from below.
And the upper integral is
given when we approximate
the integral by step functions
from above.
Hence, we only get one
well-defined value here
which we call the integral
of the function F.
Now I can tell you it's possible
to rewrite this definition
here without using
supremo and infimum.
In this alternative form,
you might recognize the
approximation in a better
way to get the
idea.
Let's simply to a
small graph here.
So you see our mission is
that we approximate this
area here from above
and from below.
Now let's say this here is
a step function phi and
you see it's an approximation
form below.
Also, then you can see
without a problem.
And even with the same partition
of the x axis, we can choose
a step function phi that
approximates the integral
from above.
However, the important thing
I want to show you here is
that the area between both
step functions is very
small even
better.
We can make it as small as
we want.
And exactly this fact is
what we can use for an equivalent
formulation here.
Namely for all
epsilon greater than
zero,
we find step functions
Phi MS
with the property that the
one lies below F
and the other one above F.
And moreover, we have
that the difference between
both integrals here is
less than the given epsilon
here.
Please note we know that
the integral of Phi is
always bigger than the integral
of Phi.
So we don't need an absolute
value here.
We can just calculate the
difference.
OK.
Now this description here
makes it a little bit easier
for us to look at examples.
Therefore, I would say let's
start with the first one
now and I would like
to start with a
counterexample.
It's the so-called dela
function.
Indeed, it sounds more
complicated than it really
is.
And I would say let's define
the function on the interval
01.
And now the common definition
of the function just considers
two cases.
We either get the value
one or zero
depending if the X we
put in is rational or
not.
By using the set names, we
can say it's one when X
comes from Q and it's zero
when X comes not from Q.
Now, at first glance, this
looks like a very simple
function.
So let's tour the graph for
it.
And there you should immediately
see we have infinitely
many rational points for
the value one, but also
infinitely many irrational
points for the value zero.
And moreover, we know the
rational points like
dance in the real number
line.
Please remember this is
exactly how we constructed
the real number line.
For this reason, it's very
hard to draw this graph of
the function correctly
because you have infinitely
many jumps no matter how
much you zoom in.
And there you might already
see that this function is
not Riemann integrable.
You see this when you want
to choose a step function
si that lies above
the graph of f
such a step function then
also lies essentially
above one.
This is simply because for
any segment you choose on
the real number line, you
always find a rational number.
Hence the value one is
always included in such an
interval.
Indeed, the same holds for
the irrational numbers.
When we want to choose a
step function phi from
below there, the
step function also has to
lie essentially below
zero.
In summary, you see we have
two properties here that
hold for all step functions,
Phi and Phi
and therefore we have immediately
an estimate for the two
integrals here.
And the conclusion will be,
we can't push the difference
below one.
Of course, the first integral
will always be greater or
equal than one and the other
one always less or equal
than zero.
In other words, we cannot
fulfill this property for
all epsilon.
In fact, this is all we need
in order to show that the
deli function is not
riemann integrable
here.
Again, in the difference,
this first part here is
always greater or equal than
one.
And the second part without
a minus sign is always
less or equal than zero.
Hence the difference of both
numbers is always
greater or equal than one.
OK.
There you see this was our
first counterexample.
Then next, I would say we
look at a function that is
actually Riemann integral.
Of course, for the start,
let's look at a very simple
example.
And I guess the identity
F of X is equal to X
is a very suitable example.
This is simply because when
we toward the graph, we immediately
see what the integral should
be.
You see the area is given
by this triangle which
means the area should be
one half,
it's simply half of the square
where we have the sides as
one and one.
However, if we work with
the definition of the Riemann
integral, what we need to,
we can't use the triangle,
we need to use rectangles.
Hence, here we can actually
see if our approximation
works.
OK.
Now, the question here is
what is a good step function
we can choose here?
Now, the one we see in the
picture has four
steps, the
first height here is
zero, then we go up one
quarter, then the next quarter,
the next quarter and then
it's the end.
Hence, we have our four
values 0,
1/4 2/4 and
3/4.
Also, it's not hard to see
that we split the X axis
also in four equal
parts.
So we have to interval 0
to 1 quarter, one quarter
to two quarters and so on.
OK.
So you see this is a well
defined step function.
You can choose for the approximation
from below.
It has exactly four
equidistant steps.
Therefore, let's put a four
into the index here.
Of course, this tells you
now that the approximation
will get better when we choose
similarly a step function
with more steps.
In fact, this is exactly
what we will do.
But now for an arbitrary
integer N,
hence we have exactly N
steps now, which means the
denominator here.
And here is now N
however, now, instead of
writing in different cases,
I want to put all of them
into one closed formula.
And this is what we can do
with another index K.
So you should see when K
is equal to one, we are in
the first case
K is equal to two, gives
us the next case and so on
until K is equal to
N gives us the last case
here.
Hence, the only thing missing
here is now the value at
the position which is K
minus one,
which definitely fits because
it's zero in the first case
one, in the second case and
so on.
OK.
So this is a step function
that looks like this.
But now with N steps,
OK, maybe it's not so
precise because here
we should have chosen an
open interval.
However, then you see it
will clash with the last
case here.
However, we can ignore all
of that because you already
know for the integral, the
boundary points here don't
make any difference.
Speaking of the integral,
maybe let's immediately calculate
the integral of phi N.
Now, as we have learned before,
the integral of a step function
is always the sum of
the areas of the
rectangles,
please recall we have N
steps.
Therefore, we have N
rectangles.
Honestly, the first one has
area zero.
So we could ignore it, but
we can include it nevertheless.
So now the area of one
rectangle is simply the
height times the width.
And by construction, this
is for all our rectangles
one over and
you see we have one over
N squared which we can pull
out of the sum.
And then you see the only
thing we have to calculate
now is the sum of
the first N minus one
integers.
And then we can use something
some people call the little
Gauss formula.
In this case here, it's N
times N minus
one divided by
two.
In the next step, you see,
we can simplify this
into one half
minus one divided by
two N.
OK.
So this is our result here,
the result of this integral.
And what you should immediately
see is that if our approximation
gets better and better.
So if we send N to
infinity, the result is
one half.
However, that's not enough
for showing that F is we
are integral because we
also have to approximate
the integral from above.
And of course, this is now
what we do with a similar
step functions.
I here I would say
let's use the same picture
as before to sketch the
new step function.
Of course, it should be the
same staircase as before
but now shifted above the
function.
Therefore, the definition
of PN should look
more or less the same as
the definition of phi.
Of course, the partition
of the X axis should be the
same.
We only have to shift the
values indeed,
instead of K minus one, we
now can choose K.
So you see it's not hard
at all to define such a step
function.
And indeed in the same way
as before, we can calculate
the integral
again, it's just a step
function.
So we add up all the
areas of the
rectangles.
And now the only difference
from before is that the height
of the rectangles is slightly
larger.
Still here, we can pull the
fact of one over N squared
out of the sum.
And the only thing that remains
is the sum of the first and
numbers, this
means that we can apply the
same formula as before.
But now we have one additional
number at the end.
For this reason, this sum
is then given as N times
N plus one divided by two.
OK.
And then in the last step,
we can simplify this again
and we get one half
plus
1/2 N.
So with this, you should
see we've reached our goal
because the difference between
these two integrals is
exactly one
divided by N.
In other words, we can make
the difference as small as
we want.
So if you recall the epsilon
criterion from above, then
you see that this function
F is Riemann integrable.
And of course, this is our
result here.
Moreover, we also get the
value of the integral of
F which is one half
of course, not a surprise
for you.
But now we have proven it.
OK.
I think that's good enough
for a first example here
we will consider more complicated
examples later.
Therefore, I hope that I
see you in the next video
when we continue with the
Rayman integral.
Have a nice day and bye.