Hello and welcome to this
new series about multi-
variable calculus.
This will be a video course
where I explain things
concerning functions
defined on R^n
For example, we will talk
a lot about derivatives like
partial derivatives,
directional derivatives and
total derivatives.
However, before we start
with this, I really want
to thank all the nice people
who make such new video courses
like this possible.
And there please don't forget
if you support me on Steady,
you get access to the PDF
versions and quizzes for
all the videos.
Speaking of other videos,
I can tell you it will be
helpful that first you watch
my real analysis course
simply because there we
discuss the normal
calculus in one
variable.
In other words, multivariable
calculus will extend
this series here.
However, of course, you don't
need to understand everything
in real analysis to start
with this multivariable
calculus course.
Moreover, soon you will
notice that we will extend
a lot of notions from one
variable here to several
variables there.
And exactly for this reason,
also my linear algebra
course can help you there.
This is what you will understand
immediately when we write
down functions from
R^n to R^m.
In the linear algebra course,
such functions would
be linear functions.
However, here in multivariable
calculus, we will consider
a lot of different functions
from R^n to R^m.
But still, we will
ask if we can
approximate these functions
with linear functions
which as you might know from
the one variable case
leads to the notion of
derivatives.
Moreover, you also know
such derivatives can help
finding maxima and
minima of functions.
And now with this course,
we will be able to do this
for quantities of interest
that depend on several
factors.
And indeed, you will see
we have a lot of applications
for this.
In addition, this course
now can help you to
understand my more advanced
courses.
Indeed quite fitting after
this will be my manifolds
course.
And also functional
analysis will generalize
a lot of topics from here.
And lastly, I can tell you
if you know how to deal with
multivariable calculus,
you also know how to deal
with complex analysis.
So in some sense here, you
can use a lot of facts for
functions from R² into
R².
OK.
Now I think we can talk a
little bit about the topics
you can expect here.
First, we start very
simple and talk about
continuous functions.
So we will extend the definition
of continuity that we
learned in real analysis.
Then in a similar sense,
we will generalize the notion
of a derivative from one
variable. However,
it turns out there are a
lot of different possibilities
for that.
And therefore, we will talk
about partial derivatives,
directional derivatives and
total derivatives.
Indeed, we will see all
of these notions will be
important for us.
Moreover, by using
these things here, we can
generalize an important theorem
from real analysis,
namely Taylor's theorem.
So I would say this is a
very important fact
but also the most
important fact for multi-
variable calculus will be
the implicit function
theorem.
In fact, this is a result
that is used in a lot of
applications
and in a similar way, the
next one here is also used
a lot,
it's the famous method of
Lagrange multipliers.
OK.
There we have it, this is
the overview of the course
and we start in the next
video with continuity.
Therefore, I would say let's
meet there and have a nice
day.
Bye.