Hello and welcome to a new series about complex analysis
and before we start i really want to thank all the nice people that support this channel on Steady or Paypal.
Now this is part 1 in this series and we just start with a short introduction and some basic definitions.
So the topic is called complex analysis, because it deals with functions defined on the complex plane.
More concretely we consider differentiable functions f with domain C and codomain C.
So you see it's different from our real analysis course, where we have the real number line R as domain and codomain.
Now soon we will see that this makes a major difference in the definition of differentiability
and from that a lot of strong theorems will follow. Which indeed don't hold in real analysis.
However since the real number line R is a subset of the complex plane C, we can often apply these theorems even if we just consider some real functions.
For example a real problem, where complex analysis can be really helpful is calculating an improper Riemann integral.
This could be the integral from - infinity to infinity of the function: (x * sin(x)) / (1 + x^2).
Now indeed finding an antinderivative of this function is really, really hard.
However just calculating the whole integral with complex analysis is surprisingly simple.
Indeed the result we find is a number slightly larger than 1. Namely it's pi divided by e.
How to do this simple calculation here, we will learn in this course.
However of course first we have to start with the basics.
and i already told you in contrast to real analysis we immediately start with differentiability.
The definition first looks the same as in real analysis,
but it's way more powerful as we will see.
Now in order to understand this new definition, you will need to know some basic facts.
First you need to know how to work with sets and of course you also need to know how to calculate with complex numbers.
If you have problems there, you find everything you need in my "start learning mathematics" series.
This is the whole playlist that covers all the basics you need for this course here.
In addition, it's also good if you already have a basic knowledge of some topics of real analysis.
For example you should know what a continuous or a differentiable function from R to R is.
Also could be very helpful for you, if you already know what a power series is.
For all these topics of course my real analysis series can help you.
However you don't need to watch the whole course. Some videos about these topics might be sufficient.
Ok, by knowing this i now thing we can start with the course.
The first part will be about some definitions we will definitely need throughout the course.
First i can tell you, the complex numbers form a set with the distant function.
Formally we call such a construction a metric space,
but don't worry it's not complicated at all.
It just means that the distance between two elements of the set make sense.
and of course we can immediately visualize this in the complex plane.
This means that a complex number z can be found in this plane.
and on the x-axis we find the real part of z and on the y-axis the imaginary part.
Now you can imagine that we have a second complex number here, we call w.
and now what we want to do is to measure the distance between both points.
Indeed this is what we calculate with the absolute value in C.
and what we need is the absolute value of the complex number (z - w).
Now such a notion of a distance is important, because with a distance we can say: what a convergent sequence is, what limits are and so on.
Otherwise we wouldn't be able to say that a sequence gets closer and closer to a given point.
Indeed we have to measure this closeness.
Hence, now we are able to talk about sequences of complex numbers and convergent sequences.
So a sequence of complex numbers is denoted by z_n, where n goes through all natural numbers.
So formally we just have a map that goes from the natural numbers into the complex numbers C.
However we will always write the sequence in this form.
and now we are able to define what it means that this sequence is convergent to a fixed complex number "a".
It just means that the distance, we can measure between z_n and "a" gets smaller and smaller until it reaches 0 in the limit.
This means that we can just look at a sequence of real numbers.
Namely the sequence of the absolute value of (z_n - a).
This is but a definition of the absolute value, a sequence of real numbers.
Of non-negative real numbers.
and now in the case that this sequence of real numbers goes to the limit 0,
we call the sequence of complex numbers z_n convergent to "a".
Now if you don't remember the definition of convergence for real numbers, lets recall it.
So we find that for all positive numbers we can call epsilon, there exists an index, we can call capital N
such that for all indices afterwards, so n is greater or equal than capital N,
we get that the distance between z_n and the point "a" is less than epsilon.
So you see this is exactly the definition we learned in real analysis.
However now we can visualize it in the complex plane.
Now, this formular with the distance less than epsilon means that we can draw a circle around "a" with radius epsilon.
With this we get that eventually the sequence member z_n lie inside this circle.
So only finitely many can lie outside.
and because this whole picture here is so important, we call the inside of the circle an epsilon ball.
and for the notation we use a capital B with index epsilon.
Moreover the middle point "a" here, we put into parentheses afterwards.
Now by definition this is the set of all the complex numbers w, with the property:
|w - a| is less than epsilon.
So this is the definition of an epsilon-ball in the complex plane.
Ok, because you now know what a convergent sequence in the complex numbers is,
you also know what a continuous function between C and C is.
In fact it has exactly the same meaning as for real functions.
Hence small deviations, small errors in the input should be translated into small errrors in the output.
Indeed this can be formulated with sequences.
Therefore we say a function is continuous at the point z_0 in C
if for all sequences of complex numbers called z_n, we have
that if z_n is convergent to the point z_0, then also
the images f(z_n) are convergent with limit f(z_0)
Of course here we use a common notation that tells us that a sequence is convergent to a given point.
No matter which notation we use, you should remember continuous at a given point just means that convergence in the input implies convergent in the output.
Ok, so with this we have the definition of continuity for complex functions.
Therefore the next thing we need to define is the important notion of differentiability.
This is what we will do in the next video, where we actually start with complex analysis.
Now if you have any problems with these definitions in this video here, please check out my real analysis course.
There i talk a lot about these definitions for real functions.
However if you understand it, you can immediately translate this to complex functions.
Ok, please also note the pdf version of this video, you can find in the description.
as well as a quiz about this topic.
Then i hope i see you next time.
Bye!