Hello and welcome back to complex analysis.
and as always first i want to thank all the nice people that support this channel on Steady, via Paypal or by other means.
Now, today in part 3 we continue talking about complex differentiability.
More precisely we introduce the complex derivative and i'll explain to you why this gives us a linear approximation.
and finally at the end of the video, i show you concrete examples.
However first please recall that the domain of the function we consider is always an open set, we call U.
Moreover from this set U we always fix a point z_0.
Now, because this set is open, z_0 is always an inner point.
Which means that there are a lot of points around it, such that limits makes sense.
Indeed this is what we need, when we want to define that the function f is differentiable at the point z_0.
and if we want to make it clear that we have a complex function here, we say complex differentiable at z_0.
Now, we have seen in the last video that this definition here looks exactly the same as for real functions.
Namely, that the following limit exists.
Indeed this is the slope of the function at a given point.
and often it is called the differentiable quotient.
Now since this describes the slope, we can refomulate it to a linear approximation.
The only problem is that the visualisation is not so good when we deal with complex numbers.
Here i mean that for a real valued function, you can simply draw the graph of the function.
So maybe it could look like this.
However for a complex function the input is the complex plane and the output is the complex plane.
Hence the corret visualisation of the graph of the function should live in 4 dimensions.
So you see there is no way i can correctly draw this here.
Hence we just take an abstract picture then, where the x-axis represents the whole complex plane C.
and in the same way the output, the y-axis also represents the whole complex plane.
So you see we lose a lot of information here.
It's not the best picture at all, but we can see the linear approximation then.
In other words we approximate the function f around this point z_0 with a linear function.
Therefore you recognize, this works exactly as for real valued functions.
So we get a statement that is equivalent to our definition of being differentiable at the point z_0.
Namely we just have to give this expression a new name and we call it a function delta.
and this delta gets an index, where we write the function f and the point z_0.
Then you see z could be any point from U, so we have a function from U to C.
Ok and now we can just reformulate this expression here and we get the property the function delta_f,z_0 should have.
Namely f(z) can be written as the constant f(z_0), so the value at the point z_0
+ a linear term times the delta function.
Of course this property here holds for every function f. So we need one more ingredient here.
and here please recall, we want that this limit exists.
Hence this means that the function delta_f,z_0 is continuous at the point z_0.
Hence this continuity property is really what we need and this one makes the differentiability.
Now, with this linear part here you might already see why we call this a linear approximation of the function f.
If you have never seen this, you can watch my real analysis course, where i talk a lot about linear approximations.
However here, we finally should define the derivative of the function f.
This not so complicated, because now we have everything.
Moreover you might already know the derivative is denoted with f'.
and then in parentheses we write the point z_0.
and now by definition the value of the derivative is simply the output of the delta function we get, when we put z_0 into it.
and now because delta_f,z_0 is a continuous function at the point z_0, we can calculate this number with a limit.
Namely, simply this limit here.
Or in other words, it's simply the same thing.
and now this complex number we call the derivative of f at the point z_0.
and again if you want to make it clear that we work with complex functions, you speak of the complex derivative of f at z_0.
So you see the definition is not complicated at all, but please always keep in mind: f'(z_0) is a complex number.
Ok, then i think we are ready to look at 2 simple examples.
The first one we consider should always be the linear polynomial, but now the complex valued one.
So we have a function f, where the domain U can be chosen as the whole complex plane C.
and the definiton of this complex function would be f(z)
is equal to a complex number m times z + another complex number c.
So this is simply the common linear polynomial, but now complex valued.
There, because the function is already linear, a linear approximation will not change  so much.
However lets try for a given z_0 to rewrite the function in this form.
Hence first we need f(z_0).
Which is not so complicated, because it's simply m times z_0 + c.
and then we want to add (z - z_0) times something.
Now of course this something we now can figure out.
What we want to get in the end here is m times z + c
The c we have already got, so we have to get rid of this term here.
Of course this is no problem for us, because we can multiply this term by m.
Then z_0 times m will cancel out and the only thing that remains is z times m.
Or in other words, now we have rewritten the function.
The first term is f(z_0) and this part here is our function delta.
The function is constant. It's equal to m, so we don't have any problem putting z_0 into it.
Hence we know the derivative, no matter which point z_0 we choose.
The derivative is always equal to m.
This shouldn't be a surprise to you, because the m stands for the slope of the linear function here.
However still now we have proven that this function is indeed complex differentiable.
and indeed no matter which point z_0 we consider.
Ok, for the next part lets look at an example that a function is not differentiable.
Again lets take the domain as the whole complex plane.
and now the definition of the function should be that z is send to the complex conjugate of z.
So with our notation we would right z bar.
So you see this is not a complicated function at all.
To see what the function does, lets draw the input space here and the output space here.
So our function f maps from the left hand side to the right hand side.
Now lets take any point z from the domain and then the function f just flips this point with respect to the x-axis.
The real part of the numbers stays the same, but the imaginary part gets a different sign.
So you see this reflection is all the function f does.
Therefore it's not hard to show that this function is indeed a continuous function.
However it turns out that it's not differentiable. No matter at which point z_0 we look.
and this is immediately interesting, because in real analysis it's not so simple to find such a strange function.
Indeed in complex analysis this property is not strange at all.
In order to see this i would suggest that we try calculating the derivative at the point z_0 = 0.
Indeed all the other points will work exactly the same.
Now by definition, if the derivative exists f'(0) is given by our limit.
So we have f(z) - f(0) divided by (z - 0).
So we can immediately simplify this, because when we when we flip 0, we don't change anything.
Hence we have the limit z to 0 of z bar divided by z.
Ok and now it turns out that exactly this limit does not exist.
In order to see this please recall that z to 0 here means that in a complex plane we have a lot of possibilities.
So we can go from different directions into 0.
For example we could use the real number line to go from the right hand side into 0.
For example with the sequence z_n = 1 over n.
Hence there the question is: what is z_n bar divided by z_n?
Of course this is not so hard to see. This is 1 over n divided by 1 over n.
Or in other words, it does not depend on n. It's always the same number, 1.
Therefore also in the limit n to infinity, we get out 1.
So the conclusion is, if this limit exists it has to be 1.
That this can't be true we see, when we look in another direction.
Now lets use the imaginary axis and one from the bottom to 0.
For example this can be done with the sequence z_n is equal to -i divided by n.
So again we have the same question. What is z_n bar divided by z_n?
So now in the numerator we actually have a flip.
It's simply +i divided by n divided -i divided by n.
Therefore we can cancel everything and the only thing that remains is the - sign.
So we get out -1.
So we see, also in the limit n to infinity this is -1.
Which is of course not the same as before. So this is not equal.
Therefore the conclusion is: The limit from before does not exist.
In other words f is not differentiable at the point z_0 = 0.
Accordingly we immediately have a counterexample for differentiability.
Here please recall i already told you, you can do the same prove for every other point z_0.
So the conclusion is indeed, the function is nowhere complex differentiable.
At first this might be surprising, because the function is continuous and indeed a very simple function.
In fact we can reformulate this and say that differentiability for complex functions is a very strong property.
and i can promise you, this will get very apparent soon.
and with this i hope i see you in the next video.
Bye!