Hello and welcome back to complex analysis.
and as always, first I want to thank all the nice people that support this channel on Steady, via Paypal or by other means.
Now, this part 4 is about holomorphic and entire functions.
So you see, we are still at the beginning of this interesting field such that we first have to fix the manner of speaking here.
In fact the definition of a holomorphic function is what we need throughout this course.
Therefore let's immediately start with this.
So we consider a function f with domain U.
and of course this should be a complex valued function.
Now, we have talked about this before. The domain U should always be an open subset of the complex numbers.
So it does not matter how it looks like in the complex plane. The important thing is, it's an open set.
However later we will see that often we have a very nice looking domain.
Nevertheless, still it's very helpful to introduce holomorphic functions in this general sense.
Hence let's immediately do this.
So a function f is called holomorphic, if f is complex differentiable at all points.
So you see it's not a complicated definition at all.
It just tells us that the complex derivative makes sense no matter which point z_0 we choose.
Therefore sometimes it can be helpful to emphasis the domain again.
So we would say holomorphic on U.
So what you should remember is
a holomorphic function is just a complex valued function that is differentiable at all points of an open set.
Now in the literature also see that other names than holomorphic are used.
For example some people speak of regular functions.
Moreover you also sometimes see the term complex analysis used for this definition here.
However later i will tell you what this term should actually mean.
It has something to do with power series.
Ok, now there is another special name for holomorphic functions, whose domain is the whole complex plane.
For this largest possible domain the holomorphic function is then called an entire function.
So in other words, entire just means holomorphic on C.
Ok, by knowing this we can now talk about some basic properties of holomorphic functions.
Let's start with the properties we can immediately adapt from the real valued counterparts.
First we know the proof that differentiability implies continuity.
Hence in complex analysis this means that a holomorphic function is always a continuous function.
Indeed for showing this fact we can exactly redo the proof we did in real analysis.
and this is what we can do for a lot of basic facts here.
For example we still have our sum and product rule for derivatives, when we consider 2 functions.
Therefore this implies, if f and g are holomorphic functions, the sum and the product are also holomorphic functions.
Of course this is a fact, we will naturally use a lot in calculations.
Ok, now besides the sum and the product rule, you also now the chain and quotient rule for derivatives.
and also for them we can just redo the proof from real analysis.
Therefore we can just state sum, product, quotient and chain rule still hold.
For example you can check my video about the chain rule for real functions and when you see the proof,
you will see that you can do the same steps, when you consider complex numbers instead of real numbers.
Ok, by knowing this i think we are ready to talk about some important examples of holomorphic functions.
Now, by simply using the rules from above we immediately see that polynomials are entire functions.
More precisely this means that we have a function f, where the domain is the whole complex plane
and where f(z) is given as a sum with fixed coefficient "a".
So we have a_m times z to the power m
+ a_(m-1) times z to the power (m-1)
+ and so on
until we reach the constant term. The coefficient a_0.
However here please keep in mind, the coefficients are fixed complex numbers.
Now such a function here we call a complex polynomial.
and if a_m is nonzero, we call m the degree of the polynomial.
Of course here its not hard to see, using our sum and product rule, that a polynomial is a holomorphic function.
and because there is no restriction in the domain, it's also an entire function.
Indeed just by using induction, you can calculate the derivative f' for every point z.
and now it might not surprise you
this is m times a_m times z to the power (m-1)
+ (m-1) times a_(m-1) times z to the power (m-2)
+ and so on, until we reach 2 times a_2 times z to the power 1.
and finally + the new constant term, a_1.
So you see, this is what you really should remember.
More precisely, when you want to calculate the derivative of such a term
it just means you bring the exponent in front and reduce the exponent by 1.
Hence the polynomial is still a nice function in the complex numbers.
In fact the same holds for rational functions.
Where we simply divide two polynomials
However, because we have a denominator there, the domain can't be the whole complex plane.
This means that we have to exclude the zeros of the denominator.
For example in the case that we consider the function f(z) is given by 1 over z.
Then we are not allowed to divide by 0. Therefore we have to exclude 0 from the domain.
Now the important thing to note here is, in the case we exclude finitely many points from the complex plane,
we still get an open set.
Therefore we can combine this fact with the quotient rule and conclude that this function is also holomorphic.
Now, obviously this whole argumentation also works for any rational function.
So in summary a rational function is also a holomorphic function.
Now as a reminder the definition of a rational function is simply given as one polynomial p divided by another one, q.
So f(z) = p(z) divided by q(z).
Then the finite set S, we have to exclude here, is simply given by the zeros of q.
Hence all points z in C, where q(z) = 0.
Now such rational functions often occur in applications.
Therefore it's good to know that they are also holomorphic.
However please keep in mind. In general they are not entire functions.
Ok, with this we have some examples we can work with and of course later we will talk about other examples as well.
But first, in the next video we will talk about the Cauchy–Riemann equations.
In fact these equations will explain why complex analysis is so interesting.
Therefore i really hope that i see you in the next video.
Bye!