Hello and welcome back to complex analysis.
and of course as always, first i want to thank all the nice people that support this channel on Steady, via Paypal or by other means.
Now in todays part 5 we go into the direction of the Cauchy-Riemann equations of complex analysis.
In order to understand them, we first have to talk about differentiability in higher dimensions.
In particular we need to know the notion of total differentiability from functions from R^2 into R^2.
The reason for that you immediately recognize, when we visualize the complex numbers as the complex plane.
So you know, a complex number has a real part and an imaginary part.
Therefore the natural question you could ask here is: is there any difference between this and the vector space R^2?
At first glance both totally look the same.
and even the operation how we add vectors and add complex numbers is actually the same.
In fact if you know the construction of the complex numbers, this is no surprise for you.
For this we know that C is R^2, but it carries one more operation.
and this is the multiplication we have to add to the vector space to get the complex numbers.
This all is important to know, because it means, when we define a map from C to C, it's the same as defining a map from R^2 to R^2.
Therefore it's important to understand how we can switch between both cases.
So lets remember the fact that each complex function induces a real function.
More precisely, if we have a map f from C to C, we can also define a map from R^2 to R^2.
and maybe for the moment lets call this map on the right hand side f with an index R.
Ok, of course this also works the other way around.
So if you start with a map f_R here, we can define a map f from C to C.
Now, how we exactly do this, we could formally write down, but maybe it's better to just look at an example.
I really think after seeing this example, everything is clear.
Therefore the function we consider now shouldn't be too complicated.
Indeed just lets look at a quadratic function, which sends z to z^2.
Now, squaring a complex number is not so hard.
In order to get a visualisation for the function, lets draw the complex plane again.
Now, the function f maps the complex plane from the left hand side to the right hand side.
For example if you consider the point "i" here one the left.
Then it simply gets squared and we find it as -1 on the right.
In the same way, you could take any other point to visualize how it gets mapped.
Now, on the calculation side of the problem, you could take the real and the imaginary part of z and calculate with them.
Hence we could say x + iy is mapped to (x + iy)^2.
and then, without a problem we can just expand this expression.
So we get x^2 + 2ixy - y^2.
Of course this now looks more complicated than just z^2, but it now tells us how we can define the map f_R.
We simply know and use that the real part is the first coordinate and the imaginary part is the second coordinate.
More precisely we write f_R from R^2 into R^2 and we start with a vector with 2 coordinates.
As we said, the first one is x and the second one is y.
and this vector now gets mapped to a new vector with 2 components.
Now, the first component should be the real part of this. Which means x^2 - y^2.
In the same way, the second component should be the imaginary part. Which means everything with an "i".
Ok, now we have the map f_R. Which carries exactly the same information as f.
Indeed we can simply check that with the same example we have given with the picture.
Hence, here we would put in the vector (0, 1). Which represents this point.
Now, using our definition of f_R, we can calculate and get in the first component -1 and in the second component 0.
and by seeing this you know, this vector is to be found here.
Ok, in summary this shows us, that if we want to analyse a complex function f,
we can equivalently analyse a real function from R^2 into R^2.
However in this connection it's not clear at all what differentiability means.
We have a definition for complex functions, which means we also need one for such functions here.
Indeed you might already know that differentiability makes totally sense for functions between R^n and R^m.
So you see the exact dimensions for the vector spaces here and there are not important for the definition of differentiability.
and exactly for this reason the notion for differentiability for these functions
is different from the one we already know for complex functions.
Therefore our task here is to form the connection between both notions.
However before we can do that i should first explain to you how we define the derivative for functions between vector spaces.
Of course for us it's sufficient to only consider maps between R^2 and R^2.
Nevertheless you will see this definition works, no matter which R^n and R^m we choose.
Now, the correct notion we now introduce for such maps is also called differentiable.
However sometimes it's needed to distinguish it from all the other differentiability notions
and therefore it's often called totally differentiable.
Ok, so the idea here is the same as always.
We want a linear approximation around a given point.
Therefore we have to fix a point in R^2. So maybe lets simply call it (x_0, y_0).
and now you should know, a linear map in R^2 for the linear approximation can be described by a 2x2 matrix.
and this matrix we want to call J.
Of course everything is real here. So the entries of the matrix J are also real numbers.
Ok, with this we are ready to write down what we mean by linear approximation here.
The function f_R at any point (x, y) can be written as a constant + a linear term + an error term.
and indeed this error term should be small, when (x, y) is close to (x_0, y_0).
So more concretely first the constant is the value of f_R at the position (x_0, y_0)
and then comes the linear map. Which is given by the matrix J.
To get a linear map, this matrix is multiplied from the right hand side by the difference of the 2 vectors.
So we have (x, y) - (x_0, y_0).
and with this we already have what we call the linear approximation.
Therefore the only thing we have append now is the error term. Which measures how good this approximation is.
and this one is given by a map we call phi.
Of course here the input and the output space should be the same as for f_R.
Now, the important claim here is that this error term gets smaller and smaller, when (x, y) gets to our point (x_0, y_0).
Indeed then the term should go to 0 and faster than linearly.
Namely this means when we look at phi(x, y) and divide it by the length of the difference vector
So the vector (x, y) - (x_0, y_0)
Then this expression should go to 0 when (x, y) goes to (x_0, y_0).
Ok so this is what we need, but maybe i should explain some details here.
First this double line here we use for the notation of a norm in a vector space.
Therefore with such a norm we just measure the length of a vector.
and most of the time in R^2 this is just the standard euclidean norm.
and this one you should know. It's simply the square root of x^2 + y^2.
Now, in addition when we can measure lengths in the vector space, we can also measure distances.
Therefore it makes sense that we say that one vector converges to another vector.
It simply means that the length of the difference vector goes to 0.
Therefore you see this whole definition also makes sense when we are in another vector space
like R^3, R^4 or just the vector space where we can measure lengths.
and exactly for this reason and please keep that in mind,
this definition is not the same as the differentiability definition for the complex numbers.
However maybe you are very familiar with this definition here and in this case i can tell you, this matrix J has special name.
Most of the time it's simply called the Jacobian matrix.
and more precisely we would say, Jacobian matrix of f_R at the position (x_0, y_0).
Now, if you are used to partial derivatives, you might also know that the Jacobian matrix has a very nice representation.
Please recall, in our case it's a 2x2 matrix. So it has 4 entries.
Now, in the first column you find the partial derivative of f_R with respect to the first variable. Which is x.
Here please don't forget, this is a vector with 2 components.
So in fact, we have 2 entries of the matrix here.
Ok and maybe not a surprise for you, the second column is given by the partial derivative of f_R with respect to the second coordinate.
So in other words we have the partial derivative with respect to y.
and again this is a whole vector. So we get 2 entries of the matrix.
Now of course in our case here, you would evaluate these partial derivatives at the point (x_0, y_0).
and then we just have a 2x2 matrix, where the entries are real numbers.
Ok, now in the case you have never seen this and this is all confusing for you, i really think an example can help.
With this example you should see, it's not so complicated after all.
and for consistency lets reconsider the example from above.
So this is a nice function. We have x and y as the input and the output has 2 components as well.
Then in the next step we can just calculate this Jacobian matrix J and show that we indeed have a linear approximation.
Indeed the result will be this function here is differentiable at all points.
Therefore lets simply look at the partial derivatives here.
So first we just form the partial derivative with respect to x. Which means here y is just a constant.
Therefore in the first component we get 2 times x + 0, because y is a constant.
and then in the second component we get 2 times y,
because y is still a constant and the derivative of x is simply 1.
Ok then for the second column lets switch the roles.
Now we form the partial derivative with respect to y.
Or in other words, now x is a constant.
For this reason the first component tells us, now we have -2 times y.
So, this was just this part here and now the last step is just considering this function here.
and the derivative with respect to y just gives us 2 times x.
Ok so this is the Jacobian matrix of the function f_R.
and here please recall, this function f_R represents a complex function f, which was complex differentiable.
and now maybe you recognize some symmetries in this matrix here.
Indeed you see this is a very special matrix we get out.
With this i would say lets use the next video to explain why this structure of the matrix is so important for complex analysis.
Therefore i hope i see you there and have a nice day.
Bye!