Hello and welcome back to complex analysis.
and you might already know, first as always I want to thank all the nice people that support this channel on Steady, via Paypal or by other means.
Now, finally in today's part 6, we will talk about the Cauchy-Riemann equations.
In order to understand them we first have to recall the 2 notions of differentiability we have for complex function.
The first is the normal one. The one we introduced at the start of this series.
This one we simply called complex differentiable at a given point z_0.
Now, as a reminder in other videos I already explained, the domain here doesn't have to be the whole complex plane C.
It's sufficient to have an open subset.
However this might be distracting for this video here. Therefore I always write C for the domain.
So if needed you can just substitute this domain with any open subset U.
Ok, back to the differentiability here. This one can be described as a linear approximation in C.
More precisely this means that we can find the complex number, we can call f'(z_0).
Indeed, this could be any complex number.
Then with this it's possible for us to write f(z) as a linear term + an error term.
and you already know, everything happens locally around z_0. Therefore the constant term is f(z_0).
Then next comes the linear map. Which has a slope given by f'(z_0).
More precisely we have this number times (z - z_0).
So you see again, this is the linear approximation of the function f around the point z_0.
and please recall, in real analysis this represents the tangent.
Therefore the only thing missing here is a corresponding error term, we could call Phi.
Of course this Phi is also a function from C to C.
Now as an error function this map here should go to 0, when we send z to z_0.
and this convergence to 0 should go faster to 0 than the linear function would do.
Or more concretely Phi(z) divided by (z - z_0) should still go to 0, when we send z to z_0.
Now, with this property we really get a linear approximation around the point z_0.
Indeed, this is what we could read as the definition for complex differentiability at the point z_0.
However to be honest it looks a little bit different than the definition we gave before.
Yet I would say it's not hard at all to get this reformulation from our definition.
and I guess it's a good exercise for you to think about it.
After this you see, you simply can take this for the definition of complex differentiability.
and that's a good thing, because we can nicely compare this to the definition of total differentiability we explained in the last video.
As a reminder, this definition we introduced for functions from R^2 into R^2.
and there please recall, we have a 1 to 1 correspondence between functions from C to C and functions from R^2 into R^2.
Therefore often both functions are just called by the same name, f.
However to distinguish them I give the last one here an index R.
Ok, now we can recall the definition of total differentiability for such functions.
Also there we have to fix a point in the plane. So let's call it (x_0, y_0).
Then we know the function is called totally differentiable at this point, if there exists a matrix J and an error map Phi.
Please note I use another variant to denote the letter Phi here.
Then what we need is also a linear approximation. Now given by this matrix J.
and lastly of course this error term here should also go to 0 in the same way as before.
Which means if we divide it by the length of the difference vector, we still get out 0 in this limit.
Here please note, before this 0 was the 0 in the complex numbers and now this 0, is the 0 vector in R^2.
However using the identification C with R^2, you could say they are exactly the same.
Therefore a natural question here would be: where exactly is the difference between both notions here?
So I would say let's try to spot all the differences.
First this might be obvious, in the second case we see when we use the division here, we need the length of the vector.
This is what you know, we can't divide vectors.
However in the complex numbers we don't have this problem, we simply can divide one complex number by another one.
Now, maybe this is not a crucial difference, because both things just explain that the error term goes to 0.
and of course if we wanted, we also could use the absolute value here.
Indeed this wouldn't change anything for the linear approximation here.
Therefore we have to look at the linear approximations to see the differences.
Since we immediately see that the constant terms fit, we look at the linear terms here.
and there you see, this dot here stands for the multiplication in the complex numbers C.
and that's the difference because this multiplication does not exist here.
Indeed what we find here is a matrix-vector multiplication.
Now exactly this does not translate in general to the multiplication in C.
Therefore the conclusion is immediately this definition here, complex differentiability is much stricter than this definition there.
and now in order to get a translation from the complex definition to the one in R^2, we have to answer one question.
Namely in which cases does a matrix-vector multiplication represent a multiplication in the complex numbers.
Now, because we know how to calculate with complex numbers, we can answer this question without any problem.
Just let's check how the multiplication in the complex numbers looks like.
So we take 2 complex numbers w and z, and multiply them.
Of course here w and z have a real part and an imaginary part respectively.
Therefore we say w = (a + ib) and z = (x + iy).
and now we just do the multiplication, where we use that i^2 is -1.
Then we get: a times x - b times y + the imaginary part.
Which is b times x + a times y.
Of course this was not hard at all, because you know how to calculate with complex numbers.
However now we want to rewrite this as a matrix-vector multiplication.
and the vector should represent the complex number z. Which means we have x and y as the coordinates.
and on the left of it, we have a 2x2 matrix where the numbers a and b should occur.
and indeed how the entries exactly look like we have to figure out now.
and of course this is no problem for us, because we already know the result.
The first component should just be the real part here.
and then the second component is just the imaginary part.
and now the question is: Which 2x2 matrix brings us to this result?
Now the first row we see immediately, because it should be "a" and -b.
Of course in the same way we also see the second row. Which be b and a.
and indeed that's it. This is the matrix that represents the multiplication of complex numbers.
Therefore our conclusion here is, if we want complex differentiability we need that the Jacobian matrix here has this form.
So I would say let's fix this important result with a theorem.
In fact in this theorem we will now find the Cauchy-Riemann equations.
Ok in order to get everything together let's start with a complex function.
That should be complex differentiable at a given point z_0.
and now we can just split this point into a real and an imaginary part.
and as before we call them x_0 and y_0 respectively.
So with the reasoning from above we know that this statement here is equivalent to
The statement that the corresponding real function f_R from R^2 to R^2 is totally differentiable at the point (x_0, y_0)
and that the Jacobian matrix at the point (x_0, y_0) has the symmetric form from above.
So there you see this is our final connection between both notions of differentiability.
and exactly this connection now leads us to the Cauchy-Riemann equations.
We simply get another equivalence when we use the fact that the Jacobian matrix has partial derivatives as entries.
However in order to do this we have to introduce new names for the components of the function f_R.
That's no problem at all, because we know we just have 2 components.
The first one we simply call u and the second one v.
Now both components depend on the 2 variables x and y.
Therefore we simply write u(x, y) and v(x, y).
In other words here we have 2 new maps that send R^2 to R.
So please don't forget, here we just have real functions.
Ok and now we know from the last video that in the top left corner for example we find the partial derivative of u with respect to x.
and now you see, with the partial derivatives in the Jacobian matrix we find a connection.
And exactly this connection is what we call the Cauchy-Riemann equations.
There are just 2 partial equations for u and v.
In particular the first one is simply that du/dx = dv/dy.
So here you see this equation just represents that we have the same number in the top left corner and in the bottom right corner.
Ok and then you might already see it. The number b here gives us the second equation.
Which is du/dy = dv/dx.
and of course both equations have to be fulfilled at the given point (x_0, y_0).
Ok now you know that we have these 2 equivalences to describe complex differentiability at a given point.
and of course then we can extend that to a whole open subset. We talk about holomorphic functions.
In other words a holomorphic function has to fulfill the Cauchy-Riemann equations at all the points.
Ok then i think it's good enough for today.
Let's talk about examples in the next video.
Therefore I hope I see you there and have a nice day. Bye!