Hello and welcome back to complex analysis.
and first i want to thank all the very nice people that support this channel on Steady, via Paypal or by other means.
Now, in todays part 7 i show you examples for the famous Cauchy-Riemann equations.
For this lets first recall the important theorem from the last video.
There we introduced the Cauchy-Riemann equations with respect to the complex differentiability.
Hence we can immediately reformulate the theorem for holomorphic functions.
and as always for this we have to choose an open subset capital U in C.
and now you should already know the complex function can be equivalently described as a function from R^2 into R^2.
However in this case for the new function the domain should also be an open subset of R^2.
So maybe lets simply call it U_R.
Obviously when you visualize U and U_R in the plane, they look exactly the same.
In other words the open domain here does not make any problems at all.
Ok, now in the last video we have learned that we can split up the function f into a real and an imaginary part.
and both we can see as a function from U_R as a subset of R^2 into R.
In particular the real part function here, we denote by a lower case u.
So please recall this u is a real valued function.
and then exactly in the same way, the imaginary part of f gives us a function we call v.
So also here we have a function with domain U_R and codomain R.
Hence you see, the whole information of the function f is now translated into these 2 functions.
Indeed the property that f is holomorphic translates into the fact that u and v fulfil the Cauchy-Riemann equations.
These are not complicated at all. There are just 2 partial differential equations.
The first one simply says that the partial derivative of u with respect to x is the same as the partial derivative of v with respect to y.
and then in the second equation you see, when you switch the roles there is a minus sign included.
In summary what we need for a holomorphic function is that these 2 equations are fulfilled at each point in the set U_R.
In fact this equivalence here, we have discussed in the last video.
Now in this video i want to show you concrete examples.
and i would say, lets immediately start with a very simple one.
So lets take the complex function f from C to C. Given as the identity.
Which means the number z is simply mapped to z again.
Now, because we want to deal with the partial derivatives with respect to x and y, we have to write z as (x + iy).
Hence we do this change on the left hand side and on the right hand side.
and then you see, here the real part is our function u and the imaginary part is our function v.
So you see in this case it's not complicated at all.
and now we just want to check if the Cauchy-Riemann equations are satisfied.
So lets write down the partial derivatives.
First we have du/dx. Which is in this case simply 1.
In the same way we also see that dv/dy is very easy to calculate, because this is a simple function and the derivative is just 1 again.
Hence we immediately see that the first equation is satisfied at all points.
So lets go to the second equation, where we have du/dy.
There we see, there is no y in u. Therefore we get 0.
In fact the same holds for dv/dx, because there is no x in v.
and also of course, the minus sign does not change anything.
In summary, both Cauchy-Riemann equations are fulfilled.
From that we then can conclude that the function f is holomorphic.
Of course this is a fact we have already known.
Therefore i would say in the next example, lets look at a function where we already know that it is not holomorphic.
Indeed this was simply the complex conjugation.
So f(z) is z bar.
Now as before, in order to apply the Cauchy-Riemann equations we have to rewrite that with x and y.
Of course this is not so complicated. The imaginary part just gets a minus sign.
and then as before, the real part is u and the imaginary part here is v.
So you see it's different from before and it will change the Cauchy-Riemann equation.
Of course here du/dx is still 1, but dv/dy is now -1.
Therefore we can conclude: this is not the same.
Indeed no matter which point we put in.
In conclusion we get the result, we've expected. Namely f is not holomorphic.
Here you see, showing this was very simple by just using the Cauchy-Riemann equations.
However maybe we should also look at a more complicated example.
So lets take another complex function f.
and now i want to look at it as z^2 + iz.
To be honest. You already know that this is a holomorphic function, because it is a complex polynomial.
Indeed we already know how to calcualte the complex derivative for such a complex polynomial.
Here it should be 2 times z + i.
Still it's helpful to check it with the Cauchy-Riemann equations.
Now, by writing x + iy instead of z, we actually have something to do now,
because in this expression here, we don't see immediately the real and imaginary part.
We first have to calculate a little bit.
However that's not so complicated, we simply can do the whole calculation here.
So we have x^2 + i2xy - y^2 from the binomial + ix and -y.
Now lets put the real part to the left and the imaginary part to the right.
So the real part is everything without an "i" and for the imaginary part i factor out one "i".
and then we have the result we wanted,
because again, here we have our function u and there we have the function v.
Now with these 2 functions we can check the Cauchy-Riemann equations again.
First du/dx, not hard to see, is simply 2 times x
Then the second partial derivative we want to calculate is dv/dy, which is also 2x.
Hence our first equation is actually fulfilled.
Going to the second one, you see we have to do a little bit more, because this derivative is -2y - 1
Ok, then the last derivative we want to calculate would be the partial derivative of v with respect to x.
and there you see, it's 2y + 1
and then for our equation we just have to put a minus in front.
and then we recognize this is the same as du/dy.
Therefore also here both equations are fulfilled. So the function f is holomorphic.
I already told you, this is not a surprise for us.
However with this example you have learned how you can apply the Cauchy-Riemann equations,
when the function f is given as a real and an imaginary part.
and in fact you also get the complex derivative of f from these partial derivatives here,
but i think this is a good topic for the next video.
Therefore i really hope that i see you there. Have a nice day and bye!