Hello and welcome back to complex analysis.
and as always, first I want to thank all the nice people that support this channel on Steady, via Paypal or by other means.
Today in part 8 we will continue talking about the Cauchy-Riemann equations and I will also explain what Wirtinger derivatives are.
For this as often, we consider a complex function f, that is holomorphic on an open domain U.
and for such a function we will define a new differential operator as a partial derivative with respect to the variable z.
Then when we apply this to the function f and look at a given point z_0, this is often called the Wirtinger derivative.
However, this is not quite correct, because there is also another Wirtinger derivative.
This one is a little bit strange, because it's written as the partial derivative with respect to z bar.
However it turns out that both things here are well defined and indeed useful for our theory.
For example: for a holomorphic function f this one here should give us the complex derivative of f at the point z_0.
With this in mind, we will be able to define this new differential operator.
Also, then we will see that for a holomorphic function, the other Wirtinger derivative should be 0.
Therefore let's first concentrate at the Wirtinger derivative on the left hand side. df/dz.
Now, to make our life a little bit easier let's write (x + iy) instead of the point z_0.
So this means, this is the complex derivative of f at the given point.
Hence it's just another complex number, which we can write as (a + ib).
and now this is what we have learned in the last videos. The real part and the imaginary part can be written as partial derivatives.
This works when we take the real part of the function f as a function u and the imaginary part of f as a function v.
and then this "a" here is du/dx and b is dv/dx.
Of course both partial derivatives here are to be evaluated at the given point (x, y).
However in the upcoming calculation we will omit this point to make everything clearer.
Of course now in the next step here we want to use the Cauchy-Riemann equations.
and in order to include them correctly the best thing we can do is to double this complex number here.
So you see, we add the same number again, but then we have to divide everything by 2.
and now the idea is, that here in the second part we apply the Cauchy-Riemann equations.
So instead of du/dx we can write dv/dy.
and on the other hand dv/dx can be written as -du/dy.
Ok, what you now should see is that some symmetry is involved. We have 2 partial derivatives with respect to x and 2 with respect to y.
and this is what we can apply to our knowledge that u is the real part of the function f and v the imaginary part.
Or in other words we can also look at the map that has (x, y) as an input, but a complex number as an output.
Namely f at the point (x + iy) should be the output.
So you see as the map f_R this carries exactly the same information as the map f.
It's just again another point of u.
and this helps us, because this function we can write as u + iv.
and now you might already see, on the left-hand side we use exactly this.
Here the first part we can write as the partial derivative with respect to x of u + iv.
and now in order to get this in the second part as well you see we have to pull out a -i
and when we do this, you see we also have the partial derivative now with respect to y of u + iv.
Ok, so this is the result for f' you really should remember.
Indeed it's easier to remember when we use that (u + iv) are essentially the function f.
Hence we can just define 2 new differential operators.
Namely we just call the first one df/dx and the second one df/dy.
and indeed this makes sense. This one is the partial derivative with respect to x, when you see f as this map here.
Ok, soon I will show you an example and then these 2 operations should be clear.
However first I want to define the Wirtinger derivatives, because with this calculation here we already know how to do this.
We can just use combinations of the partial derivatives with respect to x and y.
Firstly, now when we write d/dz. This should stand for 1/2 times d/dx - i*d/dy.
So you see, this is exactly what we have learned above.
The definition makes sense and for a holomorphic function f it gives us the complex derivative of f.
Ok, now in a similar way we will define d/dz(bar).
and indeed this should look very similarly. So we also take 1/2 times, and now d/dx + i d/dy.
We do this, because you see by the Cauchy-Riemann equations, we get 0 when we apply this operation to a holomorphic function f.
and here please recall. This fits to our motivation from the beginning.
Ok, then as promised let's look at an example.
It shouldn't be a complicated one. So let's look at a polynomial.
Namely we just look at a quadratic function z^2.
Which means using x and y, we have (x + iy)^2.
Hence, let's just expand the square. Which means we have x^2 - y^2 + i2xy.
Therefore this first part here is our function u and this part is our function v.
With this we can immediately calculate df/dx, which is here 2x + i2y.
and similarly we can calculate df/dy, which is here -2y + i2x.
Now, both things can be simplified when we just use the fact, that (x+iy) is the complex number z.
Hence, df/dx is simply 2 times z.
and in a similar way you see for df/dy we have 2 times i times z.
So we can always use that i^2 is -1.
Now, with these 2 nice short expressions we should be able to calculate with 2 Wirtinger derivatives.
So let's start with the second one, df/dz(bar).
It's 1/2 (2z + i times 2iz).
Again, we know i^2 is -1. So we get 0 here.
This is what we expected, because the polynomial is a holomorphic function.
Ok, then in the next step it's not hard to calculate df/dz.
It's the same calculation as before, but now with a minus sign here.
Therefore in this case, in the parentheses we have (2z + 2z) divided by 1/2, gives us back 2z.
Also here the result is not so surprising, because it should give us the complex derivative of f.
Ok, then I would say let's summarize the video by stating the important fact we have proven here.
Indeed, this is something one can nicely remember.
Namely, a complex function f defined on an open domain U is holomorphic if and only if df/dz(bar) is equal to 0 at all points.
Indeed, this equivalence you already know, because here we simply have hidden the Cauchy-Riemann equations.
and then in this case as we have proven above the other Wirtinger derivative gives us the complex derivative of f.
So f' can be calculated by using df/dz.
Ok, with this you now know a lot of different differential operators we can use in complex analysis.
Then I hope that I see you in the next video, where we will talk about power series.
Have a nice day! Bye!