Hello and welcome back to complex analysis.
and first many, many thanks to all the nice people that support this channel on Steady, via Paypal or by other means.
Please don't forget, as an supporter you get a PDF version and a quiz for this video.
Now, todays part 9 will be about power series.
Indeed, this is a very important topic in a complex analysis course.
In the case you have watched my real analysis course, you already know a lot about power series.
Now it turns out, for this concept in the complex numbers, we can do exactly the same as in the real numbers.
Moreover by working with complex numbers we will find the true nature of the behaviour of some power series.
Hence you need to work in the complex realm to understand power series completely.
and why this is important, i can immediately show you with an example.
Namely one of the most important functions is given by a power series.
This is the exponantial function denoted by exp(z).
and now you know the value of the function is defined by an infinite sum.
There we have z^k divided by k!.
Now, this definition you should know for real numbers,
but then we don't have any problems also putting complex numbers into the formula.
Of course then in general the outcome is also a complex number.
Here please don't forget, this symbol infinity means there is a limit involved.
This means we have a limit of complex numbers and because you know how to measure distances in a complex plane, you don't have any problem with this.
Regarding this there is simply not much difference to the real counterpart.
Now with this philosophy we can also talk about the general definition of a power series in the complex field.
In other words if you know the definition for real numbers, you know exactly what comes now.
Of course the starting point should be the coefficients we have in the infinite series and are now complex numbers.
and a fitting name is just a_0, a_1, a_2 and so on.
Ok, then for these numbers we can define a complex function, we can call f.
Moreover the domain we call D. So we have a function from D into C.
Then this map is defined by sending z to the infinite series of the coefficient a_k times z^k.
However, since later it will be important that we can shift the whole function by a fixed number z_0, i already introduce it here.
So we simply have (z - z_0)^k.
and i can already tell you this z_0 is often called the expansion point.
Of course what is still missing here is the explizit definition of the domain D.
However you might already know this, because here in the definition of the map there is a limit involved.
And maybe this limit does not exist for all complex numbers z we can choose.
Hence this restriction is now what we have to put into the definition of D.
So we can say: we have all the complex numbers z, where this limit exists.
Or in other words we simply say the series is convergent.
Ok, then you see we have a well defined function. Maybe the domain is very small, but still we always call this function a power series.
With this knowledge i would say we look at an example.
This is an important one and you already know it from real analysis.
It's the famous geometric series.
It's not complicated at all, because all coefficients are just 1.
Therefore we have the series that start with k=0 of z^k.
Now, in fact by using exactly the same proof as in real analysis, we can show that this series has the value 1/(1-z).
However you might already know, this proof only works if the absolute value of z is less than 1.
Indeed if the absolute value of z is greater or equal than 1, then this series does not converge.
In other words the domain D here is the ball around 0 with radius 1.
and this is such an important fact, that you really should remember it, because we can use it a lot in the future.
Moreover please recall the notation we use for the epsilon ball.
So it's the open ball, so we call it B and the radius is 1. So we have an index 1 and the middle point is just 0.
Ok, so what you see here in the complex plane: we have a circle and inside we have convergence and outside we have divergence.
Now it turns out that for any power series this situation is not essentialy more difficult.
Indeed the following fact follows from the geometric series.
It simply tells us that for a given power series, there is a maximal radius r for this circle here.
Or to say it more concretely, the open ball with radius r lies completely in D.
So you see the only difference from before is that we don't need equality and also the middle point should be z_0 now.
So here you see the worst case for r would be to be 0, which means there is only 1 point in D, z_0.
and the best case scenario would be that r is infinity.
Which means D is just the whole complex plane.
So by using formulas we would write: r comes from the interval 0 to infinity. However, also infinity should be included as a symbol.
Therefore to be precise we would distinguish between 2 cases here.
Of course i told you before, the second case is just that D is the whole complex plane.
This is the best case, because there the power series converges everywhere.
In the other case please note that we know, that somewhere on the boundary or outside of the ball, we have divergence.
Indeed, because this r is chosen maximally, the result is that everywhere outside we have divergence.
Therefore the general picture looks like this.
In the complex plane we have this ball with z_0 in the middle and with radius r and in the inside of this ball convergence is quaranteed.
Moreover in the outside of this ball, divergence is quaranteed.
The only thing we don't know in general is what happens at the boundary.
Indeed, depending on the power series different things could happen there.
For example for the geometric series the boundary was completely divergent as well.
However, for a different power series you could have convergence or both cases mixed.
Ok, then lets state the divergence part here also with a formula.
Now, the outside in this complex plane here, could be described as this set difference.
So it simply means that z is not an element of this ball.
However, then the boundary would be included so we have to exclude this as well.
We can simply do this by taking the closure of this ball.
So this notation simply means: this is the set including the boundary.
So in this case it's not the open ball, it's the closed ball.
Now, for points that are not in this closed ball we know that the power series here is divergent.
So in summary you should see this here is a very nice result, we can use a lot when we deal with power series.
Indeed, it's not hard to prove. We can just use the root criterion from real analysis and combine it with the geometric series here.
Ok, if you are interested in seeing this prove, please let me know in the comments.
Now, for the end here i can tell you, often it's sufficient to know that there exists such an r,
but sometimes it would be nice to have an explizit formula for it.
Then we would be able to calculate this value of r.
Probably you already know this formula. It's often called the Cauchy-Hadamard theorem.
In fact this is what we have discussed in my real analysis course in part 33.
and it tells you that 1/r can be calculated by a lim sup.
Namely we look at the coefficient a_k in the absolute value and then we take the k-th root of this real number.
Then we take the lim sup k to infinity and we know this always exists.
It's either a real number between 0 and infinity or this symbol infinity.
and then simply the inverse of this number gives us our maximal r.
There of course you should know, inverses with 0 and infinity are here defined by this formula.
Hence the best case scenario is: in this lim sup is 0.
Ok, the last important thing i should tell you is that this maximal r is often called the radius of convergence for the power series.
and i would say it's a good exercise for you to calculate the radius of convergence for the exponential function from above.
Ok, then i hope i see you next time, when we start talking about the uniform convergence.
So have a nice day and see you there.
Bye!