Hello and welcome back to complex analysis.
and before we start i want to thank all the nice people that support this channel on Steady, via Paypal or by other means.
Now, here you see we've already reached part 10 in this series.
Therefore it's time to start talking about the important concept of uniform convergence.
The definition for this convergence is indeed exactly the same as in real analysis.
Moreover you will also see that in complex analysis we can immediately apply it to the power series.
However lets first start with the formal definition.
So what we need is a sequence of functions. Now they are complex functions with the same domain U.
This means for each natural number n we have a function f_n here.
Additionally we need another function f, which should be our limit.
Hence we say: the sequence of functions f_n is uniformly convergent to another function f,
if the supremum norm of (f_n - f) goes to 0 when n goes to infinity.
and as usual the supremum norm is denoted with an infinity symbol in the index.
Now in the case that you have never seen the supremum norm, lets quickly define it.
In fact the only thing we need is that the values of the functions that are involved are numbers.
Then it does not matter if we have real or complex numbers, because we can always take the absolute value.
and then we are just interested in the largest value that can come out or more precisely
we look at the supremum where we go through all numbers z.
and now what we want for the uniform convergence is that this supremum goes to 0, when n increases to infinity.
So please note, we don't just fixed the point z and look at the convergence, we look at all points at the same time in the limit.
and exaclty this makes the convergence here uniform.
Ok, now this notion helps us a lot when we deal with power series.
In fact this is such an important result that we can use it a lot in complex analysis.
Essentially it tells us that all power series are holomorphic functions.
Later we will see that in some sense the reverse implication is also true.
However lets first start with the statement here, which holds in general for all power series.
So you see what we have is a power series with coefficients a_k and expansion point z_0.
Now, the only thing we put in is that the radius of convergence is greater than 0.
It could be infinity, but it's not 0.
To say it differently the power series here is convergent at a different point than z_0.
Therefore we can define this function on the whole open ball B_r(z_0).
I always call it ball, but you now, in the 2-dimensional complex plane it's a disk.
Therefore sometimes i speak of the open disk around z_0.
Now, from the last video you know inside this open disk we have convergence, but now we see, we also have uniform convergence.
In fact we have this for this power series here, when we see it as a function defined on B_c(z_0).
So we have a number c as a radius involved, which is smaller than the radius of convergence.
and this is very important, because we don't know if we have convergence on the boundary of this disk here.
However, if we make our ball a little bit smaller, now we know we have also convergence on the boundary, on the circle.
Therefore we can also include the boundary in this statement here.
and there you know, the closed ball is denoted with this line here.
Ok, if you are not used to working with series and power series, here you see an alternative formulation of this statement.
I simply give you the explizit definition of sequence of functions f_n, we need for the uniform convergence.
and you see, it's defined by using partial sums.
and now this sequence of functions converges uniformly to the function f.
However, only when we restrict f_n to the closed ball B_c(z_0).
Ok, so this is the first statement and the next 2 will tell us that the power series is indeed a holomorphic function.
In order to show this we have to look at the formal complex derivative here.
So the power k comes in front and we reduce the exponend by 1.
We already know this works for polynomials. So when we have an end index here, but we don't know if this also works for power series.
But you will believe me, this is exactly what we want to proof now.
The first step for this is that similarly to before we also get an uniform convergence for this new power series here.
More precisely here we can also say, we have a sequence of functions f_n' that converge uniformly to this function here.
Indeed here the name f_n' is justified, because it's the complex derivative of this polynomial here.
Of course in the end this is what we want when we have the derivative of f. We want to approximate it with these derivatives here.
and obviously exactly this should be our last statement, three.
Hence we can write: the function f is complex differentiable and the derivative is given by this formula.
So maybe this is not such a big surprise, but still it's a very nice result for us.
and here please recall f is defined on an open domain and complex differentiable at all points.
Hence, the power series gives us immediately a holomorphic function.
So with this result we immediately get a lot of examples for holomorphic functions.
In summary, in order to understand complex analysis, you really should remember this whole result here.
In a few words we could say this result tells us that each power series is holomorphic on its open disk of convergence.
Of course if you really to believe this result, we should prove it.
However this will take some time. So lets do this in the next video.
Therefore i hope i see you there and have a nice day. Bye!