Hello and welcome back to complex analysis
and of course, first I want to thank all the nice people that support this channel on Steady, via Paypal or by other means.
Now, today in part 11 we will prove the important result about the uniform convergence and power series from the last video.
In order to do this let's quickly look at the statement again.
So we have a power series named f, defined on the open disc of convergence.
Then we are able to show 3 important statements here.
The first one is that inside the open disc, for every closed ball, we have the uniform convergence.
Next, the second statement tells us that this property also holds for this formal derivative
and then in the last step we can show that this is indeed the derivative of our power series f
or in other words, f is complex differentiable for any z and the derivative is as we expected.
Now, I already told you, this is an important result, because it tells us that every power series is a holomorphic function
and for this reason I think it's very helpful that you can see, that we can actually prove it.
The proof is not so complicated and indeed only part 3 will take some time.
However also for the other 2 parts, to make our life a little bit easier let's assume that the expansion point z_0 is equal to 0.
This is not really a restriction, because the general case would work exactly the same.
In the end this is just one translation in the complex plane to get any other expansion point.
Still for us here everything is tidier and clearer when z_0 vanishes from all the equations.
Ok, knowing this let's start with the proof of part 1.
There we need to show a uniform convergence and therefore we consider the difference (f - f_n) in the supremum norm.
Here of course f_n is just the polynomial given by the partial sum.
Also please note z_0 is set to 0 here and this one is our domain.
Which means we have a closed ball inside the domain of convergence.
Of course this is how you should understand the supremum norm here. It's a supremum norm with respect to this domain.
Hence we can immediately write this down as a supremum where z goes through all the points of this closed ball
and it's applied to the absolute value (f(z) - f_n(z)).
Which is of course simply our power series that now starts with n+1.
Simply because we subtracted the terms from 0 to n.
Now, this is something we can work with, because for the absolute value we have the triangle inequality.
Now, in order to apply it we first have to pull this limit here out of the absolute value.
This is possible, because the absolute value is a continuous function.
Ok, then the triangle inequality just means that now we have the absolute value inside the sum.
So we simply have the absolute value of a_k times the absolute value of z to the power k.
So what we can use now, is that the point z lies inside the closed ball with radius c.
Hence the length of this point, the absolute value of z, is not greater than c.
So we know we have the nice bound here. This is less or equal than c.
Okay, so this is a nice result because now we can omit the supremum here,
because there is no z involved anymore.
Hence what we get is a power series that starts with n + 1 of the absolute value of a_k, times c to the power k
and now you might already see, this looks close to a geometric series and indeed we can use a geometric series as a majorant here
and please note here, because there is the absolute value involved, we are only working with real numbers now.
For this reason you might recognize the whole argument here from real analysis.
Still, I really think it's helpful that we discuss it here.
Okay, now the last step here I want to put as a remark on this side.
By assumption we know that this power series is convergent, because the real number r tilde here lies in the region of convergence.
So the point here is, we can choose a number that lies between c and r.
So what we know is this series is convergent. Hence the sequence inside has to be bounded
Hence we find a bound we can call B, such that the absolute value a_k r tilde to the power k is bounded by B.
Now the left-hand side we can simplify, because r tilde is a positive real number which does not need the absolute value.
Therefore in the next step we can write this as:
B is greater or equal than a_k in the absolute value, times r tilde to the power k.
Okay and now you see we have to bring c to the power k into the game here.
Of course we can just do this in this way, but then we have to divide by c again
Hence what we have here is the factor "a" tilde divided by c to the power k
and here you see this number r tilde divided by c is a number that is greater than 1
Therefore we can call this number q to the power -1.
Hence then q is a number strictly less than 1.
Okay and now you see this whole thing here we can use for an estimate of this part there.
This is now simply less or equal than B times the series of q to the power k.
and there you should see, this is just a very nice geometric series. Which is of course convergent, because q is less than 1.
This means when we send the lower index n to infinity this whole thing goes to 0
and exactly this is what we wanted, because it means all the terms here are 0 in the limit.
Hence the supremum norm goes to 0 and we have the uniform convergence.
Okay, there we have it. The first part is proven.
Now, fortunately the 2nd part can be proven with exactly the same steps and in order to see this let's go back to the statement.
So you see it looks exactly like part 1. The only difference is that we have another power series
or in other words, we just have other coefficients, but these don't change the argument here.
Therefore the only thing we actually have to check is that this power series has the same radius of convergence like the first one
and this is what we can do using the Cauchy hardaman theorem.
So please remind yourself, this is just one lim sup we need to calculate.
For this please note that our new coefficients for this power series are given by a_k times k
or more precisely we can give it a name and call it b_(k-1).
The index is k-1, because the power here is also written as k-1.
Okay and now you know
for the radius of convergence we need to calculate this lim sup for k to infinity of the k-th root of the coefficient in the absolute value b_k.
Hence what we have inside here is (a_k + 1) times (k + 1).
Okay when we have this, I don't have to go into the details, because you see we can split it up into two parts.
The first part where the coefficient a_k is involved gives us the original radius of convergence r
and the 2nd part just goes to 1 in the limit, k to infinity.
Therefore the radius of convergence of this new power series is simply the same as we had for the original one
and this means we can simply redo all the steps, but now instead of a_k we would write b_k.
So I would say that's enough for part 2. The interesting proof is indeed part 3.
For this reason let's invest the next minutes to calculate the derivative of our function f.
Of course what we want to get out, is that the derivative is given by this power series.
Hence we need a good name for this function. Let's call it f tilde.
So in the end we want to get out that f tilde is actually f'.
However at the moment we don't know if f ' exists.
Therefore we are not able to assume it. We have to show it in this proof.
However, of course we can look at the difference quotient.
this can be written as f(z + h) - f(z) divided by h.
Obviously here h is also a complex number and in the limit h to 0 we get f'(z).
For this reason a good idea would be to subtract f tilde of z.
Then the thing we want to show, is that this term here goes to 0, when h goes to 0
and of course in order to do this we also will use a triangle inequality,
but before we do this let's split our power series f into two parts.
So you see here, instead of f, I write it as the sum of p_N + q_N.
Hence the idea here is to take the infinite sum and to divide it at the index N into two parts.
More precisely this means p_N(z) as given by the polynomial that ends with the index N.
Accordingly q_N is simply defined as the whole rest that starts with N+1.
Now, the reason why this splitting here can be helpful, we have seen above.
The derivative of the polynomial we can immediately calculate
and exactly this derivative of the polynomial we want to include here and then use the triangle inequality.
However before we do that let's first put p_N at the front and q_N at the back.
So here's the difference quotient with p_N and there is a difference quotient with q_N.
Of course we still subtract f_n, but here we want to add and subtract the derivative of p_N now.
Hence you could say we have simply added a 0 here.
Okay, now you should see that this really helps, because now we have 3 different parts here.
Also you surely remember our goal is to apply the triangle inequality, so what we have to do is to take the absolute value on both sides.
Ok, then you should see this really helps us, because now we can separate the 3 parts in the absolute value and get the inequality.
Now, this is very nice, because we can give the parts names and talk about them separately.
Of course we don't need fancy names. So maybe we call the first one simply "A", the second one B and the last one C.
So then let's see which one of them makes problems.
For the first one, "A" we already know, when we send h to 0 this one goes also to 0.
Hence no problems there. What about the second one?
Indeed by the property 2 from above, we already know this thing here converges to 0, when capital N goes to infinity.
This is simply because the uniform convergence implies the pointwise convergence we have here.
Of course in this case the question remains. What happens with the last part C here, when N increases?
If this one went bigger and bigger, it would not help us that the first two ones get smaller and smaller.
Therefore we have to analyze part C in detail.
First i would say, inside the absolute value, let's substitute q_N again with the power series.
Hence we have one part with z + h and one with just z.
Then of course we should put both terms together.
So we simply have the series with a_k times (z + h) to the power k - z to the power k, divided by h.
Now, this looks much simpler than before and indeed we can simplify this even more, when we use the geometric sum formula.
Indeed this one is applicable, because we have the same power and the difference involved.
To refresh your memory, the geometric sum formula holds for any number q and it looks like: (1-q) to the power k divided by (1-q).
So you see there's one exception for q. q is not allowed to be 1.
However in all other cases this is indeed the finite sum starting with 0 and ending with k-1
and we simply sum up all the powers of q.
Now, in order to apply this formula here, the trick is to use a suitable q.
Maybe not so hard to see is that we need both z+h and z in q.
Hence what will work is, when we choose q as z divided by (z+h).
Then we can just multiply on both sides with the correct numbers, such that the left-hand side here looks like this.
Additionally and I simply tell you this, now we find that the right-hand side has a very nice form.
We start with the highest power of z+h which is the power k-1.
Then the next term in the sum is z+h to the power k-2.
However, then in addition we also find z to the power 1.
Hence we can say here in the first term we had z to the power 0.
So you see, this whole sum continues until we reach the last term, z+h to the power 0 times z to the power k-1.
Now, please don't forget ,this whole sum here is only the part inside the series after a_k.
This is important, because you know we apply the absolute value on the whole term.
Of course then we can use the triangle inequality again.
First we use it here to push the absolute value inside the series
and then you see, for this whole sum here we can use the triangular inequality again.
Indeed what we can use there is the fact that both z and z+h lie in our ball.
Hence we know, the number r is an upperbound for the absolute value of both numbers.
So you see for the absolute value we have r to the power k-1 here, here and so on
and because the sum has exactly k terms, we know we have this k times.
In conclusion, we get a very nice inequality now.
Of course we still have the series and the absolute value of a_k, but then comes r to the power (k-1) times k
and that's a very nice series we get here.
So you see this is related to the derivative, we already considered in part 2
and then you should see, I need to correct myself here, because we need to lie inside the domain of convergence.
Hence in order to do this correctly we need to choose a number r tilde which is less than the radius of convergence r.
This is no problem at all, because z and z+h lie inside the domain of convergence.
Hence instead of the number r we can choose a smaller number r tilde as the bound for all these numbers.
Then we get this series here and the most crucial fact is: this is a convergent series
and therefore this tail of the series has to go to 0 when capital N goes to infinity.
Ok and with this you see, we have complemented the last missing part of our estimate above.
To make it clearer, I would say for the end of the video let's go through the argument again.
So we start with a fixed point z and a small h. Then I just give you an arbitrary epsilon greater than 0
and then you simply choose N so large, that this part and this part are both smaller than epsilon.
After this, in the last part we simply take the limit h to 0 on both sides.
Then A will vanish and we have the fact that this limit here is smaller than our epsilon.
To put it in other words, the limit is arbitrarily small and therefore the limit has to be 0
and there you see, this concludes the whole proof.
Well, I still hope after this technical proof you are still interested in complex analysis.
The next video will be easier, when we just look at examples for power series. So I see you there and have a nice day. Bye!