Hello and welcome to this
video about the election system for
the "Bundestagswahl 2025".
Mainly, I want to explain
how the German parliament (Bundestag)
is put together after each voter
has given his two votes (There are Erststimme and Zweitstimme)
Often one says that the whole
election system is really
complicated since it is adapted again and again.
However, in this video
you will see that the entire
distribution procedure is actually
quite simple and the first thing to
remember is that the whole
election prodecure essentially has three
layers. On the outermost layer,
we have the entire federal republic of
Germany. This defines the electoral area.
But it is split, on the one hand,
into 16 states. And the other hand
it is split into 299 electoral districts (Wahlkreise)
There, it is important to know that a Wahlkreis
always lies completely inside a
given state. Then these districts are
enumerated from 1-299.
For example for the state Hessia
we find the numbers 166 to
187. And it's important to know that
in each district, the given ballot paper
looks different. In that sense, voting
happens on the layer of the electoral districts.
If we pick out one of them,
then we see that within the
given Wahlkreis, so-called constituency candidates (Wahlkreisbewerber)
compete against each other.
They are also called "direct candidates" because
one can vote for them directly, as a vote for a person.
That is exactly what you can do with your first vote.
This is one is called "Erststimme".
Your own Erstimme, which you can use,
is only applicable in the given
electoral district. On the other hand, your second vote,
the so-called "Zweitstimme" is stronger.
It's applicable to the whole state you are living in.
However, with this Zweitstimme you do not vote for a single person anymore
but for a whole list of people
that is given by a political party.
This means each party in a given state
can state a whole list of candidates
and the voter can use his Zweitstimme
to say which party he wants.
In the following sense,
the Zweitstimme is stronger than the Erststimme
because the total number of votes in the Zweitstimme
determine the proportions of the parties
in the Bundestag.
So, only the Zweitstimme says
how many seats a party has in the parliament.
However, the people who can actually take the seats with priority
are the winners in the electoral districts.
It's common that these candidates are
associated to political party as well.
This is not
a strong requirement but
it's still the normal case.
In exceptional cases, it can happen
that an independent candidate
wins a given district.
In this case, this independent person immediately gets their seat in
the Bundestag. Everything that follows now does not hold for this person.
The winners that
are associated to a party
don't get their seats immediately.
For them, it's important
how many votes their part got with the Zweitstimme.
To make it clear again:
The winner of a district
is just the candidate that got the most
votes with the Erststimme.
So their is exactly one winner for each district.
However, if this winner associated to a party
really gets a seat in the parliament
is only decided by the amount of votes
in the Zweitstimme.
Let's see how this works. After the election
we have the total number of valid votes in the Zweitstimmme.
This is done on the upper level, for the entire federation.
A common number in Germany is around 46 million votes.
And since the Zweitstimme can only be given
to a party,
we have a distribution of votes across all parties
that took part in the election.
So we just count the votes (Zweitstimmen)
and then we know how well a given
party has done.
Obviously, we can write this
as a percentage as well.
So we have the share of votes in relation
to the total number of valid votes.
On the other hand, we can also look
how successful the parties
were with respect to the Erststimme
This means how many of the 299 districts
they could win.
This is really important because now
it will be decided which party is
important enough for the Bundestag.
Unimportant are parties with less than 5% of the total second votes.
They will be thrown out completely unless
they have won at least three districts
with the Erststimme. In that case, they are spared.
So first check the 5% barrier and, if they are below, then check
how many districts are won.
For example, here 4.8% is not enough.
and two districts are also too little.
After these cancellations,
only some parties remain and exactly these
will get the seats in the parliament.
So we just have to find the correct number
and this is done with the so-called
Sainte-Laguë method/ Webster method.
I have a separate video for that
if you are interested in it.
Here, we can just apply it
and it's only important to know
that the total number of seats in the Bundestag
is given by 630.
So with all the votes in Germany,
we find the suitable distribution of seats.
This distribution for the different parties is called "Oberverteilung".
It already tells out the power of different parties
in the parliament.
However, we already know that
we need to put in more
because the votes (Zweitstimmen) were given
to a list in a state.
Hence, in the next step, we have to distribute
the seats to the 16 states.
This can be done for each party separately
since we know how many votes
each party got in each state.
Therefore, we just create a new list
where all 16 states are listed
with the corresponding number of votes
for the given party.
To this list, the Sainte-Laguë method is applied again.
Afterwards, each party knows
how many seats for each state
they get in the Bundestag.
Just to clarify: this second distribution
is often called "Unterverteilung".
This distribution has to be calculated
for each (important) party.
With that, we also know the people who
will occupy the seats.
In order to see this, let's jump
to one state, let's say that this
is state 2 and we consider the party B.
So, we know that 8 seats can be given.
Please recall that, from the beginning,
the parties had lists of people in the states.
Indeed, this state list of the
given party is numbered consecutively
such that we can got step by step
to give the seats to different persons.
We can do this until all seats
are taken. However, actually some other people
have a higher priority first.
They are put on top of the list.
These are exactly the winners of the districts
that belong to the given state and party.
So people with the most votes (Erststimmen) in a district
are higher ranked than the state list.
Obviously, we only consider winners
that belong to party B. With that we
can order the whole list.
On top, we have the best winner. So the candidate that had the
highest percentage value in votes (Erststimmen).
Then comes the candidate with the next highest score.
And then it just goes on like this.
The list of priorities is done
and we can allocate the 8 seats.
At this point, you should see
that we have exactly 3 possibilities.
Let's start with the best case.
There, all winners of the districts
take seats in the Bundestag.
And maybe also the first persons on the state list get seats.
In this case, it does not matter at all
how good a winner in a district actually was.
However, if there are too many winners
of the given party,
then it can definitely play an important role.
In this case, the worst winners
will not get a seat in the Bundestag.
There are simply not enough seats for the party
and in this case, the state list is also
untouched.
Now, the third case is something that
actually should never happen, but theoretically, it's possible.
It could happen that the state list
is too short, meaning that the party
did not find enough people to put on the list
and now they can't fill all their seats.
Therefore, these seats will just stay empty
and they remain unoccupied in the Bundestag
Hence, only if such a case occurs,
can the total number of seats
in the parliament be smaller than 630.
In fact, on the other hand, there is still
a special case that the total number is greater
than the planned 630.
This can only happen if a party
get more than 50% of the
relevant second votes (Zweitstimmen).
Then this party must get more than
50% of the seats in the parliament.
Because of rounding errors
during the distribution procedure,
this is not guaranteed.
Hence, one has to add seats until
until 50% are exceeded.
For the election 2025 this is not expected.
I now hope that this voting procedure is clearer and
that there will be no more confusion
when you have the ballot paper in front of you.
Otherwise we can discuss further
questions in the comments.
See you next time.
Bye!
[Musik]
of