Hello and welcome.
and the mathematical symbol of today is given by the quaternions.
Denoted with such an H.
Seeing that double line here, you might already guess that this symbol stands for a special set.
and indeed it's a number set that extends the complex numbers C.
It's an extension in the sense that it's a bigger number set, with almost the same rules as we have it in the complex numbers.
In fact in H we lose one important calculation rule, namely that the multiplication is commutative.
This means that if you multiply numbers in H the order matters now.
However if you want to multiply numbers you need to know about which numbers we talk.
and i can tell you a quaternion consists of 4 parts.
So maybe lets call them a, b, c and d.
and these are ordinary real numbers.
Now as you might know it from the complex numbers, we can connect these parts with +
and then introduce a new strange number "i".
This means that we have that i^2 is -1.
However now you can see we have 2 parts left.
Therefore we need to introduce two new numbers we can call j and k.
and indeed j^2 and k^2 should also be -1.
Moreover we also have the property that if we multiply all 3 together,
So first "i", then j, then k.
We also get out -1.
Ok and there you have all the rules we need to calculate with quaternions.
Indeed this construction here is what we would call a quaternion.
Now using these rules and some other basic assumptions, like associativity
we can show that the multiplication is in fact not commutative.
For example we get that "i" multiplied with j is - the other order.
So j multiplied with "i".
Indeed if you combine "i" with k or j with k, you will get the same relation here with the - sign.
So in general you can remember, if you multiply quaternions the order matters.
and now to close this video i can tell you, the letter H for the number set is chosen to honor the mathematician William Rowan Hamilton.
So i hope that this was helpful and that i see you next time.
Bye!