Hello and welcome.
and the mathematical symbol of today is the laplace operator.
Denoted with a capital Delta.
This famous operator is also often called laplacian.
and indeed there is no single laplace operator. There are a lot of different meanings depending on the context.
However often the first time one sees triangle in mathematics or in physics is as an differential operator on the space R^3 or in general R^n.
and then it simply acts on functions f defined on the space, but with values in R.
Hence laplace f just denotes the new function also defined on R^3.
So here the variable in R^3 is simply denoted by x.
So we have components x_1, x_2 and x_3.
Indeed with respect to these components we look at a partial derivative.
and the important thing to remember here is, for the laplacian we always look at the second derivative.
So the first thing we have here is the second partial derivative with respect to x_1.
and then you see we simply add the next one.
Which is the second partial derivative with respect to the second component.
and then we simply continue adding the second partial derivatives,
until we reach the second partial derivative with respect to the last component.
So therefore please remember here we don't have mixed second partial derivatives.
However all the other once, the unmixed once, are added.
Therefore now i think you shouldn't have any problems writing down the laplace operator defined on R^n.
Ok and with this i hope that you learned something today and that i see you next time.
Bye!