Hello and welcome back to the next mathematical symbol.
Which is the set symbol N
and throughout mathematics it always denotes the so called natural numbers.
They are called natural, because you use them for counting.
However, sadly there is no consensus with which number you should start counting.
Therefore you usually find 2 competing definitions.
On the one hand the one where we first count 1 object, then 2 and so on
and on the other hand we have the definition where also no objects at all are represented with a 0.
So there we have 0, 1, 2 and so on.
Therefore if you start reading a mathematical book, you always should check and make sure which of both definitions is used.
For example if the first notation for the natural numbers here is used,
then also the second set is important and usually gets a new name. Like N with index 0.
This happens, because the natural numbers including the 0 element represent a very important mathematical structure.
Namely it is a so called monoid.
More precisely it's a monoid with respect to the addition.
So there is an important fact. In the set of the natural numbers we know what the addition means.
This I don't have to tell you. I assume that you know what it means when you have to add numbers.
However if you want an explanation for this, an axiomatic approach,
I have a whole video course about it called "start learning number".
But most importantly after you know how the addition is defined, we find 2 properties for it.
First we find it's an associative operator when we add 3 numbers.
So we have a,b and c as natural numbers and then we get the equality for these 2 expressions, where we just add the 3 numbers.
So it means we can set parentheses as we want, without changing the result
and now exactly this property is called associativity.
Ok and this is the first part we have for a so called monoid
and the second part is that a so called neutral element exist.
Often it's also called the identity element and it just means that it doesn't change the element in the addition
and now for our natural numbers here, this is of course the number 0.
So "a" + 0 is "a" again and also from the other side. 0 + "a" is also "a"
and this holds no matter which natural number "a" we choose
and with this you now know the definition of the mathematical concept called a monoid
and moreover you also know an important example. The natural numbers including the 0 element
and now if you want to learn more about the natural numbers, you can watch my other videos
or otherwise we meet in the next video about mathematical symbols.
Have a nice day and bye!