Hello and welcome back to the next mathematical symbol.
Which is today this partial d.
I just call it partial d, but there are a lot of other names for this cursive d.
However it's important to see that it's not a lower case delta.
Of course it's related, because it should look like a rounded version of a lower case d.
Indeed some people just call this symbol del, but this can be confused with the nabla operator.
Therefore if you pronounce this letter here, you can simply say d
and now you might already know, we mostly use this symbol when we talk about partial derivatives.
So for example, if we have a function from R^2 to R, we can form the derivative with respect to the first variable here
and this is then the partial derivative, denoted with the curved d.
So we have df over dx_1
and then we simply say: this is the partial derivative of f with respect to x_1
and there you see, we use this curved d to distinguish the partial derivative from a normal derivative in 1 variable.
However, our partial d here is also used in other contexts.
So for example in topology we talk about open and closed sets
and then it turns out that for each subset in a given space, we can define the so called boundary of the set.
In this picture here, we would visualize it as the shell of the given set A
and then we denote this boundary by partial dA.
So you see this is a completely different usage of this curved d, then we have it for the partial derivatives.
Now, if you know other cases where the partial d is used, you can tell me in the comments.
Otherwise I would say let's meet in the next video about mathematical symbols.