Hello and welcome back to the next mathematical symbol.
Which is today the element symbol.
This is exactly written like this. So you take a lower case c with a line inside it
and then you use it as a binary operator, where we have a left-hand side and the right-hand side.
On the right-hand side you find a given set and on the left-hand side an element of this set.
So you would read it like: " a is in A"
and now you remember, this is the sole operation we need to describe sets.
Hence the visualization would be that the set A is such a collection of elements.
This means if "a in A" is a true statement, we would draw the lower case a inside the capital A.
However it's also possible that the set A is also an element in another larger set.
So we could write capital A is an element of a larger set curved A.
Hence for this it would mean, the visualization is exactly the same.
So capital A can be seen as a point in this curved A.
So we learn, such an object can be an element, but also a set.
So it can be on the right-hand side, but also on the left-hand side.
So in the visualization it would mean, if you zoom in, you see that this element has also elements for itself.
So there we have it. This is the element symbol we use throughout mathematics to describe the element-set relation
and if you want to learn more about this I have a whole video course about this called "start learning sets".
So let's meet there or on the next day for the next mathematical symbol.