The mathematical symbol of today is this small circle, we use for the composition of maps or functions.
It's a binary operation, where we have one map "f" on the right hand side and another map "g" on the left hand side.
Indeed the composition is very basic, but it's an important notion throughout mathematics.
It simply merges two maps into a new one.
and the definition can simply be given when we put in an element "x".
First f is applied to x and then g is applied on this output.
In other words we put f(x) into g.
So we have g(f(x)).
Now to remember this order, it's always good to have a visualization of the sets, where the maps act on, in mind.
First we have f that maps from left to the middle.
and then we have g that maps from the middle set to the right set.
Therefore the new map g composed with f goes immediately from left to right.
Ok and that explains the composition symbol.
If you want to know more i have a whole video about the composition of maps.
and with this i hope i see you in the next video.
Bye!