Hello and welcome back to the next mathematical symbol.
Which is the integral sign with this circle inside.
So you see, this is a variation from the integral sign, from the last video
and here the circle always tells you that the integration is closed in some sense.
For example often it denotes a so called "closed line integral".
There we simply have a curve in some space. For example the plane and we integrate along it
and exactly this is what we would call a line integral and most importantly, it has a starting point and an end point
and now this circle here gives the additional information that the start point and the end point coincide.
So a closed integral means that the curve ends where it started.
So indeed the curve could look complicated. It's just important that we find the end point at the beginning again.
Ok and now it turns out that these integrals occur so often that it's useful to introduce a new symbol for them.
For example in complex analysis it turns out that this closed line integral carries a lot of information.
You can look at a function 1/z and then it turns out that this closed line integral is not always 0.
Indeed we find that for the circle that goes one time around the origin, this integral is exactly 2*pi*i.
So this is what we can easily calculate in the complex plane
and if you want to learn more about this, I have a whole video course about complex analysis.
So let's meet there or in the next video about mathematical symbols.
Have a nice day and bye.