The mathematical symbol of today is the convolution.
Denoted with such a star.
In fact in mathematics you find different possibilities to define the convolution.
Depending which problem you consider.
Most importantly you find a continuous version and a discrete version.
Now in this video i want to show you the ordinary continuous version.
So we consider functions f and g defined on the real number line.
Then for these two functions we define the convolution of f and g.
In fact this convolution should give us a new function also defined on the real number line.
More precisely "f star g" is again a function from R to R.
and the idea to get this new function is to mix f and g together.
Moreover this mixing works in two different directions inside the integral.
Of course this is what we should explain in a formula.
So lets look at "f star g" at a given point x.
Then we define this value by an integral that goes through all numbers. So we start with - infinity and go to infinity.
Of course inside we have the functions f and g and the variable name for the integration.
and for this i want to use the greek letter Tau.
This is very common, because in some sense the variable can stand for time.
So here you see we have the first function f at the point Tau
Times the function g at another point.
and now i already told you g should go the other direction so what we need inside is (-Tau).
Moreover we also shift the point here by our given point x.
and that's what we have. This product of the two functions is integrated.
and if this integral exists for all points x in R we have the convolution.
Indeed this convolution has some nice properties and therefore it is very important in a lot of applications.
For this reason i hope that you now can remember the definition.
Then have a nice day and see you next time. Bye!