Hello and welcome back to the next mathematical symbol.
Which is today the empty set symbol.
Usually it's denoted like this, but sometimes you also see just this set brackets
and as the name tells us, both things just denote a set, which is empty.
So it's a set with no elements at all.
This means the logical statement given by "x is an element of the empty set" is always false
and exactly because of this result, you can formulate some strange statements for the empty set.
So for example you can say: "for all x in the empty set it holds, if x an even number it's also an odd number".
So at first glance it looks false, but it's indeed a true logical statement.
Simply because there are no elements x in the given set here.
Hence it does not matter what we claim here.
In fact this is what can happen in mathematics.
That you prove a very surprising statement, but then it turns out that you have actually proven it just for the empty set
and then the claim does not hold any information at all.
Ok and with this I would say we have learned what the empty set symbol is
and if you want to learn more details, I have a whole course about this called "start learning sets".
So I hope that I meet you there or in the next video about mathematical symbols.