The mathematical symbol of today is the set bracket.
Which we use in mathematics to construct new sets.
For example you often see something like this, that after the set bracket we have a function f(x).
and then on the right you see a vertical line or a colon.
Moreover next to it you find something like: x is an element in a set "A".
Of course there could be more conditions than this, but in the end we have a closing set bracket.
Now the meaning of this is that we apply the function f to all elements x from the set "A" and then we form a new set.
and the elements of the new set are exactly these values.
So you could read it as the set of the elements f(x), where x comes from "A".
Indeed this is a construction you see very often in mathematics.
Therefore it might be helpful to look immediately at an example.
So lets look at a set of the elements where the function f is given by (2 times x + 1).
and here x should come from the set .
So you see we construct a new set using this set here and that function.
and now you should see the values that come out are just the first 4 odd numbers.
Hence 1, 3, 5, 7.
For example 7 we get when we apply this 3 here.
So you see this construction is not so complicated, but it occurs very often. Therefore you should know what it means.
As a fun fact i can tell you this set construction is also included in the programming language Python.
So you can use the curly brackets { and type "2 times x + 1 for
So you can see the "for" as the vertical line.
and then we just type "x in the set  curly brackets.
curly brackets
Ok now i hit enter and you see the result.
So not so surprising we get the same odd numbers, we calculated before.
Ok i hope that this was helpful and that i see you in the next video.
Bye!