Hello and welcome
The mathematical symbol of today is simply an arrow.
More precisely i want to talk about two arrows.
This one and that one.
In mathematics both arrows are used when we talk about maps.
For example lets consider a map f.
Then the first arrow is used, when we want talk about the sets, where the map lives on.
So we have a set X on the left hand side, which we call the domain of f.
and a set Y on the right hand side, which we call the codomain of f.
In other words f maps elements from X into the set Y.
and in order to describe this mapping on the element level, we use the second arrow.
Hence an element on the left hand side, lower case x
is mapped to an element on the right hand side in Y, we call f(x).
In fact this is all you should learn here.
We have two different arrows for the two different levels.
Now maybe lets do a simple example.
So we consider the quadratic function defined on the real number line.
Hence you would use the first arrow to denote that R is mapped into R.
and then you see, we use the second arrow to denote that x is mapped to x squared.
In summary with this the whole function is described.
In the first line we have the domain and the codomain.
and in the second line we see how this assignment should work.
Now if you want to learn more about maps. I have a lot of videos about them.
and with this, i hope i see you next time. Bye!