Hello and welcome to Riemann integral vs. Lebesgue integral.
Often students ask me why we have two integral notions at all.
Or why we need the Lebesgue integral when we already have the Riemann integral.
In this video, I explain why we go from the classical integral definition, which is the Riemann integral,
to the more modern one, which is the Lebesgue integral.
However, let us first start with the Riemann integral.
Here, we want to integrate a function f that starts from R and goes into R.
So a normal function defined on the real line and with values in the real line.
And as you should know, this integral is related to the calculation of an area below a graph.
So let me do a rough drawing of the graph of the function f here.
And consider an interval on the real line. So maybe start with a and go to b.
Then we are talking about this area below the graph. So exactly this one.
In short, this means the Riemann integral of the function f, from the interval [a,b], is related to this area here.
Therefore, we have the well-known idea to choose a partition of the x-axis and to approximate this area by choosing rectangles.
And this approximation is known as the lower sum or the upper sum.
So what I draw here is the well-known lower sum.
And if we now choose finer and finer partitions,
we call this limit of the lower or upper sums the Riemann integral if the limit is well-defined.
Well, this was a short summary of the Riemann integral.
And now we immediately find some problems here.
These problems give us a reason to define another integral notion.
Firstly, it is difficult to expand the Riemann integral to higher dimensions.
Yes, you can expand to higher dimensions. So it is possible but very laborious.
For example, if we would have a 2 here.
This means that the x-axis here is now a two-dimensional space.
So we can't use rectangles for the partition.
Of course, we now could use cuboids.
So this is the two-dimensional space in the domain of definition R^2;
then our partition is now just rectangles in the plane.
And our integral approximation now is given by cuboids. So maybe in this way.
As you can see, it gets very technical and it will be much more
work with additional dimension. Just one more dimension but you have to much more work.
For example, to build the limit process in the end.
This is directly clear if we consider the domain of definition here.
In the one-dimensional case, we only had an interval, which is an easy thing
since it starts with a and ends with b. Just an interval.
But even if we add even one dimension more.
So here is the picture, x1, x2, f(x1,x2).
So even if we even add just one dimension, there are a lot of more possibilities.
For example, the domain of definition for the function could be a circle in this plane.
So let us focus on the domain of definition now.
So I draw another picture, just the x1, x2 axis;
and then we find the circle just there.
Now, what we now want to do is to choose a partition of the circle and put the cuboids above.
However, fo course, this is not exactly possible. So we can put rectangles inside the circle here.
But as you can see: we even need a limit process to approximate the circle in the domain.
Again I say it: it is feasible but it's a lot more technical work.
In summary, this is one problem of the Riemann integral,
we directly understand.
It is much more work to do this in higher dimensions.
The second problem of the Riemann integral, and what you should know
from this one dimensional case,
It is that we need some continuity property for the functions
we want to integrate
in other words:
we have some dependence on continuity.
Recall that in the best case, the function we want to integrate
should be continuous. Then we don't have any problems.
However, if have discontinuity points, then there should be only finitely many of them.
But if we have infinitely many, it can destroy the integrability of the function.
I hope you know the typical example.
So an easy function that you can't integrate using the Riemann integral.
Hence, the dependence here is, indeed, a disadvantage of the Riemann integral.
Now the most important disadvantage of the Riemann integral is the relationship to limit processes.
The question here is in which situations is it allowed to interchange
some limit processes? Or in other words, can I pull in the limit sign inside the integral sign.
So let me show this in an example.
So we have the limit n to infinity
and we integrate a function from a to b (so this is sequence of functions f_n)
and we integrate them with respect to x.
The question is then: when is allowed to pull or push the limit inside the integral.
When does this equality hold?
For the Riemann integral, we don't have many possibilities here.
We also need the uniform convergence of this sequence of functions.
only then we know that is allowed to pull the limit inside the integral.
However, this uniform convergence is a very strong notion,
and in some sense, it's related to the continuity, again.
And therefore, we want to weaken this notion.
Indeed, we have a lot of examples where there is no
uniform convergence of the sequences of functions at all,
and we still have the same result on both sides.
Hence we know it should be possible to generalise this convergence theorem.
However, not by using the Riemann integral.
The Riemann integral is just not flexible enough to prove such a convergence theorem.
Well these are three important points that show the difficulties
we may have when we use the Riemann integral.
Most importantly, we have a wish to the generalisation to higher dimensions.
So we want an integral notion that is not restricted to one dimension.
So we don't want to do all the work again if we just change the space of the domain of definition here.
We want an integral that works in every dimension the same.
In order to understand this generalisation,
we need more technical details.
Hence, I would suggest, we start with the Riemann integral.
Again, we do some sketch (so we have the x- and the y-axis). We also have a function, where I draw the graph in green.
So we have a function with values in the real numbers.
For the Riemann integral we now choose a partition of the x-axis as before;
and now we can calculate the upper and lower sum.
Here I have drawn the lower sum.
This means that we take the infimum in each subinterval for the height of the rectangles.
And for the upper sum, we will take the supremum.
So here, for example, this rectangle. Hence we get the upper sum.
If the difference between the upper and lower sum can be made
arbitrarily small, for a finer partition,
then we can define the Riemann integral.
Then you can define it as the supremum of the lower sums or the infimum of the upper sums.
This is then the same value
and this value is then called the Riemann integral for the function f in the interval [a,b].
In order to this, it was necessary that we have a function that goes from the real numbers into the real numbers.
Otherwise, we can't do the partition of the x-axis, and we don't have a height.
The idea of the Lebesgue integral is now different.
As you have seen before, it was very restrictive to find a partition of the domain of definition.
(if it is not R itself)
If, for example, we have a three-dimensional space,
then we can't find a partition easily.
But we map still in the real numbers.
So the right-hand side is still the same since we consider functions,
so functions with values in the real numbers.
So this is the same, but the left-hand side not the same.
This means that the domain of definition, the left-hand side here,
can be very high-, or even very abstract,
and therefore, we don't know what a meaningful partition of the left-hand side should be.
Just because we don't have these simple intervals in a higher dimensional or abstract space.
However, on the right-hand side, we still find the real numbers, the one-dimensional space of the real numbers.
So instead of finding for a partition of the x-axis;
it would be easier to just find a partition of the y-axis.
And indeed, this is what the Lebesgue integral does.
Although, this is not the way, the Lebesgue measure is normally introduced.
However it is still a very good idea to visualise the Lebesgue integral.
So let us draw the graph again.
And keep in mind, the x-axis may be high-dimensional or even abstract, but the y-axis is still the real line.
And that is what we decompose now.
Since this is only the real line, we can find the same interval partition as before.
So we choose some values and define some intervals here.
So this is a partition of the real line as we did before on the Riemann integral on the x-axis.
So maybe we call these partition elements C_i,
while in the Riemann integral we usually call them x_i.
Maybe as a reminder: In the Riemann integral we defined an upper sum
of some partition of the x-axis.
So you would write U(P)
and this is the sum of the rectangles,
which means we have the sum and then choose the supremum
inside the interval times the length Delta x_i.
And you can do the same for the lower sum L(P),
given by infimum in the given interval
times the length of the rectangles/intervals
Delta x_i.
In this way, we defined the Riemann integral.
However, now we want to decompose the y-axis,
for getting the Lebesgue integral.
We have the following picture.
For example, this line here ...
... this value gives you this line from here
and we have this line here.
Now, we want to find all the parts of the function
that lie between these two lines.
So meaning: inside this interval in the real line.
This means that we don't draw rectangles like before, but we look at which parts of the function
fall between these two lines.
So we find here that we have a part on the left-hand side,
so we find all the arguments in x, that lie in this set,
are sent to values inside this interval by the function f.
And we also have here a part of the function.
And we find all the arguments of x that are sent
to the interval.
Now these two parts are associated to the decomposition/partition of the y-axis, c_i, we chose.
This is similar to the idea of the Riemann integral,
but we immediately see
that the decomposition of the x-axis below here is not connected.
Then we have different sets that are not connected like the intervals
that we saw before.
And this is the whole idea. Instead of choosing a fixed partition of the x-axis,
we now choose a partition of the y-axis, of the values of the function.
And then we get a useful partition of the x-axis
that we can work with.
Now the next question could be how to measure these lengths
on the x-axis below.
Therefore on the domain of definition which is here
R^3, (or it could be some space)
We need a so-called measure.
We want to measure volumes in the space.
This means that we want to measure the size of sets
inside this space.
For example, if this space is R, we measure lengths.
In R^2, we measure areas.
In R^3, we measure volumes of sets.
But, in an abstract sense, we will always speak of VOLUMES.
Hence, on the x-axis here we could choose a general measure space. We just have to know how to measure
the size of sets,
the volumes of sets!
Such a measure space is usually denoted by Ω.
This means that in the end we will have an integral that
works on all functions that are defined on some measure space Ω.
Indeed, this is all we need to define the integral.
Now you see how we could define
an "upper sum" in some sense.
So we take these c_i here,
and now I want the c_i to be this one. So the c_i is this stripe here.
So this would be an upper sum of the integral if we know the measure of these sets together.
Of course, these blue sets are the preimage of this interval under the function f.
Maybe we just call it A.
Now if I call the measure we have here in our measure space just by
μ,
then we calculate this generalised rectangle.
It is c_i (the height) times the length on the bottom. This is the measure of our set A, μ(A).
Now we have one part of the whole integral and now we can do it for the whole partition.
So we have a finite sum over i.
c_i times μ(Ai)
Of course, I should also put an index i on the preimage. Then we have a sum.
Since we chose a finite partition on the y-axis, we have finite sum here.
and it will be the upper or lower sum depending which
c_i we chose here.
Then again, with some limit process with finer partitions
we will get the Lebesgue integral.
Usually denoted by integral f dμ.
Since it is now depending on the measure we chose on the x-axis.
This construction now works with arbitrary measure spaces,
since the x-axis does not need a partition any more.
We just need a partition of the axis that is R anyway.
However, in this case, we really need the notion of a measure,
even in one dimension.
So here, in R, we know what the length of a subinterval is,
it is simply the difference between the right side
and the left side.
But here we need more.
Or in other words:
In the Riemann integral we only measured the lengths of intervals
but in the Lebesgue integral we can have any fragmentation
and we have to know the measure of this fragmentation.
But if we know how to measure any set in the real line,
then we have a very robust integral definition.
Well this generalizes the Riemann integral and eliminates
all problems we had in higher dimensions.
Since this measure theory works for any dimension you want. We just have to know how to measure volumes.
We have also eliminated the problem of dependency on continuity
since we can now measure the size of the set of points where
there is discontinuity.
For example, if we had a set with infinite points of discontinuity,
but the measure of this whole set was 0,
we don't have a problem in the definition of the integral at all.
And also for the last point, so these limit processes,
we have good answers for.
We will see that we have very good limit theorems
that describe these limit processes
for the Lebesgue integral.
Even strong results for the one-dimensional case but also in the general case of measure spaces.
Okay, to sum it up, the Riemann integral is the classical notion,
it may be easier to understand at a beginner level,
but in the end, everyone wants to work with the Lebesgue integral.
Thank you very much and see you next time.