Hello and welcome.
Today I show you how to calculate the kernel of a given matrix.
And this will be an easy example of a 3x4 matrix.
Well, this is the matrix, we will consider here.
And we will consider it over the real numbers,
and as you can see, it has 3 rows.
So 3x4 and 4 is the number of the columns here.
However, first of all, you have to know what the kernel is.
So the kernel of a matrix A is, by definition, the set of all vectors that are sent to 0 by this matrix.
So this means that we have here all vectors x and they come from R^4, since we have 4 columns here.
So we need a vector with 4 rows and then we can give Ax a meaning. So Ax.
So this will be a vector in R^3 and this goes to the zero vector in R^3.
So Ax = 0.
Well, this subspace of R^4 is exactly the kernel of A.
And as you can see, this is just a system of linear equations.
So we calculate the kernel by solving the system of linear equations given by the matrix and the right-hand side: 0.
Therefore, this means that we can row operations  on this system of linear equations, here.
And they don't change the system, so the solution set!
We want the solution set here for the kernel. So we can just do row operations on this matrix inside the kernel here.
And we don't change the kernel! So this is what we do now.
We want to change the second and the third row.
In such a way that we can create zeros here in the first column.
So, meaning, we have to add, on the second row, a multiple of the first row. And this is just 3.
So, -3 times the first row gives us what we want here.
So 0 here; there we have -2; and -2; and 1.
Then, we do the same for the third row. So third row minus 4 times the first row.
And then we have the zero as wanted, and -8 (so -4 -4); and -8 as well; and +4 here.
Okay, now we have the zeros in the first column and we want to do the same in the second column as well.
So we want to create a zero here.
As you can see, this is very easy now. So the new third row here gets just 4 times the new second row here.
And just with minus again.
And then we get: 0, 0, 0, 0.
So very boring here.
But, of course, this was obvious since just the third row here is just a multiple of the second row.
And now we are finished since we arrived at the so-called row echelon form here.
Or in other words, just a triangle form here since all elements below this diagonal here are zero.
This is what we want. Then the system is solved.
Now, we call these variables here, given by these non-zero elements in each column, the bound variables (= leading variables).
And the other ones here, so the 2 here, are the free variables.
And now we can just write it down.
The second row here is an equation. So please keep in mind that we just have the equation with right-hand side zero.
That means that we have, here for the second row, we have -2 times x_2  minus 2 x_3 plus x_4 is equal to zero.
So, now we already set here the free variables.
So, we can just choose here another letter, maybe an alpha and here a beta.
And then, we can just write the bound variable in terms of the free variables.
So here x_2 (so this implies) x_2 is equal to minus alpha.
(so we just divide by 2)
Plus one half beta.
And the equation in the first row gives us x_1 plus x_2 plus 2 times x_3 plus x_4  equals to zero.
But we already know that we can write (maybe I put this here into orange)
We can write x_2 as minus alpha plus one half beta.
We know that this here is just 2 times alpha and this is just beta.
So we can write x_1 also in terms of alpha and beta. And this is just minus alpha (so 2 alpha minus one)
And minus three half beta.
Of course, this is the solution set of our system of linear equations given by Ax = 0.
So now we can just write the solution set, that is the kernel.
So, set brackets here and then we have the vector. So it's minus alpha minus three half beta.
This comes from the x_1 component. And then we have the x_2 component.
Minus alpha plus one half beta. And x_3 and x_4 were the free variables, so just alpha and beta here.
And most importantly, don't forget to write "alpha, beta are coming from R". So they are elements in R.
And this is the whole solution set.
So an arbitrary vector given in this form where alpha and beta are coming from R.
So, of course, we can split this up into two vectors. So we use the alpha coefficient.
Then we have the vector: -1, -1, 1, and zero.
Plus beta and the vector with coefficients in front of beta, so: minus three half, plus one half, 0 and 1.
And the same again: we have to mention that alpha and beta are coming from the real numbers.
So obviously, this is the same set. So we just wrote the vector in another way.
And this is the whole kernel. And by our calculation, we know
that these two vectors here are linearly independent and therefore form a basis of the kernel.
Of this kernel of A.
That means: for this example, the kernel is a two-dimensional subset of R^4.
And this is all for today. Thank you for watching!