Hello and welcome back to
abstract linear algebra,
the video series where we
talk a lot about some advanced
topics in linear algebra.
And now in today's part nine,
I want to talk more about
the so-called change of
basis.
More concretely, we will
look at a common example.
However, as always before
we start, I really want to
thank all the nice people
who support this channel
on Steady, here on youtube
or via Patreon.
And moreover, as a reward,
you find a lot of additional
material for all the videos
with the link in the description.
So if you're interested in
learning mathematics, please
have a look.
OK, then let's immediately
start with the topic of today
by recalling the so
called change of basis
matrix.
We also know it has some
other names like transformation
matrix or transition
matrix.
However, the important fact
is it's a square matrix
that transforms vectors given
in the basis C into
vectors given in the basis
B.
Hence a column vector that
comes in here from the right
hand side should be
interpreted as a vector
represented with respect
to the basis C.
And then the column vector
that comes out is
represented with respect
to the basis B.
So please recall they are
just the images with respect
to the basis isomorphisms.
So usually we say they
represent the same vector
V in our abstract vector
space.
However, with respect to
different chosen bases.
So now we know if the abstract
vector space V has dimension
N, then this change of base
matrix is an N times N
matrix.
Moreover, we also know
it's an invertible matrix.
Of course, this makes sense
because we should be able
to translate back again.
OK.
And now in this video, we
will look at a very concrete
example for such a change
of basis matrix.
Indeed, it's a very common
one and you can always use
it if you want to change
the basis in RN.
This means in our picture
here, the abstract vector
space V is now given
by R two.
And at this point, you might
argue it's not needed to
have this abstract picture
here because the vector space
is already given by the
very concrete one R two.
However, the basis
isomorphism are still
helpful to understand what
is happening here.
This means if we have two
bases given we can
still translate them to R
two again.
Hence we land in R two
again.
But now with the canonical
basis and as
always the corresponding
basis isomorphisms are
denoted by Phi B and
Phi C respectively.
OK.
Now let's look at a very
concrete example, let's say
B is given by two
vectors namely
1 2 and
3 4.
And on the other hand, we
also define C by
two vectors.
And here we choose
1 0 2 2.
The first thing you should
note is that both are
bases in R two.
And maybe you chose spaces
B because it's helpful to
solve a particular problem,
but then you have to solve
another problem.
And then it turns out that
the basis C is
beneficial.
Therefore, the only thing
you need is the change of
basis matrix here.
On the lower level
with this matrix T, you can
do all the translations between
both sides.
However, now, in order to
calculate this matrix, it's
helpful to introduce a
third basis as well.
The reason for this is that
we already have a very nice
basis in R two,
namely we have the canonical
basis, the standard
basis.
And I will denote this with
a curved E
now as a reminder E is
just given by
1 0 0 1.
So you know, this is exactly
the basis we want to have
here on the lower level.
Therefore, our basis
isomorphism in this case
does not change anything.
So Phi E is simply
given by the identity map.
And exactly this fact
implies that we have two
very simple transformation
matrices here.
And please note the first
one here sends B to
E and the second one
here sends E to
C.
And in addition, the composition
of both matrices is
exactly our TCB
and exactly with this matrix
product, we want to
calculate this transformation
matrix.
OK.
Then I would say let's write
down what we already
know, namely,
we already know the
matrix T EB
because it reads that the
basis B is to be
expressed in the standard
basis.
Indeed, if you look at the
basis B, you see the
vectors are already given
with respect to our standard
basis more precisely.
And by definition T E B
is given by Phi
E of b1
in the first column and
Phi E of b two in
the second column.
However, please don't forget
Phi E is just the
identity map.
In other words, we have a
matrix here with b
one and b two in the
columns.
Hence, we can just take the
basis vectors as column
vectors and put them into
a two times two matrix.
So for our example here,
it means we have
1 2 3 4.
In other words, by writing
down the basis B like this,
we already know we have
this change of basis matrix.
And in the same way, we
also have this for the basis
C represented in the
canonical basis as well.
So this is exactly the inverse
of the matrix we actually
need in the end.
However, this is also
something we should already
write down.
So let's write down T E C
and now with the basis vectors
of C, which
as you might recall were
given as
1 0 2 2.
OK.
And with that, you see, we
have all the information
we need to actually
calculate the matrix we
want.
And now I want to show you
the most efficient way to
do it.
Indeed, it's simply a
composition where we have
one inverse involved.
However, first you should
see that the change of basis
matrices nicely fit
together with their indices.
For example, here, if B
goes in from the right hand
side, it also has to
go in from the right here
on the other side.
And moreover, if the basis
C comes out on the left
here, it also has to come
out here.
So whenever you want to put
in a third matrix in the
middle, you just have a matrix
product where E is
also in the middle here.
However, now for our
calculation, we see that
this matrix here is the
inverse of a matrix we already
know.
Hence, we just have to calculate
the inverse here and
multiply the result
with this matrix
T E B.
Now, of course, in this particular
example here, it's no
problem at all to calculate
the inverse of this two times
two matrix.
However, in higher
dimensions, an inverse can
make a lot of problems
because calculating it is
a lot of work.
And actually, we don't need
to know the inverse because
we just need to know this
product here.
Therefore, the efficient
way is to calculate this
product in one go.
Indeed you might already
know how to do that because
it's just a Gaussian elimination.
However, for the sake of
completeness, I want to show
you how to do it.
Now, the first thing you
should note here is that
in order to calculate this
product, we need to solve
an equation.
In fact, the solution of
this matrix equation should
be exactly this
transformation matrix here.
And maybe let's call this
solution.
We want simply X.
And now if we bring this
matrix here to the left hand
side, we simply have
T E C times X
is equal to
T E B so
exactly this is the
matrix equation we want to
solve.
And now the important thing
to note is that this is
simply a system of
linear equations.
More precisely these are
more systems packed together
because we have more right
hand sides.
In this case here, you see
we have exactly two
right-hand sides because
we have two column vectors.
But we can simply do the
Gaussian elimination for
all right hand sides
simultaneously.
And indeed, this immediately
saves a lot of work.
OK.
Now let's write down what
we have to solve.
We have
1 0 2 2 on the
left hand side and
1 2 3 4
on the right hand side.
OK.
And now we can do the Gaussian
elimination as always, which
means we bring the left hand
side into a row echelon
form.
But then we can also do the
backward substitution.
And indeed, in this example,
we already have the row echelon
form.
So we just need to do the
backward substitution.
However, we want to do this
inside this matrix
notation, which
essentially means in order
to solve this system here,
we need to generate an
identity matrix on the left
hand side because
then the components of the
solution X can be read
on the right hand side.
In fact, this is what produces
a nice algorithm for us.
OK.
Here, our first step should
be that we multiply the
second row by one
half because then
we already have the one here
in the right lower corner.
And then in the next step,
we want to generate a zero
here.
Hence, from the first row,
we subtract two times the
new second row.
And then we have it, we have
the identity matrix here
on the left hand side
and on the right hand side,
we find minus one minus
one here and there
we have it, the system is
completely solved.
And with this backward
substitution in this matrix
notation, we find all the
components of the solution
here.
And you see, as we've
expected, we find a
unique solution
and this solution X is
exactly our change of
basis matrix.
So it's exactly TCB
and this answers our question
from the beginning.
So with this matrix now
we can do the translation
from the matrix (basis) B
into the matrix (basis) C.
Moreover, you should see
this whole procedure I've
demonstrated here.
Would also work.
For example, for R five,
the only thing that changes
is that you have a little
bit more work in solving
this system here.
However, the whole idea is
exactly the same.
So now you can apply it to
all other examples.
OK.
So now you know how to
calculate a change of basis
matrix.
So with the next video, we
will go more abstract again.
Therefore, I really hope
we meet again and have a
nice day.
Bye bye.