Hello and welcome.
The mathematical symbol of today is given by the outer product for vectors.
Which is given by this product sign here.
So you see it's a common multiplication sign with a circle around it.
Now since this is such a nice symbol it's also often used to denote other mathamtical objects.
However the outer product for vectors might be the simplest one of these.
Indeed this outer product here is related to the kronecker product for matrices.
Which is also denoted with this symbol.
Therefore some people say the outer product is just a kronecker product, but for vectors.
So maybe i can immediately explain it.
We have one vector on the left hand side of the sign
and one on the right hand side.
Indeed the dimensions could be different.
So we have the 2-dimensional vector here and maybe a 3-dimensional vector on the right hand side.
In other words we have a vector v times a vector w.
and now what should come out is a matrix.
Indeed the height of the matrix is given by the vector v and the width is given by the vector w.
Now the entries of the matrix are not so hard to remember,
because in each column of the matrix we first find a copy of the vector v.
Of course the vector w comes also in, but now we find a copy of it in each row.
This means that you first have to transpose the vector.
and then you can push it to the row.
and in the same way we have it for the second row.
Ok and now you see in each entry of the matrix we just have the product for ordinary numbers.
In fact this is already the whole construction for the kronecker product with two vectors.
and of course it's not hard at all to generalize this to other dimensions than 2 and 3.
You just have to remember how the matrix entries are formed.
So v times w gives us always a matrix.
and now we can just look at a general entry with indices "i" and j.
and as you have learned before this one is simply given by v_i times w_j.
So you see we can use this for the definition of the outer product.
and with this i hope you have learned something today.
Then see you next time.
Bye!