The mathematical symbol of today is a lower case sigma with an index.
Which stands for a Pauli Matrix.
Indeed there are 3 Pauli matrices. Sigma_1, sigma_2 and sigma_3.
And they are very important if you do physics. Especially quantum mechanics.
However of course they are given as mathematical objects, because they are defined as 2x2 matrices.
Therefore they are actually not so complicated.
For example sigma_1 is given as 0, 1.
1, 0.
Then sigma_2 look similarly, but there we need the imaginary unit "i".
So we have 0, -i
i, 0.
and then the last one sigma_3 is simply given as 1, 0, 0, -1.
Now the most important property for the Pauli matrices is that they all square to the identity matrix.
Hence if you multiply the matrix with itself, you get out 1, 0, 0, 1.
This is something that you can easily check for all 3 matrices.
Now another question you could ask is: what happens when we multiply two different Pauli matrices?
and what i can immediately tell you there is that the order matters.
So sigma_j on the left and sigma_k on the right is different from sigma_k on the left and sigma_j on the right.
So what we get out here is not the 0 matrix, when k and j are not the same index.
and indeed what you can show is, this is 2 times the imaginary unit i
times the Levi-Civita symbol epsilon_jkl
Times the Pauli matrix sigma_l.
Now this nice equality holds for all possible combinations of the indices 1, 2, 3.
So maybe it's a good think to check it for some of them.
Ok, now you know the beautiful Pauli matrices.
and if this was helpful then i hope that i see you in the next video.
Bye!