Hello and welcome.
and the mathematical symbol of today is Euler's phi function.
Denoted with a lower case phi.
It's also called Euler's totient function and used in number theory.
Therefore the domain of the function is given by the positive integers.
So we have the natural numbers N. Starting with 1.
and also the codomain is given by the natural numbers.
Now of course the question here should be: What is the definition of phi of n?
and the short answer is that we simply have to count numbers with 2 properties.
So lets use the letter "a" for the numbers we count and then i explain the 2 properties.
The first one is very simple. We only consider numbers that are less or equal than n.
This means that the outcome of the phi function can never be greater than the input.
Then the second property tells us that "a" and n don't have a single common divisor.
Of course except 1, because 1 divides everything.
Hence we can write this as the greatest common divisor.
gcd of "a" and n.
Is equal to 1.
In mathematics then we say that "a" and n are mutually prime.
Now if you have never seen this greatest common divisor then i think examples will help.
For example what is phi of 4?
Now, because of property 1 we already know we only have to look at the numbers 1, 2, 3 and 4.
Of course property 2 immediately tells us that the number itself so 4 here can not be counted.
Indeed you see the gcd(4, 4) would be 4 again. Not 1.
However then you also see that 1 does not have any divisors.
Therefore it always fulfils both properties.
Then in the next step we have to exclude 2, because 2 times 2 is 4.
Ok then looking at 3 we see there is no common divisor greater than 1.
and now you see when we count the numbers that remain that fulfil both properties we get out 2.
Hence phi of 4 is 2
So maybe lets look at another example. So lets choose 5.
Now we can look at the list again, but maybe you already know that 5 is a prime number.
Hence the only number in the list we can cancel would be 5.
Therefore finally we count 4 numbers.
In fact with this reasoning here we can immediately calculate phi of p. When p is a prime number.
and now you know this should be (p - 1).
Now there a lot of other nice properties for Euler's phi function, but maybe this is good enough for this video.
Therefore i hope that i see you next time.
Bye!