The mathematical symbol of today is the factorial.
Which is written with an exclamation mark.
and usually you see the definition for a natural number n.
This is because this n with an exclamation mark, represents a product with exactly n factors.
We start with the number n itself. Then we reduce the number by 1
and then we continue this whole procedure until we reach the number 1.
This means when you see this definition, you know we need a positive integer n such that this makes sense.
For example when you see 4!
This just means you have 4 times 3 times 2 times 1.
Which is, as one can remember 24.
also you should remember 1! is just 1.
Now what you see here with the factorial is what in mathematics we call a recursive definition.
This means that we first fix a starting value and indeed we can do this with 0.
Here 0! should be defined as 1.
This makes sense for a lot of formulas, so this is indeed something you really should remember.
and then the next step in the recursive definition is saying what happens with the successor of a given natural number.
So n! should be n times (n-1)!
So when we know what the factorial does to (n-1), we also know what it does to n.
and because we have a starting value, we now could calculate the values for all other natural numbers n.
Ok, this is the definition for the factorial. Which you can apply for natural numbers n.
Thanks for listening and see you next time.