The mathematical symbol of today is the so called beta function.
Which is denoted with the greek letter beta.
However you see it's the capital letter, which looks like a normal B.
Now the beta function has two variables as its input.
So lets call them x and y.
Indeed x and y could be complex numbers.
However then the real part of both numbers should be positive.
So we write: real part of x greater than 0 and real part of y greater than 0.
Ok by knowing this we now can write down the definition of the beta function.
and indeed it's given by an integral from 0 to 1.
and the variable we integrate over we call t.
Now the first t here has a power, where x occurs.
Indeed the exponent is (x - 1).
and then comes the factor (1 - t), where in the power we find y.
More precisely it's (y - 1).
Ok so this is the whole definition of the beta function.
and when you already know the gamma function i can tell you an important identity.
Indeed the beta function and the gamma function are closely connected.
More concretely B(x, y) can be writen as "gamma(x) times gamma(y) divided by gamma(x + y)."
This can be proven when you use the integral definition of the beta function and the integral definition of the gamma function.
and now i can also tell you, because the gamma function is related to the factorial, the beta function is related to the binomial coefficient.
However that can be a whole topic for another video.
Here you have seen the definition of the beta function and i hope that this was helpful.
In this case i see you next time.
Bye!