Hello and welcome back to the next mathematical symbol.
Which is the subset symbol.
For denoting such a subset relation you either see this symbol or that.
Personally I prefer this notation, because the line here immediately tells you that the equality of sets is also allowed here.
However some authors take this simple arc here. Maybe because it's shorter.
Therefore please always pay attention to which symbol is used in a given book.
It's very important, because often there is also a notation which is used to denote a proper subset.
This means there the equality is actually not allowed.
Hence if we use the first notation here, we can do the same if we denote inequalities.
So you see, if we want to denote a proper subset, we can just omit the line here.
So unfortunately this is the same symbol some people use to denote a general subset.
However this also means that these people need another notation for a proper subset
and usually they use the first symbol, where they just cross the line underneath.
Ok, so in summary what you should remember is that the symbols here come always in these two combinations
and they just tell you that one set is contained in another.
So if this here is the set B, the set A should lie completely inside
and then we would just write: "A is a subset of B"
and indeed most of the time we will not exclude the equality here
and now this symbol just means that for all x the following implication is true.
So if x is an element in A, it's also an element in B.
So you see, this new definition just goes back to the element relation
and now since we have the implication from left to right, you also often see a mirrored version of this symbol.
More precisely you would say: "B is a superset of A"
and then of course this means exactly the same thing written here.
So I would say now you know the subset symbol and also the superset symbol
and if you want to learn more details about sets, I have a whole video series about it called "start learning sets".
So I really hope I see you there or in the next video about mathematical symbols.
So have a nice day and bye.