Hello and welcome.
and the mathematical symbol of today is the so called Heaviside function.
Often denoted with a capital H.
However you also often see the greek letter Theta.
Moreover sometimes the Heaviside function is called the unit step function.
This is because the definition of H(x) is very simple.
There is just one step involved.
So we can consider 2 cases.
So either the function is 1 or 0.
and indeed the sign of x tells us in which case we are.
Positive points get the value 1 and negative points get the value 0.
Therefore only the question remains what to do with the point 0.
and as you can see here we put it to 1.
However there are also other conventions what to do.
Sometimes x = 0 is set to 0.5.
Then the value lies exactly in the middle here.
However actually for a lot of applications it does not matter at all what we do with the point x = 0.
The important thing is just that we have this step here.
Hence the graph of the function looks very simple. We just have these 2 constant parts.
Ok now you know the Heaviside function.
Which is by the way not called Heaviside, because there is a heavy side in the graph.
It's called Heaviside as in the mathematician Oliver Heaviside.
Ok then just i tell you one last fun fact for the end of the video.
You can calculate the derivative of H and you get something nice out.
Of course what comes out should be 0 here and here
and maybe not defined here at 0.
However this only happens if you do a classical derivative.
What one can do is use the derivative for distributions.
and then what comes out is the famous Dirac delta distribution.
This is a really nice connection if you see both functions as distributions.
In fact if you want to know more about distributions, i have a whole series about them.
Therefore i hope i see you there.
Have a nice day. Bye!