The mathematical symbol of today is modulo.
Written as mod.
mod.
This is the modulo operator which i explain here as a binary operator.
Which means we have a number x on the left hand side and a number n on the right hand side.
and this whole operation here gives us a number back.
Indeed often x and n are chosen as positive integers, but the whole thing also for positive real numbers.
Now the whole idea of this operation is that you get the remainder after you divide x by n.
For example if you consider (5 mod 3) you immediately see 3 only fits one times into 5.
So what remains, what you can't divide is 2.
In other words 5 is not a multiple of 3. We have to subtract 2 to get one.
Therefore the next example is simpler. If you have (6 mod 3), you see this fits well. We get out 0 as the remainder.
So you see if we divide 6 by 3 we get out exactly 2, but we are not interested in the 2.
We are only interested in the remainder. Which is 0 in this case.
Ok then with the next example maybe lets leave the integers and now we consider (7.1 mod 3).
Also here we find that the 3 fits 2 times into the number on the left hand side.
Hence the remainder term is exactly 1.1
So i hope you now know how this works.
I like thinking of subtracting 3 so many times until something less than 3 remains.
and the thing that remains is exactly our result.
So maybe i should also explain this with an example.
So lets consider (9.7 mod 2.1)
So first lets subtract 2.1 here. So we get 7.6
So lets do this again and then we get 5.5
Of course we do it again and then we get 3.4
and then in the last step we finally get 1.3
Which is of course less than 2.1
Hence this is our result here.
So this is how you can think of this, but the important thing is always remember it's the remainder term we want here.
Hence here for the definition we could simply say: this is a number r.
and this number lies in the interval 0 to n.
Where n is not included.
However of course the remainder term could be 0.
Moreover now we also know how we get this number r, because we can write x as a sum.
Namely it's n times an integer, we can call q + the remainder term r.
So you see for our positive numbers x and n this is exactly the procedure we explained before.
Ok now for the end of the video i want to show you how the modulo operator is included in Phyton.
Indeed this is simple. Instead of mod we use the % sign.
So you see this is exactly what the modulo operator should do.
and of course it also works for our decimal numbers, as we had it before.
However as you can see what can occur are some rounding errors.
Ok and with this i hope i see you next time.
Bye!