hello and welcome.
The mathematical symbol of today is the binomial coefficient.
Written with parentheses.
and there at the top we find an integer n and at the bottom an integer k.
Now usually you read this binomial coefficient as "n choose k".
We do this, because it represents the number of possibilities to choose k elements from a fixed set with n elements.
Here i always think it's a good idea to visualize this with an example.
So here you see we have 7 balls. So n is equal to 7.
and now i tell you we take 3 of them out. So k is equal to 3.
Here maybe one possibility would be to get 2, 3 and 6.
and please note here there is no order involved.
So we take them out with one pick.
Of course still there are a lot of other examples.
Maybe 5, 6 and 7.
and now the question the binomial coefficient answers, is how many possibilities there are.
Therefore i would suggest trying to calculate them.
So here you see 3 empty slots that we can fill in with numbers.
Now if we just take out one ball then we could have any number here in the first position.
Hence counting the possibilities we have exactly n here.
Then for the second position we take out another ball.
However now the first ball is already gone. So we have exactly (n - 1) numbers.
and finally for the third position (n - 2) numbers remain.
Now multiplying these numbers gives us exactly the possibilities for filling in these slots with the balls here.
However then you might see we have an order involved.
Therefore we have to divide this thing here by the number of orders we have for these slots.
Indeed the reasoning now is similar to before.
If you want to rearrange the first ball, the first slot, you have 3 positions to choose.
Then for the second only 2 remain and for the last one only 1 remains.
and with this we have it. This is what the binomial coefficient should do.
So in general here we would have: n times (n - 1) times (n - 2) and so on until we reach (n - k + 1).
So you should see this is the generalisation of our example.
and moreover then we would find k! in the denominator.
So indeed this is the definition of the binomial coefficient "n choose k".
and for the end i can tell you there is a shorter definition for this.
Namely we have n! divided by k! as before and also (n - k)!.
There you should see these 2 parts here just cancel to get you this.
Ok so this is the binomial coefficient.
and i hope that you learned something today.
Then see you next time.
Bye!