Hello and welcome back to
start learning
reals.
And as always, I want to
thank all the nice people
that support this channel
on study or paypal.
In today's part four, I will
show you how we can actually
construct the real numbers.
This means that the starting
point is the field of the
rational numbers.
And then we form a new field
where every Cauchy sequence
is actually convergent.
Now because you have seen
all the other number
constructions, you might
already guess that also
here equivalence relations
will be helpful.
Our idea in this case should
be that each point on the
number line can be
represented by a Cauchy
sequence.
For example, for the 0.1
3rd, we can choose the
sequence that has the
members one third, one third
and so on.
So it's simply a constant
sequence.
Therefore, in particular
a Cauchy sequence and also
a convergence sequence.
However, the important part
is that the limit is our
0.1 3rd.
Therefore, this infinite
sequence of numbers
represents one point on the
number line.
But now you should see that
this representation can be
in no way unique because
we can just write down another
sequence with the same limit.
For example, we can just
use decimals and start with
0.3.
Of course, you already know
this is just another notation
for the fraction 3/10.
And then the next member
in the sequence should be
0.33.
With this, we just continue
a pending threes.
OK.
With this, we have a well
defined sequence where you
can also easily check that
it is also a Cauchy sequence.
And because we get arbitrarily
close to 1/3,
eventually, we also know
we have a conversion sequence
with limit one third.
So we can conclude when we
form our equivalence classes
soon, these two sequences
here should land in one
single box simply
because they have the same
limit.
However, you already know
we cannot just look at the
limits because there are
Cauchy sequences in Q
without limits.
Indeed, for this, we will
find a simple solution.
OK.
The first step is to define
the set of all the Cauchy
sequences we consider.
So here XN stands for a
sequence which means an
infinite list with the
properties that
for all natural numbers
NXN is
a rational number
and that the sequence
XN is indeed a Cauchy
sequence.
And this nice set that contains
all the Koshy sequences
is denoted by C.
Now for two elements from
the set, let's call them
A and BN.
So for two Cauchy
sequences, we define
an equivalence relation
OK.
At this point we want that
these two sequences here
are equivalent, but we don't
want to use the explicit
limit.
Therefore, the question is
here, how can we do that
in a simple way for
this?
Let's imagine that we see
all the sequence members
here on the number line.
In the case that the two
Cauchy sequences, we present
the same point, they
accumulate around this
number.
So the sequence members get
closer and closer to this
point.
Therefore, the difference
between two members from
the two sequences gets
smaller and smaller.
Hence, this difference is
the new sequence we should
consider.
And now we already discussed
that it should be a convergence
sequence with limit zero.
In other words, for any point
on the number line, we just
shift the problem to zero.
OK.
Now we have everything we
need because we can show
that this defines indeed
an equivalence relation.
This means that we can show
the three properties.
It's reflexive symmetric
and transitive.
Now, as always, when we have
such a nice equivalence
relation, we can go over
to the boxes where we put
in the equivalent Cauchy
sequences.
And we call these boxes
equivalence classes
by definition, the equivalence
class of X and is
just a set of all Cauchy
sequences that are
equivalent to XN.
And therefore, this equivalence
class now uniquely
represents one point on the
number line.
To put it.
In other words, we now can
actually define the real
numbers, the set
R is just given by the
set of all equivalence
classes.
So the set of these boxes
defines the complete number
line.
Now, the only things that
are still missing are the
two operations, addition
and multiplication and the
ordering.
Therefore, for the first
part, let's define how we
can add two equivalence classes
here.
Indeed, that's not hard at
all.
We can just use the addition
we have for the rational
numbers for all the members
of the two sequences.
Of course, as always, then
we need to check that this
definition does not depend
on the chosen representation
of the two occurrence classes.
In this case, you just have
to calculate a little bit
with the sequences.
And then we get out.
Yes, it's well defined.
And afterwards, you will
believe me that everything
works the same.
When we define the multiplication,
we just use again the well
known multiplication for
rational numbers.
OK.
Now looking back at the axioms
we want to fulfill, you see
that the last thing we need
to define is an ordering.
So we want to define in which
cases one equivalence class
is greater than another.
One.
Of course.
Here we need to use the
ordering we have for the
rational numbers again.
However, claiming this for
all sequence members is
much too restrictive for
us to see this.
Please keep the number line
in mind.
For example, our B and C
could accumulate around
one third and
maybe the sequence with AM
has zero as the limit.
But of course, we have infinitely
many sequence members here.
Therefore, for example, a
four could lie over here,
but still the limit would
be zero.
Hence, this inequality
here should be satisfied
only eventually.
In other words, we can just
ignore finally many
members.
Therefore, we would write
there exists a capital N
such that for all indices
greater than capital N, we
have A N is less
than BN.
OK.
This now looks better, but
it is still not correct.
In order to see this, just
imagine one point on a number
line where the sequence BN
comes from above and the
sequence A comes from
below.
So they should describe the
same point but this
one is still fulfilled.
Therefore, maybe it's better
to think in distances.
So let's bring this one to
the other side, then it
simply reads that BN
minus A is greater than
zero.
Therefore, this means that
the distance here could be
arbitrary small.
And when you look back at
the first example here, that's
not what we want.
So there should be an actual
minimal distance between
the two points.
And maybe we just call this
distance simply
delta.
So we simply have to add,
there exists a distance
delta greater than zero.
Of course, the distance delta
could be very small.
The point is it holds then
for all end
OK.
There we have it, these are
all the operations we need
for the real numbers.
Now, in the last step, one
can just calculate that all
the properties we want, the
axioms are actually
satisfied.
For example, we can define
the zero element and the
one element and show that
we have a field again.
However, the important part
we have now by construction
is the completeness axiom.
Every Cauchy sequence is now
actually convergent
with this, we can close this
video and I hope that you
now know a lot about real
numbers.
And in the next videos we
will talk about the complex
numbers.
Therefore, I hope I see you
there and have a nice day.
Bye.