Hello and welcome back to probability theory.
and as always, first i want to thank all the nice people that support this channel on Steady or Paypal.
and in todays part 5 we will talk about the so called product case.
More precisely we will talk about product spaces, product sigma algebras and product probability measures.
Now before we can define this product case, we first have to talk about the definition of a probability space.
Indeed this is not so complicated, because we already have all we need for this.
We just need a sample space Omega, a sigma algebra "A" and a probability measure "P".
Of course they all should fit together, which means the sigma algebra is a sigma algebra for Omega.
and also the probability measure is defined on the sigma algebra.
Then in this case all these 3 things together, which we call a triple, is called a probability space.
So the meaning here is, we have an abstract space, where we can calculate with probabilities.
Now the product case occurs when we want to combine multiple probability spaces.
In this case we can simply introduce an index "n".
Depending on the context here we could have 2, 3 or even infinitely many probability spaces.
However i want to stay at countable many, so we choose the natural numbers as the index set.
Now this whole idea seems very so i would suggest that we first look at an example.
To keep it simple lets combine two random experiments we already know.
First lets take a discrete case, where we just look at the throw of a die.
and then lets do a continuous case, where we throw a point into this interval.
In other words here we have an one dimentional dart game.
and we can hit real numbers between -1 and 1.
Now because we have an order here, we first do the one experiment, then the other, our outcome would be a tuple.
Which is in this case is just a pair of two numbers.
For example 3, 0.25 would be a possible outcome.
Now the overall question would be how can we calculate probabilities in this scenario
In order to answer this we first have to write down the corresponding probability spaces.
Now for the first probability space we take the index 1.
Of course we already know for throwing a die the corresponding sample space would be the numbers 1 to 6.
and then the sigma algebra can be chosen as the power set.
Moreover we also know what the probability measure "P_1" should be in this case.
The probability mass function is just given by 1 over 6.
Now in the same way we can also say what the second probability space should be.
Of course here lets take the index 2.
Of course now we already know the sample space should be the full intervall from -1 to 1.
and consequently in the continuous case we have the Borel sigma algebra.
and then the probability measure "P_2" can be written as an integral.
Where the probability density function is given by 0.5.
Ok the only thing we have to do now is to combine both probability spaces into a new one..
Since you already know, the possible outcomes are given by pairs, we know that the new sample space should be the cartesian product.
This means that in an abstract sense, we have Omega_1 on the x-axis and Omega_2 on the y-axis.
and now possible events where we want to measure probabilities are just given by subsets in this plane.
Therefore we already know what the new probability space should be.
First the sample space should be given by this cartesian product.
This means that we have an order here. First we throw the die and then the dart.
and now the sigma algebra we need here is what we usually call the product sigma algebra.
To define this we take the cartesian product of the two sigma algebras and then say
use the sigma algebra that is generated by this set.
Maybe we shouldn't focus here on the sigma algebra, because it can distract from the overall idea.
However later i will tell you a little bit more about this construction.
If you want to know more details you can look at my measure theory series. It's part 17.
There i also explained how we can define the probability measure, we just call "P" now.
It's a well defined probability measure and we just call it the product measure.
For us now it's not important to know the whole construction, but only one important property this measure has.
For this lets look at two events. The first we call "A_1" from the first sigma algebra and the other one "A_2" from the second sigma algebra.
and then we want to calculate the probability of the cartesian product, which is a subset in the plane here.
Now, the nice property of the product measure is that this is exactly the product of the two single probabilities.
This means, if we know these two probabilities, we can immediately calculate this probability.
Hence lets look what we get in our example here.
Here i want to caluclate the probability that we first throw a 2 or a 3
Of course with the die.
and then with the dart we want to hit the first half.
Hence the event we want to measure is this cartesian product.
and by our formula for our product measure this is simply this product.
Hence first we use "P_1" here and then "P_2".
and it's not hart to see that we first have "1/3" times 0.5.
So the probability of this event is exactly 1 over 6.
Ok, so what you should see with this example is that the product case is very natural and also very important for calculations.
Therefore now lets write down the general definition.
Instead of two we now look at infinitely many probability spaces.
Lets denote them as before, where we choose the index set as the natural numbers.
To define the product space we use the same symbols, but now without an index.
At this point we already have a rough idea, what this space should be.
The sample space Omega is just the cartesian product as before, but now an infinite one.
Indeed one often denotes that with a product sign.
Now the important thing to note here is that elements of this sample space, are not just tuples now, but sequences.
and they have the property, like in this example, the lower case Omega_3 comes from the sample space Omega_3.
So you see the sample space is not complicated at all.
However the sigma algebra "A" is much harder to write down.
Usually we just say in short it's generated by cylinder sets.
and in this case we denote that as before with a sigma at front.
Now the idea here is that we first consider special subsets of this infinite cartesian product.
Namely they look like this. Where we have the whole space, where we only change one sample space.
So infinitely many are still at Omega_j.
Indeed this is the important thing. So this would be another example.
and then we look at the smallest sigma algebra that contains all these subsets.
and with this we have the thing, we call the product sigma algebra.
So you see it's just a generalisation of the part we had before with only two factors.
and exactly the same holds for the product measure.
Here please recall, we want to be able to measure probabilities like this one.
However now in our case we have an infinite cartesian product.
For the cylinder sets we already discussed the idea, that we only want to change finitely many sets here.
This means that after we reach the index "m" only Omegas will follow.
We do this, because in this case we have a similar formula as before.
We have the finite product of the single probabilities.
This is important, because as before it means we can immediately calculate such a probability.
Ok, so this whole thing is the abstract definition of the product space you really should remember.
and maybe it's easier to understand it, if we look at an example.
So maybe we keep it simple here and stay with our ordinary die.
Now lets throw this die very often. Indeed infinitely many times.
Now the big advantage here you immediately see is that each of these Omegas in the cartesian product is the same.
Of course for every throw we have the same die. Therefore we don't have to distinguish the indices here.
Hence lets keep it simple and lets use the index 0 each time.
and of course we already know this is the probability space, where we throw the die only once.
Accordingly we can immediately write down the corresponding product space.
The sample space Omega is just the infinite cartesian product, where at each step we have Omega_0.
and of course the product sigma algebra "A" and the product measure "P" are immediately given by the definition above.
Ok, now in order to make our example more concrete lets calculate the probability of a given event.
So lets simply call the event "A".
Here the event should be given as at the 100-th throw we get a 6 for the first time.
Therefore the first step is always to put that into a formula.
So what we have here is that at the first throw we don't get a 6.
So it would be the complement of the set that only contains 6.
The notation i use for this is simply a "c" as an upper index.
In fact we need this set 99 times.
After this comes the 100-th throw, which means now we have the set that only contains 6.
Now the good thing is that we also know that afterwards it does not matter what happens.
Therefore here only Omega_0 occurs in the cartesian product.
Ok, now because we have the formula from above we can immediately calculate the probability of "A".
We just have to put "P_0" in front of these sets and multiply them.
Therefore we get this nice formula here.
In fact it's the one probability to the power of 99 times the other one.
Hence it's not hard to calculate we have 5 over 6 to the power 99 times 1 over 6.
Therefore this is the probability of our event "A".
and of course i can tell you it's very, very small.
Ok, with this i now hope that you can work with product spaces more easily.
and then i see you in the next video. Bye!