Hello and welcome back to probability theory.
and as always first i want to thank all the nice people that support this channel on Steady or Paypal.
Now in todays part 6 we will talk about the Hypergeometric distribution.
It's the name for an important probability measure, we find for discrete cases.
and here we will talk about the general formulation for it. Also called the multivariant Hypergeometric distribution.
Here you can immediately keep 3 important ingredients in mind.
First the size is given by a natural number n,
The sample is unordered and without replacement.
Hence a useful visualisation is again given by an urn model.
This means that in this model we take out n balls from the urn and look what we get.
So we don't have an order and we don't replace the balls.
Therefore in short you could say we draw n balls at once.
and there you should see, this is only interesting if we have different coloured balls in the urn.
For example we could have 4 different colours here.
Hence our first question here is: how can we mathematically formulate this?
First we can say that the different colours are just given by a finite set we call capital C.
In our example here we could just index the colours, so we choose numbers from 0 to 3.
Of course every set with 4 elements would do the work, but working with numbers is much easier for calculations.
Also here in our simple example we could talk about possible outcomes, maybe in the case that n is equal to 5.
One possible sample could be this one, where we have 2 green balls, 1 red ball, 1 blue ball and 1 orange ball.
We don't have an order. We can just count how many balls of each colour we have.
Hence in mathematical terms, here we would have a function from the set of colours, C into the natural numbers including 0.
and there you see immediately it's very helpful to index the colours with numbers.
Because then we can rewrite this function into a tuple with 4 coordinates.
So in this example here we would have 2 green balls, 1 red one, 1 blue one and 1 orange one.
So what we always should have is that the sum of all these numbers is equal to 5.
Then this could be a possible outcome of our random experiment here.
Ok now with this knowledge we are able to write down the sample space Omega.
It's simple the set of all functions or tuples of this form.
So in general we would say, we have numbers k_c, where the lower case c goes through all the colours in set C.
and then we say, this is an element of the natural numbers including 0 to the power c.
So this is the general notation of all the functions from the set C into N_0.
It's a helpful notation, because it reminds us that we can also rewrite the function as a tuple.
and we also put that into this notation here.
Ok and now the only condition we have here is that all these numbers add up to n.
So we can simply write: sum of k_c is equal to n.
and then we have our whole sample space Omega.
Of course you already know as for all discrete cases the sigma algebra is just chosen as just the power set of Omega.
Therefore we can immediately go to the probability measure.
and maybe also for this it's helpful to first look at our example here.
For our example you already know we have tuples of 4 elements.
Hence we can say we have k_0, k_1, k_2, k_3 from N_0 to the power 4.
and also the sum should be the sample size n.
Now you might already see for calculating the probability of an outcome,
we have to know how many balls of each colour are actually in the urn.
For this we have to introduce new variables.
Hence capital N with index c stands for this number.
and then of course the total number of balls in the urn is given by the sum of all these numbers.
Here we will simply use the symbol N for it.
Ok, now by knowing all this we can start calculating probabilities.
As always in discrete cases knowing the probability mass function is enough.
Hence we just calculate the probability of a singleton.
Now here we just have to count all the possibilities we can have.
and then we will have a fraction here.
Ok, we already know what is in the denominator,
because there we find all possibilities to take n balls from capital N ones.
So we simply have capital N choose lower case n.
Ok, then for the next step, you should see we want exactly k_0 green balls.
So we simply have N_0 choose k_0.
and of course we have the same thing for all the other colours.
Therefore in the next step we have times N_1 choose k_1.
and then times N_2 choose k_2 times N_3 choose k_3.
and with this we have our probability we call the hypergeometric distribution.
Therefore in the next step lets formulate this in a general case.
Also here we just give the probability mass function. So we put in a singleton.
Which we describe as before as k_c.
Then now you know we find a fraction, where in the numerator we find a product of all the colours.
So we have the product symbol with N_c choose k_c.
and the denominator we already know.
Ok and there we have it. This is the hypergeometric distribution in the general case.
Now often only 2 colours are involved, which means the whole thing here gets very simple.
However the simple case is also often known as the hypergeometric distribution.
Therefore it might be worth it to write down the formulas for the special case as well.
Of course the whole set up is the same, but we can make the sample space much simpler.
The reason for that is that for two colours only one degree of freedom remains.
For example if we draw n balls and we count the number of red balls, which means the number of ones
We immediately get the number of green balls, which means the number of zeros.
Hence if we just count the ones, we can say a sample is just the number.
This means that we can take the sample space Omega as a set 0 to n.
and then of course we can also simplify the probability mass function here.
So lets look at P of the singleton k and copy what we already know.
Which means we have N choose n in the denominator
and in the numerator we have 2 factors.
Now here k_1 is simply our k and k_0 is (n-k).
and also we don't have to write capital N_0 here, because we can use capital N - capital N_1.
and there we have it. This is the compact formulation for the hypergeometric distribution when we only have two kinds of balls.
Now for the last part of this video let me show you, how you can find this distribution in R.
It's simply given by "rhyper". So lets look at the manual here.
So you see this is the hypergeometric distribution and if we scroll down you see rhyper and all the variables here.
The arguments are explained below and this k here is actually our lower case n.
and you also see the other variables stand for the number of white balls and the number of black balls.
So in our formulation this would be capital N_1 and capital N_0.
and additionally we have the first argument for the number of repetitions.
Therefore i would say lets see what happens when we have one observation, 9 white balls, 3 black balls and we pull 5 balls out.
Then when we hit enter, we see our outcome.
So the number of white balls we got is just counted.
Ok, then lets repeat the whole random experiment.
So here we got 3 white balls. Which means we got also 2 black ones.
Ok so now maybe we can use the first argument to do a lot of repetitions of this random experiment.
So lets say we do 20.
So there you see we have a lot of of fours, but not a two.
However we know that two is possible.
Therefore maybe lets go to 200 observations.
and there you see, we find some twos, but they are very unlikely.
Hence to visualize that, lets put it into a histogram.
So we put "hist" in front.
and close the parentheses and hit enter.
The first thing we note is that it's not the best visualization for a histogram yet,
but we already have that two is very unlikely.
Now one possibility to make the whole histogram nicer, is to tell R where it should put the bits.
and these break points we can put into a vector x.
So lets choose steps of one, where we start at 1.5 and end at 5.5.
So lets hit enter and there you see our x.
and this vector x is now what we can put into the histogram function as an argument.
This is not so complicated. We choose the histogram function and then we put in ", " and "breaks"
and then these breaks should be equal to our vector x.
and there you can see, this is what comes out.
So maybe lets repeat it to see immediately what can change.
So it's almost the same. We have the same behaviour. 2 is very unlikely, but 5 is more likely.
Hence maybe we need to be more precise. Lets go to 2000 repetitions.
and there we get this histogram.
and then i want to repeat it again and again. To see that we are very much stable here.
So what you should see here is, that for this example the highest probability is at 4.
and the lowest is at 2. So we don't have a symmetric distribution.
This is the case, because we take out a lot of balls compared to the number of balls of each kind inside the urn.
Therefore i would suggest, play around with these numbers
and compare the result with the binomial distribution, we have already discussed.
Ok, then i think it's good enough for today and i hope i see you in the next video.
Have a nice day. Bye!