Hello and welcome back to probability theory.
and of course as always first i want to thank all the nice people that support this channel on Steady or Paypal.
Now this is part 7 in the series and we will talk about the so called conditional Probability.
It's a special name for a probability measure that is defined relatively to another probability measure.
Today i will explain this definition and also show you an example.
Now the starting point here could be any probability space.
Which means we have a sample space Omega, a sigma algebra A and probability measure P.
Maybe here it's a good idea to visualize Omega with a rectangle.
Hence the area should represent the probability measure P.
Which means the whole are has the value 1.
However if we look at a subset B in Omega. Which has probability less than 1.
Then we can visualize that as a smaller rectangle inside Omega.
and of course B should be an element of the sigma algebra A. Otherwise we wouldn't be able to calculate the probability.
Now the actual restriction we have here in the following, is that the probability of B is not 0.
So in our picture this would mean, we have a non-vanishing rectangle.
and when we have this we get immediately a new probability measure.
Moreover we even get the whole new probability space.
Now instead of Omega we take B as the new sample space.
Of course we can simply do that, but then we have the question:
what is the new sigma algebra and what is the new probability measure?
For the sigma algebra the answer is very straight forward.
If you only want to work in B, we can only consider subsets of B.
So we can take any element A from the original sigma algebra, if it fulfills that A is a subset of B.
and then of course we could measure the probability of A as before.
Therefore P tilde could simply be the same probability measure as before.
So in our picture it would just give us the area of the set A.
However there we see a problem, because the maximal area we would get out, would be the area of B.
Which is in general not 1.
Indeed what we rather want would be a ratio.
So the ratio of the area of A to the area of B.
Hence in our formula we have that P(A) gets divided by P(B).
Only now we have a well defined probability measure.
Because now when we put in the sample space B, we get out 1.
Ok, now i can tell you this is almost a full idea of a conditional probability.
I say almost, because actually we don't want to change the sample space and the sigma algebra.
In other words this means that we also have to consider sets A that are not subsets of B.
For example they could look like this.
So as you can see, it could have a very large area, but the intersection with the set B could be small.
Therefore you might already know how we can transform this definition here to the whole space Omega.
So our new probability space only gets a new probability measure.
and for the moment lets put an index B to it.
Now for the definition please remind yourself that we still want to measure the ratio of 2 areas.
Which means the denominator is the same as before. Which means the whole area of B,
but the numerator should now be this area.
Speaking of probabilities this would be the probability of the intersection.
and now this is the definition of the conditional probability of an event A under the event B.
Therefore i would suggest putting this into formal definition.
Of course the assumptions are the same as before. We have a probability space and also a set B, with a nonzero probability.
and then we can define the conditional probability as a new probability measure.
In fact sometimes this index notation is used for this probability measure, but often we have another notation.
Namely one uses the bar inside the parentheses and puts the condition, the set B, to the right hand side.
and then we call this number the conditional probability of the event A under the condition B.
Moreover if one wants to talk about the abstract probability measure, one uses the following notation.
We simply put a dot, where the set should go in.
and then we call this well defined measure the conditional probability measure given B.
Ok, then please never forget this measure has an important property. Namely when we put in B, we get out 1.
Of course this something we get immediately out.
Speaking of this definition here, you see it won't work if P(B) would be 0.
However now sometimes it happens that we simply don't want to check that.
Maybe we don't have enough information, but we still want to calculate with the conditional probabilities.
Therefore in this case we will use the following definition. This symbol just represents the number 0 then.
This will be useful for a lot formulas later.
However please not here in this case, we don't have such a probability measure.
Ok, so i think that's enough for the definition. Lets look at an example.
and as often it's helpful to talk about the general urn model.
So i would say lets do something new and look at an ordered one.
and to keep it simple, lets consider only 4 balls with 2 different colours.
Then lets do 2 steps. First we take out one ball. We don't replace it and then we take out the second one.
Hence a sample we get is always an ordered pair.
It has a first position and also a second position.
This means when we introduce a coloured set C with 2 colours, which is in our case green and red.
Then the sample space Omega is given by the cartesian product of C with itself.
Ok and the sigma algebra as for all discrete models, is given by the power set.
So the only thing missing here would be the probability measure itself.
Also here since we have a discrete model, the probability measure is given by a probability mass function.
and the best way to calculate this, is to look here at the different stages we have in our random experiment.
Therefore i would say a visualisation with a tree can really help.
So the first stage is very simple. We just take out one ball and the probabilities should be very clear.
3/4 in the favour of green and 1/4 in the favour of red.
Ok, then in the second stage we take out a second ball. Which also can be either green or red.
However now we have different probabilities, because we have fewer balls left in the urn.
So for the left hand side we have 2/3 for green and 1/3 for red.
Yet on the right hand side there are no red balls left. Therefore we have 1 for green and 0 for red.
Ok, then in summary with each path in the tree, we have exactly one value for the probability mass function.
For example for this part we first have green then red. So we have 3/4 times 1/3.
Which is simply 1/4.
On the other hand, first green, then green again gives us 1/2.
Then red, green is also 1/4.
and the other one is 0.
Ok there we have the whole probability measure and now we can finally talk about the conditional probability.
Therefore lets fix a condition B. So an event from the sigma algebra A.
In words, for example this could be: the first ball is green.
and in the formula this would just mean we take the 2 events that have green at the beginning.
So this is our subset of Omega, we want as a condition.
and then lets calculate the probability of (g, r) under the condition B.
So this is a nice conditional probability which shouldn't be so hard to calculate.
Indeed we can immediately use the definition and write it down.
So in the numerator we have the intersection and in the denominator we have the probability of B.
Of course this intersection here we can immediately simplify.
and now this probability of (g, r) we already know.
and in addition we also know the probability of B is given by 3/4.
Hence the overall result here is 1/3.
So this is our conditional probability here.
and maybe it's not so surprising, but still interesting, we find the number also here in the tree.
This is the case, because this first step here was exactly our condition B.
However it's important to know that the notion conditional probability is not restricted to such cases.
In fact any event could work as an condition.
Later we will see more examples and then we will also talk about independence.
Which is indeed related to the conditional probability.
and with this i hope i see you in the next videos about probability theory.
Have a nice day and bye!