Hello and welcome back to probability theory.
and as you know, first i want to thank all the nice people that support this channel on Steady or Paypal.
Now, in todays part 8 we will talk about 2 important formulas. Namely about the total probability formula and about Bayes's theorem.
This formula of Bayes is so famous that we should immediately start with this.
However it's not so complicated at all, because we already know the conditional probability of an event A under B.
Which is simply given by the probability of the intersection divided by the probability of B.
and now of course we can also filp the roles and look at the conditional probability of B under the event A.
Then we also have the intersection, but then we divide by probability of A.
However, the important part here is: the intersection is the same.
Hence with this part we can put both equations together.
Which leads us for left hand side to P(A|B) times P(B) and on the right hand side it leads us to P(B|A) times P(A).
and in fact, this is what we call Bayes's theorem.
In this order it's easy to remember, because here we have the condition B and P(B) and here the condition A and P(A).
Ok, at the end of the video i can show you how we can use this formula.
However before we do this lets talk about the law of total probability.
It tells us which possibilities we have to split up a probability.
So as always we choose a probability space given by a sample space Omega, a sigma algebra A and the probability measure P.
and now we want to calculate the probability of a subset A.
So the question is: how can we split up P(A)?
Now, one possibility would be to choose another set B.
In the picture we can also visualize this maybe like this.
So the set B is here and you immediately see how this set A is divided now.
We get this, because we have the set B and the complement of B.
and of course both together in a union gives us the whole sample space Omega.
Important to note here is, this is indeed a disjoint union.
Therefore this division here works no matter which event A we choose.
and this is now what we can put into a formula.
So we have P(A), where we can write A as a disjoint union.
Namely the union of the upper part here we have in B, with the other part we have in B^c.
and because this is a disjoint union, we can use the property of the measure and write it as a sum.
So we have the probability of this intersection + the probability of that intersection.
Now as before an intersection we can rewrite as a conditional probability.
For the first one we write P(A|B) times P(B).
and for the second one we use the same formula, but now with the complement of B.
So you see, this is a nice formula, we can use to calculate the probability of A, when we know these 4 probabilities here.
However the law of total probability goes even further.
We can also deal with the case that we don't have only one set B, but countably many.
So we could have 2, 3 or even infinitely many.
Hence we simply say we have B_i, where i comes from the index set that is a subset of the natural numbers.
and of course we have to generalize this property here.
This means that the union of all these sets is equal to Omega.
and in addition as before, it needs to be a disjoint union.
Now lets also visualize this in a picture.
There is our sample space Omega again and now we don't just find one set B, but a lot of them.
For example such a decomposition of Omega could look like this.
and here please don't forget it's possible that we have infinitely many sets B_i.
Therefore in this picture they would get thiner and thiner when we go in this direction, for example.
Of course there are a lot possibilities to visualize this.
However the important part here is that we also have a set A of which we want to calculate the probability.
In fact this now works exactly with the same steps as before.
So first we can write a set A as a disjoint union.
Of course this is again, the intersection with the B_i's. Which means in the picture we just put all these parts here together.
Ok then because it's a disjoint union, we can use the sigma additivity of the measure.
So we get out this sum for the probabilities or a series when we have infinitely many.
However in both cases we can us the conditional probabilities again.
So we have the sum of P(A|B_i) times the probability of B_i.
Now, this formula here is indeed the general law of total probability.
And how we can apply we will see in the next example.
Actually this is one of the most famous examples of probability theory.
It's the so called Monty Hall problem.
and because it is so well known, i don't want to go into the whole history and the details.
We just use it to compute a probability with the 2 laws above.
However i still have to explain how this whole puzzle works.
So we have a game show with 3 doors, where there is one door with a car behind and 2 doors with a goat behind.
and now lets assume that the car would be the better price to win.
Ok then the game works in 3 steps.
First you pick a door. Lets say you pick door 1.
Afterwards in the second step the showmaster always shows you a goat.
So he opens one of the 2 remaining doors.
and maybe lets say here he opens door 3.
and then in the last step you have to do your final pick.
So you can either keep the original door or you can switch.
and now i can already tell you, switching has the higher probability to getting the car.
Therefore if you want the goat you should stay at the original door.
However no matter what you want, we can calculate the probabilities now.
Here please note, the names for the doors are arbitrary.
Therefore we can just assume that we pick door 1 at the beginning and then door 3 is opened by the showmaster.
Moreover we need some names for the events we consider here.
Here c_j should be the event that the car is behind door j.
In addition s_j should be event that in the second step the showmaster opens door j.
Hence we already know some conditional probabilities.
Namely the probability of s_3 under the condition c_3 has to be 0.
The showmaster will never show you the car in the second step.
He always opens a door with a goat.
Therefore we also now the probability of s_3 under the condition c_2.
Because this is what i told you, he opens one of the 2 remaining doors.
Never the door you picked.
So in this scenario here, he does not have a choice.
Hence the conditional probability here is 1.
Then the last remaining case would be where he has a choice. Therefore we say the probability is 1/2.
So you see, just by knowing the problem we already get a lot of information.
And please also note, here we didn't define a sample space, sigma algebra or even a probability measure yet.
Simply because we don't need it. We just want to know what happens in any probability space, when we have these conditional probabilities.
Indeed this will be our last step here.
So we want to know: what is the probability of getting the car when i switch the door in the third step.
And this is exactly given by this conditional probability.
Now, maybe not so surprising now we can apply Bayes's theorem here.
Please recall what it tells us.
We can exchange the order in the conditional probability here, when multiply with the probability of the last part.
However we don't have it on the left hand side. Therefore we have to divide here by the probability of s_3.
Therefore often you see Bayes's theorem in this formulation.
Ok, now here on the right hand side we have a problem, because we don't know what P(s_3) is.
However we have all the conditional probabilities here. Therefore we can use the law of total probability.
Hence in the denominator we get a sum with 3 parts.
Namely we sum over P(s_3|c_j) times the probability of c_j.
and there we can put in our conditional probabilities.
Ok then lets start in the numerator. This probability here is 1.
and the same we find here in the denominator as well.
Then on the right hand side we find a conditional probability that is 0.
and then the last remaining one on the left is 1/2.
Ok now you see the last ingredient we need would be the probability of c_2 and c_1.
and there of course we have the assumption that it's the same probability.
So we assume fair game. Each door has the same probability for getting the price.
and by having 3 doors this would mean we have the probability 1/3.
Ok, now we have substituted everything with numbers, such that we can simply compute.
and we get out 2/3.
So indeed we get out the result that in this scenario switching is beneficial.
However of course the goal here was not winning a car, but rather seeing the application of Bayes's theorem and law of total probability.
Ok with this i think it's good enough for today and i hope i see you in the next video. Have a nice day and Bye! :)