Hello and welcome back to
probability theory
and as always, first, I want
to thank all the nice people
that support this channel
on Steady or PayPal.
And today in part 11, we
will talk about the distribution
of a random variable.
So therefore, please first
recall, a random variable
acts between two event spaces.
It's given as a map capital
X from Omega to
Omega tilde
and in fact, the most important
random variables occur,
when Omega tilde is given
as the real number line R
and then a useful choice
for the Sigma algebra is
given by the Borel Sigma
algebra.
OK.
Now, these are the random
variables we will talk about
today.
The overall idea for today
is that on the one hand,
you have to think of an abstract
probability space given by
Omega
and on the other hand, we
have a very concrete probability
space given by the real number
line.
I said probability spaces,
because this is what we will
have in the end.
But of course, first, we
will start just with event
spaces.
So most importantly, a probability
measure on the right-hand
side is still missing.
Now corresponding to the
two event spaces
I would say we have a random
variable we call capital
X.
From the last video, you
already know this map has
one property we call
measurable
and soon you will see why
we really need that.
However, first, I would say
let's add a probability measure
on the left-hand side.
So we have an abstract probability
measure P defined on the
Sigma algebra A.
However, now we are not
interested in abstract
calculations here on the
left-hand side, because our
whole problem is given with
this random variable X.
So we would rather like to
calculate here on the right-
hand side with real
numbers.
Hence, what we want to add
is a probability measure
for the real number line
for the Borel Sigma algebra.
So we introduce a new probability
measure and since it corresponds
to the random viable X, we
call it P_X.
Of course, this is a nice
picture you really should
always have in mind, but
it does not tell us what
the definition of P_X
is.
Therefore, let's do this
in a definition.
Here
we will explain what we mean
when we say distribution
of a random variable X
and in fact, this is a very
general definition.
It works for any probability
space given by a set
Omega, a Sigma algebra A,
and the probability measure
P
and the only other thing
we need is a random variable
X from Omega into
R. Of course, as
before the Sigma algebra,
we choose for the real number
line is the Borel Sigma
algebra.
So you see the whole assumptions
fit with this picture here.
Therefore, in the next step,
we can define the map
P_X.
Which should have the Borel
Sigma algebra as its
domain.
And because it should be
a probability measure
in the end, we can say it
maps into
[0,1].
Now to define the map, let's
take any Borel set B
and write P_X of
B is equal to
P, the abstract
P, of
the preimage of
B under X.
So you see this is a very
natural construction when
we have any set here and
want to measure it, we pull
it back to the original space
here and measure it with
P.
And then this whole construction
defines a new measure here
on the right-hand side.
Now, as a reminder, you already
know there is another notation
for denoting the preimage
in probability theory.
One simply writes X
in B.
Hence, you could also see
this as a definition for
P_X.
OK.
Now this map P_X
is what we call the distribution
of the random variable X.
More concretely one would
say probability distribution
of X and
sometimes you also see the
long name probability
distribution measure of X.
It all means the same.
Namely this map
P_X.
However, of course, the important
part here is, this actually
defines a probability measure
on R.
So let's put that into a
proposition. So
you see this is a good point
to refresh your memory,
What we need for a probability
measure. Essentially, we
just have two properties,
where the actual hard one
is the so-called sigma
additivity.
Now, of course, in the proof
we can use, that we already
know that this P, the blue
one, is already a probability
measure.
And the other part we need
to use is that X is a random
variable.
So it's measurable.
OK.
Then I would say let's start
with a simple fact
Namely that the preimage
of the whole set on the right,
is the whole set on the left-
hand side.
So this is simply Omega
and of course, this holds
for every map from Omega
into R.
And with this fact, we can
calculate P_X of
R. By definition
it's simply P of the pre-
image of R, which is
Omega.
So we have P of Omega
which is one, because P
is a probability measure.
So you see this was not
complicated at all
and now we can do exactly
the same for the empty set.
Not so surprising.
The preimage of the empty
set is always the empty
set.
OK.
Then I would say let's shorten
the whole calculation, because
it works the same as above.
In the end, we get P of the
empty set, which is zero
by the definition of a probability
measure.
OK.
And with this, we have already
proven half of the things
we need for having a probability
measure.
Hence, only the Sigma
additivity remains to show.
In order to prove this, we
need to choose countable
many Borel sets.
So B_1 B_2 and so
on, and you know they
should be pairwise disjoint.
So the intersection with
any two sets is always
the empty set.
Now, the good thing we have
is that this stays also
true for the preimages.
Again, this is a fact that
holds for any map from
Omega into R,
because the preimage has
the general property that
it is stable under
intersections.
In other words, we can pull
in the intersection here.
And now by assumption B_i
and B_j are disjoint,
this is the empty set
and then we have the same
as before. The preimage
of the empty set is the
empty set.
Hence the conclusion here
is, these countable many
preimages are also
pairwise disjoint.
Of course, this is a very
nice fact, but we should not
forget that by the definition
of a random variable, these
preimages lie in the
sigma algebra A
and this is needed when we
want to use the Sigma additivity
for the original probability
measure P
and of course, this is exactly
what we want to do now.
So what we should write down
is P_X of the
infinite union of
B_J.
Then in the next step as
before we use the definition
of P_X.
So now we have P
of the preimage of the infinite
union.
Hence, what we want to use
here is again a general
fact for preimages.
In particular, I can tell
you the preimage is stable
under any unions.
In other words, we are allowed
to pull out the union here
and there you see we have
what we want. A union of
pairwise disjoint sets
inside P.
Hence, finally, we use the
Sigma additivity for P.
So the whole thing is the
infinite sum of P
of the preimage of B_J
under X.
Which we can translate back
to P_X.
This results in the infinite
sum of P_X
(B_J)
and there you see this is
exactly what we wanted to
prove.
We have the Sigma additivity for
P_X and also the two
other rules here, such that
we get a probability measure.
So please keep that fact
in mind. The distribution
of a random variable is
always a probability measure.
And this is exactly what
we wanted at the beginning.
Now, before we talk about
examples, I first have to
tell you about an important
notation,
Namely, if we have a probability
measure which we could call
P tilde on the real number
line
and now we find out that
the probability distribution
of X, P_X, is
exactly equal to this P
tilde,
then in this case, we
write X tilde ~
P tilde.
Moreover, we read it as
X is distributed as
P tilde. Here
please keep in mind, P tilde
could be any probability
measure. I call it P
tilde simply to avoid any
danger of confusion with
the blue P, which is defined
for Omega.
However, here P_X and P
tilde are probability measures
for the real number line.
OK.
Now the last part of the
video will be a nice
example.
Let's take a very a common
one.
The flip of a coin.
Here, the probability for
getting heads should be lower
case p
and now our probability space
should represent n tosses
of the same coin here
with order. OK?
So you see this probability
space is not complicated
at all.
The set Omega is given as
the set  to the
power n, where
one should represent heads
and zero tails
and then the Sigma algebra
is just the power set of
Omega.
Hence, the only question
remains, what is the probability
measure P here?
Indeed, it has a name, it's
called the Bernoulli distribution
with parameters n and
p.
Indeed the probability mass
function you can immediately
write down.
It's not complicated at all.
We have factors p and
1 minus p where p
comes in for heads and 1
minus p for tails.
Hence, the power of p is
the number of ones in Omega
and the power of 1 minus
p is the number of zeros
in Omega.
OK.
Now, this probability space
here, you should see as our
abstract one on the left-
hand side and the right-
hand side, we only get when
we define a random variable
X and this
one should be defined as
counting the number of heads.
So without order.
In other words, when we use
numbers, X of Omega
should be defined as the
number of ones in
Omega.
Now, if you want, you can
rewatch part four where
we already explained this
random experiment here.
Then it might not surprise
you that the distribution
of X is given by the
binomial distribution.
Indeed, if you do the explicit
calculation for P_X,
you see this
coincides with the
explanations we gave in part
four.
Hence, here you see this
is a good example, where the
actual random experiment
we are interested in is
hidden in a random variable
and you will see, this will
happen a lot in future.
OK.
Then in the next videos,
we will continue our journey
in probability theory.
Therefore, I hope I see you
there and have a nice day.
Bye.