Hello and welcome back to
probability theory.
And as you already know,
first, I want to thank all
the nice people that support
this channel on study or
paypal.
Now, in today's part 12,
we will talk about the important
cumulative distribution
function.
So here you already see this
is such a long word that
often one just speaks of
the CDF
.
Now, soon we will see that
every random variable has
such a CDF.
For this, please recall
that a random variable just
translates from an abstract
probability space into a
very concrete one given in
the real number line.
In particular, this could
be a discrete probability
space where only some
values in R are relevant
for the probability measure
PX.
In other words, you can easily
embed a discrete set of
numbers into R.
This means that if you think
of both cases we had so the
discrete one and the absolutely
continuous one both are
included here.
This helps because then the
notion of a CDF is
exactly the same in both
cases.
Therefore, I would say let's
define this cumulative
distribution function.
Here.
I can already tell you we
will always denote it with
capital F where in the
index we put in the
random variable X.
And indeed, often we will
plot the function on the
whole real number line.
A typical graph could look
like this.
So it's always increasing.
However, it's also
possible that it stays
constant.
Therefore, the first warning
here, you should never confuse
this with a probability
density function.
A PDF.
OK.
I think that was enough talking
here.
Let's go to the definition.
Now, the assumptions
are the same as in the last
video.
So we have omega A P as a
probability space and
X as a random variable.
It's not an abstract random
variable but a real valued
one implicitly.
This means we have the Borel
Sigma algebra for
R.
Now, in fact, this is all
we need and now we can
define the function
FX.
It's important to remember
here that the domain for
F of X is always the
whole real number line
and the possible values lie
in the unit interval.
So what you can keep in mind
is the co domain of X
is the domain of FX.
OK.
Now, as you can see in the
unit interval FX
is defined as a probability,
namely putting in a lower
case X into the function
is defined as
the probability of the
interval minus
infinity to X.
And it's measured with
PX, the distribution,
the probability distribution
of the random variable X.
And with this, you see that's
the reason it's called cumulative
distribution function.
So we include here all possible.
values until we reach the
given point X
and here, maybe it's helpful
as a reminder that this can
be written with the original
probability measure P.
So we have P of the
random variable capital X
is less or equal than the
lower case X.
And we have learned this
is exactly the same thing
as this.
OK.
Then this nice well defined
function FX is called the
cumulative distribution
function of the random variable
capital X.
Indeed some people simply
call it distribution function
of X.
Or in short, as I already
told you, we just call it
the CDF of X.
Now, this definition
immediately applies some
nice characteristic properties
for FX.
Therefore, let's use a minute
to talk about these.
They immediately follow because
we use a probability measure
to define F of X.
For example, if we make this
lowercase X here smaller
and smaller in the limit
X to minus infinity,
we would get PX of
the empty set.
And then we have our important
property of a probability
measure.
The empty set is always
sent to zero.
Hence FX has
this property in the limit
to minus infinity.
Therefore, in the same way,
we can ask what happens when
X goes to plus infinity
there, it's also not hard
to see when X
increases.
We include more and more
in this probability measure.
Hence, in the limit we get
here the whole real number
line.
So we have PX of R
and this is the next important
property of a probability
measure.
The whole sample space is
always sent to one.
OK.
So it's not hard to see that
we have these two limits
for FX.
Moreover, we also see
immediately that the function
FX is monotonically
increasing.
Here.
Please recall.
This means if we go from
one point X one to a larger
point X two, the
value of the function
increases or it stays the
same.
This follows because the
probability measure is
always monotonic.
This means if we measure
a set with the probability
measure, then all subsets
of the set have a smaller
measure all the same.
So you see also this
property is not hard to
understand.
However, now the third and
the last property here is
a little bit more technical.
I say this because it tells
us that FX is right
continuous.
This means that in general
it's not a continuous function
but it is continuous.
If you just look from the
right hand side, this
means we have to look at
the right limit here where
X is always larger than the
point X zero.
And then right continuity
means that this limit is
always FX at the
point X zero.
And this is the property
we have for the CDF
FX.
Now the meaning of this in
the graph, you can see a
buff at each
jump point as this one.
The field in circle has to
lie at the upper part on
the right.
OK.
I don't want to prove the
fact here, but you should
see the reason for it.
We include X here in
this interval.
And the jump in the graph
would mean that the singleton
just with the point X has
a non zero probability.
And this non zero
probability is then
included in the whole
probability here.
OK.
Then I think we can look
at an example.
In fact, this will be one
of the most important examples
we have, we take the
random variable X which should
have the distribution given
by the normal distribution.
If you have already heard
of the normal distribution,
then you know it has two
parameters.
And the simplest case would
be that we set the mean to
be zero and the standard
deviation to be one.
If you have never seen this,
this is not a problem because
now we discuss it,
it's an absolutely continuous
case, which means the whole
probability measure is given
by a probability density
function.
And indeed, this one is
given by the famous bell
curve.
It's not just any bell
curve, it's given by the
Gaussian function,
which means it's given by
E to the power minus
one half X
squared.
And the correct normalization
in font would be given by
one divided by the square
root of two times pi
Now, in general, in the case,
when we have the probability
density function, the
PDF, we can easily
calculate the CD F.
In fact, the only thing we
have to do is to integrate
over the PDF,
which means we go from minus
infinity to the point
X.
And then we only have to
put in the PDF where the
constant is written in front
of the integral.
However, here, because X
is already chosen as available,
we need another one.
So let's choose T
now, for the normal distribution,
we can simplify this
integral immediately.
But of course, we can draw
a graph.
So we would start with minus
infinity, then we would increase
and increase.
And in the end in the limit,
we would go to
+11 important
property you see here is
because the PDF is
symmetric, we will hit
one half here.
OK.
Because my drawing here is
not perfect at all.
I would suggest that we now
go into our
studio
here.
The first thing we should
check is the health function.
So what is the normal
distribution in R?
Indeed here, you see we have
everything.
So the whole explanation
what the normal distribution
is.
Most importantly, we see
the probability density
function is here given
with the norm.
On the other hand, the CD
F, the distribution
function is given by
P norm.
And the last one here, Ar
nom will just give us a
sample with respect to the
normal distribution.
Of course, in addition, you
also get a lot of explanations
here.
Most importantly, you
see the definition
of the probability density
function is also given
here.
However, you see the parameter
sigma and the parameter
mu are included here.
Nevertheless, the default
values are the same as we
have chosen.
OK.
Then I would say we can play
around and plot the CD
F and the PDF.
Now for plotting, we need
a whole sequence.
So let's set X to the
sequence where we start
maybe with minus 10
and go to plus 10 with
step size
0.01
let's hit enter.
And then we see the result
here.
Indeed, we recognize that
we have 2001
points.
Then in the next step, we
can put all these points
into the density function
which was given by the
norm.
OK.
So here you see the best
thing would be to enlarge
the whole picture.
Now, in this picture, we
recognize our bell curve.
However, maybe it's better
to not just plot the
values but also the
points X.
So we put in X
comma the norm of X
and there you see, we have
our peak exactly at the point
X is equal to zero.
OK.
Then I would say in the same
way we can plot this CD
F.
So we take X
comma P norm
of X.
So here you see this is like
our picture from before,
but now from minus 10 to
plus 10.
Hence, you can see in the
limits we go from zero
to plus one.
Now I would suggest that
you play around with all
these functions to get a
good visualization for the
PDF and for the
CDF.
OK.
Now, at the end of the video,
we can also look at the function
are norm
and if we put in a number,
we get as many samples as
we want.
So in this case, we took
10 but of course, we could
also take 6000 for
example.
So showing all of them is
not so exciting, but
maybe a histogram is.
So let's put in histogram
of rnorm
6000.
And here again, we
recognize some bell
curve.
So maybe we can just repeat
the whole thing again.
And as you can see, we don't
change so much.
However, maybe we can
also increase the number
in another video, I already
showed you how you can make
a histogram a little bit
nicer and maybe
this is something you should
do here as well.
OK.
Now, I think that's good
enough for this video.
I really hope you now know
what a normal distribution
is and also what a
general CDF is.
Of course, all questions
you can put into the comments
and then I hope I see you
in the next video.
Bye.