Hello and welcome back to probability theory.
We've already reached part 18 in the series and we are still talking about the variance and the standard deviation.
More precisely today we will prove some important formulas that hold for independent random variables.
However before we start with this, a big thank you to all my supporters on Steady.
You can also support this channel via PayPal or by other means, mentioned in the description
and as a supporter, you have access to PDF versions and quizzes for all the videos.
Ok, then let's start with the topic of today.
Let's talk about some properties of the variance and the standard deviation
and as I said before, we will formulate this for 2 independent random variables X and Y.
Moreover we already know from the last videos, that the variance is only well defined,
if the integral of the random variables squared exists
or in other words the expectation of X squared has to be a finite number
and of course the same we also need for the random variable Y.
Which means the expectation of Y squared has to be a finite number as well.
OK, with this we now know the variance and the standard deviation of X and Y exist.
So all of these are well defined real numbers.
However, now we are also able to say something about the sum of the 2 random variables.
More concretely we can now calculate the variance of X + Y
and maybe it's not a big surprise for you. In this case the variance is indeed additive.
This means we can simply pull out the plus sign here.
However here please don't forget, it's important that the two random variables here are independent.
OK, so this is the addition and now you might ask: what happens when we scale a random variable?
So the question is what is the variance of Lambda times X, where Lambda is a real number
and in fact, we can pull out this Lambda factor, but with a square.
So we can simplify our variance here, but we shouldn't forget this square outside.
OK, now you might have the idea, that we should formulate the second rule here for the standard deviation as well,
because there the square should vanish in the definition.
There please recall, the standard deviation Sigma of Lambda times X, is simply the square root of the variance.
This means indeed here on the right-hand side the square of Lambda vanishes,
but now we have the absolute value there.
This makes sense, because the standard deviation has to be always positive.
Hence also here you should remember, you can pull out a scalar from the standard deviation,
but then you should forget about the minus signs.
In other words if you just look at positive number, this is a homogeneous property.
Now, I would say all the 3 rules here, you should remember, because you can use them in calculations.
However, of course first we should prove them.
Indeed this is not a hard proof,
because we can immediately use the formula we have for the variance given by the expectations.
This means the variance of X + Y is given by the difference of two expectations.
Please recall in the first one we have the square inside the expectation and in the second one outside
and now the good thing we can use here is, that the properties of the expectation, we have already discussed in part 15.
In particular we know the expectation is linear and of course this should be something that can help us here.
However first here, let's expand the square inside the expectation.
So this is X squared + 2 times X times Y + Y squared.
So not so complicated and in the next step we can use the linearity here.
Moreover here on the right-hand side, we can use the linearity immediately.
So we have the expectation of X + the expectation of Y and still we have to square the whole thing.
Ok, then in the next step let's use the linearity of the expectation here in the first part.
So we can pull out the additions and the scalars.
Hence first we have expectation of X squared + 2 times the expectation of X times Y + the expectation of Y squared.
Ok, then on the other hand here the second part we can expand the square as well.
So this means first we have the expectation of X squared,
then minus 2 times the expectation of X times the expectation of Y and finally we have this squared expectation of Y.
Ok at this point you should see, we can already put this term together with this term to get the variance of X
and in the same sense this expectation here and that expectation there gives us the variance of Y.
So you see we have already reached what we want here on the right-hand side.
Therefore the only question is what is with the 2 remaining terms here?
So maybe first to answer this let's put them together.
So it's two times then the expectation of X times Y minus the expectation of X times the expectation of Y.
So at this point we know this whole term should be 0
and indeed there the independence of the 2 random variables X and Y comes in,
because if they are independent, then this expectation here is just the product of 2 expectations.
That's also something we have stated in part 15.
So the conclusion here is, the whole term inside the parentheses here is 0 and this finishes the proof of part (a).
So now let's go to part (b). In fact, part (b) is much easier, because only one random variable is involved here,
but again we can use the formula with the expectations for the variance.
So first we have the expectation, where the random variables is squared and then we square the expectation
and now you should see in both terms we can pull out a Lambda squared.
Again simply by using the linearity of the expectation.
Ok and then the only thing we have to do now is to factor out the Lambda squared,
because then only the difference of the two expectations remains
and we have used this formula so often now, that you immediately see this is the variance of X.
In other words we have proven part (b) and also not a surprise at all from part (b), we now can derive part (c).
Essentially part (c) was the same thing, but now for the standard deviation instead of the variance.
Hence the only thing we have to do here, is to take the square root of the variance
and then by using part (b), we see we have the square root of Lambda squared
and indeed this is simply now the absolute value of Lambda
and the other factor is just this square root of the variance of X, which is the standard deviation of X.
Ok and with this you see the whole proof is finished.
So as I said please remember all these properties, all the formulas here, because you can use them in calculations
and indeed how to do that, we will see in the next videos.
Therefore I really hope that I see you there and have a nice day. Bye!