Hello and welcome back to Probability
Theory the video course where we learn
how to calculate in probability
spaces. And in today's part 26 we will
talk about two famous inequalities named
after Markov and
Chebyshev. Both can be used in applications
because they hold in a general setting.
However before we start stating these
inequalities, I first want to thank all
the nice people who support the channel
on Steady, here on YouTube, or via other
means and please don't forget supporting
me gives you benefits: so for example you
can download additional material with
the link in the
description. Okay then let's start
formulating these two inequalities for
probability space so we have a sample
space Omega a sigma algebra a and a
probability measure
P and there I can already tell you the
power of maros inequality and chabby
chf's inqu quality lies in the fact that
they are valid in any probability space
and as we will see now they are also not
hard to prove at all so let's start with
the first one here let's start with
markov's
inequality this one holds for any random
variable defined on the probability
space this means we consider a map X
from Omega into R so as always we
consider real Valu random
variables however what we actually need
for maros inequality is a non- negative
random variable therefore what we do is
to go through the absolute value of x
because this one now has non- negative
values and it satisfies what we call
markov's
inequality and in short this one just
Compares a probability with the
expectation more precisely we look at
the probability that the absolute value
of x is greater or equal than a given
Epsilon so this is the given event which
we can measure with our probability
measure and the probability that comes
out is less or equal than an
expectation indeed we can write
expectation of the random variable
absolute value of x to the power p and
then we divide that by Epsilon to the
power p as well so this is Mark of
inequality and it holds no matter which
positive Epsilon or P we choose in this
sense it's very flexible and in
particular it also holds for p is equal
to 1 and exactly this case we can
immediately visualize this is not
complicated at all let's sketch a graph
for our random variable X or as you
already know we actually want to have
the non- negative random variable
absolute value of x hence here the
x-axis just represents the whole sample
space
Omega and then the values of X just give
us a graph in this picture and now what
we can do is just fix an Epsilon here on
the Y AIS and then we immediately
recognize the samples where the absolute
value of x is greater or equal than
Epsilon more precisely we just find them
here and there so in the picture we can
just project them back to the sample
space Omega hence the subset in Omega we
want to measure is this one combined
with that one in other words by
measuring that with our probability
measure P we already have the left hand
side here and now if you multiply this
by the value Epsilon we get out the two
rectangles here so you can say what we
have is these two areas added
however on the other hand you know that
the expectation of a random variable is
given by the whole integral hence
obviously the area given by the whole
integral is bigger than just the two
rectangles here or in general we
immediately have the inequality with
less or equal here so it's easy to see
and this is the whole Mark of inequality
for the case p is equal to 1 and in fact
this idea here already covers the whole
proof the only thing we have to do now
is to extend it to any P this means here
in the picture instead of the absolute
value of x we consider the absolute
value of x to the^ P this does not
change so much because the set we
calculate here is the same for any P so
if we have a lowercase Omega which
satisfies the one inequality it also
satisfies the other one simply because
the power of p is a monotonically
increasing function therefore the
measured probability here is also
exactly the same and now as before we
want to multiply the whole thing by the
value we have but now the value is
Epsilon to the power P so let's simply
put Epsilon to the power P to both sides
and now here on the right hand side we
can do exactly the same estimate as
before in the picture but maybe as an
explanation we can put in one more step
in between namely we introduce the
indicator function this one you know we
write it with a bolt one where in the
index we find the corresponding set and
here we have the set where X to^ P is
greater or equal than Epsilon to the^ p
and for this indicator function we can
calculate the
expectation which is exactly the
probability here on on the left hand
side so we still have equalities here
and in the next step we can pull in the
factor Epsilon to the power P which
means now we have an expectation of a
step function and there you can look
back to the picture where we exactly
have this function there so the graph
has a line here and there and otherwise
it's at zero however the crucial part
here is that the whole graph of the
function lies below the graph of the
function X to the^ P hence the
monotonicity of the integral or the
expectation tells us that we have the
inequality so in the calculation here we
get that we have less or equal than the
expectation of the absolute value of x
to the power p and now if you compare
this to the left hand side you see that
we have proven Mark of's
inequality so you see that was very
quick and the whole idea was in the
picture above in other words what we see
it's a very rough estimate in general
but we can use it whenever we want and
the first application we have is to use
it to prove the famous chabby chfs
inequality this one can be used to
estimate How likely it is to be off from
the expectation of a given random
variable and again the power of this
lies in the general setting you can use
this estimate for any random variable
where the expectation is defined
therefore this is the only assumption we
have here we have a chosen random
variable X and there we want that e of X
exists or as you know you can formulate
that that the expectation of the
absolute value of x is finite indeed
here we need an expectation for the
random variable X because otherwise the
formulation would not make sense and as
already said in the formulation we look
at the set where we deviate from the
expectation of X more precisely we want
to see how likely it is to be off by a
given Epsilon in other words these are
the points in the sample space Omega
where we are not in an Epsilon
neighborhood of the expectation for the
values of X and exactly this Subspace in
Omega we can measure with the
probability measure and now the variance
of the the random variable X gives us an
upper Bound for this
probability more concretely we have the
variance of x / Epsilon s moreover you
immediately see that this inequality is
only useful if the variance of X is also
a finite number but if we have that then
the variance here gives a nice estimate
for the probability that a random
variable deviates from its mean and
indeed it does not matter which Epsilon
greater than zero you choose here okay
now with the statement in mind I would
say we can try to write down a proof for
it and there what we can immediately do
to simplify the whole thing is to
consider a random variable where the
expectation is zero so in other words we
just consider X tilder which is given as
x minus the expectation this is really
helpful because it means that the
variance of XA is just given as the
expectation of X squ so here you see we
need the formulas we have for
calculating
variances in particular you should see
that the variance of X and xti are
exactly the same this is simply because
the variance as a function is additive
and the variance of a constant is always
zero okay so this is the whole idea to
simplify the inequality and now we can
write it down so the left hand side here
is already very simple because we just
have the probability where absolute
value of xtia is involved but there you
should immediately see that this looks
exactly like the statement in Markos
inequality and since we have the power
of two here involved in the variance we
should use Markos inequality for p is
equal to 2 and there you see this is the
reason why we have formulated Markos
inequality for all values P okay and now
on the right hand side here you see we
get a fraction where we have the
expectation of x to the S and Epsilon
squared in the denominator and now
please note for the square it does not
matter if we have the absolute value or
not in other words what we have in the
numerator here is just the variance of
our random varable X so exactly what
chabby chf's inequality
stated therefore the proof here is
already finished so our general result
here is that we have two inequalities
which hold in a very general context
this means you can use this estimate
here for a lot of probability
distributions therefore we can use it
for proofs in general statements but
also in applications
and I would say we first should look at
some concrete examples so let's do that
with the next video so really hope we
meet there again and have a nice day
[Music]
bye-bye come to the bright side of my