Hello and welcome back to a new video.
And as always I want to thank all the nice
people that support this channel on steady.
The topic for today is functional analysis
because this is the one most of you voted for.
Therefore now I have a whole serious planned to
get into the real interesting stuff concerning
functional analysis. What you should know is
that functional analysis is a really wide field.
However to get an idea what it is about
you can just look at these two blocks.
On the one side you have the linear algebra and
on the other side you have the real or complex
analysis. In a rough sense if you look at infinite
dimensional spaces in the linear algebra sense,
and if you want to apply some analysis for these
spaces, then you are on the realm of functional
analysis. Of course there's much more to it but
if you have some knowledge in linear algebra and
analysis now you know what to expect. For example
here we consider spaces consisting of functions
or of sequences and of course also
linear maps between such spaces.
Because in this field we always combine
algebraic structures with analytic properties,
one often summarizes functional analysis just by
saying: it's the study of topological algebraic
structures. Don't worry what this exactly means
we will clear up in the next videos. However what
you should see here is that topology plays a role
here and indeed it's not a bad idea to start with
topology when dealing with functional analysis.
However that's not what I want to do here
because I want to start with something that
is closer to a normal analysis course. And
that is the structure we call a metric space. A
so-called metric space is not at all complicated:
we start with a set X and we visualize that as a
collection of points. For example, in the set X
we have a lowercase point x, so just an element
in our set and another element we can call y.
If we just consider a set, we can't say
anything about these points other than:
they are equal or not. So there are different
points but we don't know anything more than that.
Now this is what we now want to
change: we want to give the set
X more structure. In this case, we want to know
what the distance between two chosen points is.
Now if we want such a distance then of course
it should fulfill some reasonable properties.
For example, if we choose two distinct points,
then the distance should be always positive.
Of course the distance could also be zero but
only in the case when x and y are the same point.
In order to formalize that, we have to write down
a map. This map is called a metric and it measures
distances and now it gets two points, so it lives
on the Cartesian product of X with X. And it
maps into the non-negative real numbers, so zero
infinity, where zero is included. Now such a map
we call a metric if it fulfills three properties.
And the first one we already know. If the distance
between two points is exactly zero, then this
is only if and only the case if x is equal to y.
The second property is also very descriptive.
So if we look again at two points x and y.
And now we measure the distance from x to y. And
of course this should be the same as starting by y
and going to x. So the distance from y to x
should be the same as the distance from x to y.
This means for the map it is symmetric: it does
not matter which is the first and which is the
second element. You get the same result. And now
the last property is very important it is called
the triangle inequality. The name already tells
you now we consider three points instead of two,
so there's a point z. Now we have a distance from
x to z, and also distance from z to y. Now the
triangle inequality tells you if you go a detour,
then your distance gets longer. In other words if
you add the gray length, then it gets longer than
the blue line here. In a formal way this means:
d(x, y), the blue line, is less or equal
than distance x to z plus distance z to y.
Now with such a map, we can now
measure all the distances in the set X.
Therefore we call the set X with the metric
d a metric space. And you already know
if we can measure distances, we can do a lot of
analytical stuff. And this is what we will do
in the next videos. So please use the comments
to tell me what you want to see in a functional
analysis course. So thanks for listening and
hopefully, I see you in the next videos. Bye!
you