Hello and welcome back to
functional analysis.
First, big thanks to all
the nice people who support
my channel on Steady or
Paypal.
Now, this is part two of
the series, and today we
go deeper into the topic
of metric spaces.
We've already learned if
we have a set X and a
metric for this set, then
we call this a metric
space.
In a metric space, one can
now generalize a lot of
notions you may know from
a real analysis course.
For example, we can define
sequences, limits,
accumulation points, and
so on.
Of course, this is what we
will use a lot in this series.
However, before we do that,
let's talk about some
examples.
So let's start with a simple
one, which is also one of
the most important ones.
The set is just the complex
numbers, and the metric should
be the usual notion of
measuring distances in the
complex numbers, which means
its the absolute value where
we look at the difference
of both points.
Now, the visualization in
the complex plane gives us
indeed the normal geometry
we have in the plane.
If we pick two complex numbers,
x and y, we know we can
calculate the difference,
which is a new complex number.
And the length of this new
complex number is exactly
the distance we want.
Now, you know this normal
geometry we have for measuring
distances you can also do
in higher dimensions.
For example, if the set is
Rn, we would have a standard
metric we can choose, and
this is usually called the
Euclidean metric or the
euclidean distance.
And because you know Pythagora's
theorem, you also know the
definition of d.
It's just the first component
of x minus the first component
of y squared,
plus the second
component, and so
on and so on, until you reach
the last component, which
is xn minus
yn squared.
And then, of course, we need
the square root.
Okay, so this is the euclidean
metric, the common, but
only a possible choice of
a metric in Rn.
So please remember, for a
metric, we only need the
three properties.
It should be positive definite,
symmetric, and fulfill the
triangle inequality.
We already know that these
two fulfill the three properties.
So there are metrics on
Rn or C respectively.
So let's look at another
distance function we could
define for Rn.
This would be the
maximum,
and then we look at the difference
x one minus y
one, and use the normal
absolute value, or modulus
in r.
So let's write it down for
all components, which means
we want the maximum of
all these differences.
In fact, this is of course,
a metric as well.
It's not hard to check that
it fulfills our three properties.
And most of the time, only
the triangle inequality
needs some work.
However, we should first
visualize the whole thing,
maybe again in the plane.
So here we see two points,
x and y.
And what we now have to do
is calculate the distances
of the components here.
Now in blue we have the distance
in the first component and
in green in the second component.
And as you can see, the blue
one is bigger.
So the maximum is indeed
this number here,
which means using this
metric, this is exactly the
distance between x and y.
Or in other words, if you
choose a point z here, for
example, it has the same
distance from x than the
distance x to
y.
Of course this shouldn't
be so surprising.
Of course you could have
different points that have
the same distance from a
chosen point x.
In our Euclidean metric from
above or in a picture in
a complex plane, this would
be just a circle
around x.
However, with another metric,
such a thing we could call
a circle might look completely
different.
Okay,
So please keep that in mind
whenever we use circles to
visualize things.
For our last example here,
lets choose a more abstract
one, just any set
X which should not be the
empty set.
Then we define a metric
by distinguishing two
cases.
The first case is just X
is equal to y and the
second, of course x is not
equal to y.
By the first property of
the metric we already know
here we need a zero.
However, we are not allowed
to have a zero here, so we
can choose whatever we want.
And most of the time we just
choose one.
Ok, so let's check together
that this is indeed a metric.
As it happens very often
the first two properties
are not a problem at all.
Its positive definite by
our construction.
So no problem here.
The second property is the
symmetry.
And here you can see the
whole definition is symmetric.
So no problem here at all.
The third property is the
triangle inequality.
And this one I want to
write down in
order to show that we need
three points, so x,
y and z out of the set.
And then we look at the inequality.
This means that we go the
detour over the point z.
Or in other words, we add
the distances on the right.
Okay, so this is what we
have to show in general.
So let's first look at two
different cases.
Now the first case would
be x is equal to
y because then we know
the distance of x to y
is exactly zero.
Okay, so let's write that
here.
This is zero.
Okay.
But then we know this inequality
is correct because on the
right hand side we just have
the metric or the distances
and we already know they
are positive or zero.
In the worst case, this
means that the triangle
inequality in this first
case is satisfied
now, the second case of course,
should be the opposite.
So we have x is not equal
to y, which means the distance
is by definition exactly
one.
Now, because we know that
the only allowed distances
are zero or one, there
is nothing in between.
We know that xz or
zy have also
one or zero.
Or to put it in another way,
we know that
d(x,z)
or the other one.
So zy is
also exactly one.
At least one of them has
to be one, otherwise both
of them would be zero, which
means that z is equal to
x and z is equal to y.
But then this would be not
a second case.
However, this means now,
if we add both of these
distances, we will get
one.
Or in the worst case, when
both of them are one, we
get out two.
So we have the inequality.
So very good.
Also in the second case,
the triangle inequality is
fulfilled.
Well now, to close this example,
let's recall that this definition
defines a metric.
It works on any set, and
it's called the discrete
metric.
So you might try to visualize
this metric space.
It's a little bit strange
because there are no neighbors
around a given point, simply
because theres a fixed
distance from one point to
all the other ones.
This means that all the points
are isolated points.
Ok, so now we have a few
examples of metric spaces
we can work with.
And in the next video I will
talk about other objects
we find in metric spaces.
So thanks for listening and
I hope I see you in the next
video.
Bye.