Hello and welcome back to
functional analysis.
And as always, I want to
thank all the nice people
that support this channel
on Steady or PayPal.
We've reached part three
in our course, and today
we will talk about some important
notions in metric spaces.
Please recall a pair
consisting of a set X and
a metric d is called a
metric space.
We've already discussed that
if you fix a point x in a
metric space, you can look
at all the other points that
have the same distance from
this point x.
Seeing that in the common
geometry of the plane, this
would be a circle around
x.
Or in a three dimensional
space it would be a sphere.
Or you could call it a ball.
Now exactly, this notion
of a ball is what we want
to generalize.
For an abstract metric space,
we write B epsilon
x and call it the open
epsilon ball around
x.
It is defined as all the
points y in our metric
space X that fulfill
that
The distance from x to
y is less than
a given radius epsilon.
However, this means that
in the picture it's not the
red line, it's everything
inside.
Now please note that for
a given positive radius
epsilon and a fixed point
x from the metric space,
this epsilon ball is never
empty, because at least the
point x lies in this
set.
Using this definition of
an epsilon ball, we can now
talk about a lot of important
notions in a metric space.
The first one I want to show
you is about open
sets.
You may already know what
open means in Rn, but
now we define it for arbitrary
subsets of our metric
space X.
So let's take this subset
A and I will use this
symbol to denote a subset.
Now descriptively, openness
should mean that if you
are inside the set A, you
should never see the boundary
of the set.
In other words, if you fix
an arbitrary point x of the
set A, there should be enough
points in all directions
around this point that also
belong to the set A.
Of course, in order to describe
this we can use such an epsilon
ball.
We just have to choose positive
epsilon, but we can choose
it as small as we need it.
And if we can do that for
each point separately, then
we have an open set A.
Therefore, the definition
reads like set is called
open if for each point
we can find such an epsilon
ball.
Of course, for each x you
can choose another epsilon
if needed.
In the picture this would
mean if you get closer to
the boundary you need a smaller
epsilon, of course.
However, as long as you find
for each point such an epsilon,
we call the set open.
Don't worry, we have
consistency here.
The so called open balls
are also open with this
definition.
This is a simple exercise
you can do for yourself.
Now, with your knowledge
of open sets, you might also
want to know what close sets
are.
However, before we do that,
let's talk about so called
boundary points.
Let's take our arbitrary
subset A again, and now
we look in the picture maybe
at points around
here.
At the moment it's not important
if the point we have chosen
is an element of our set
a or not.
Of course, it's a point in
our whole metric space X.
The important thing is that
with these points we describe
something that we could call
the boundary of a.
And of course we use the
epsilon balls again for
this.
Now what you should see is
if we have an epsilon ball
around this point, then we
hit points that are in a
and we hit other points that
are not.
Of course, this clearly can
happen.
However, if it happens, no
matter how small we choose
the ball, then we are
clearly on a thing we could
call the boundary.
Then the definition reads
a point x from the whole
metric space.
X is called a boundary
point for a if
all open balls around
x contain points
from A and a complement of
A.
For the formula here we just
use the intersection and
say this one can't be
empty and also not the
one when you use the complement
of a.
There are some important
things I should point out
here.
First, a boundary point
can be inside a set A or
outside, and
secondly, the notion boundary
point makes only sense with
respect to a given subset
A.
There is a symbol to denote
all the boundary points which
is used very often.
Its this curved del in
front of A.
So we put all the points
x that are boundary points
for A into this set.
Now you can remember an open
set is exactly such a set
where all the boundary points
are outside of A.
When you see this, then you
immediately understand what
a closed set should be.
It should be a set where
all the boundary points belong
to this set.
Using the same formula.
This reads A is closed
if and only if A with the
union of the boundary is
A
again.
However, that's not what
one uses as the definition
for closed sets.
The definition is much simpler.
A subset A in X is now
called closed if the
complement in X, which
is AC, is
open.
This makes sense because
the boundary points of A
and a complement are exactly
the same.
And this just means that
all the boundary points belong
to A and not AC.
Now the last notion for today
will be the so called
closure.
The name already tells you
if you start with an arbitrary
subset A, what you want to
get out is a closed
subset.
How to get this?
You might already know, you
just add all the missing
boundary points, so you form
the union with the boundary.
And this is what we call
the closure of A, and
we denote that with A
overline.
Now please remember, this
always defines a closed set.
Indeed, it's the smallest
closed set that still contains
A. Okay, now
I would suggest that the
closure of this video is
an example.
It shouldn't be too complicated.
So let's choose a metric
space consisting of real
numbers.
X is now defined as all the
numbers between one and three,
where three is included and
all numbers larger than four.
And the metric is just defined
as the normal distance function
we have for real numbers.
Okay, let's start considering
some subsets of
X, and the first
one is the interval from
one to three, which is of
course a nice subset of
X.
My question for you is now,
is this also an open
set?
So this is how you should
visualize the set.
And now we look at each point
here and try to find an
epsilon ball around this
point.
Now you see, this is
possible for all x
that are in A, but not
three.
What you can do is just look
at the distance, what should
be the boundary here, left
and right, and choose the
minimal you have.
And if you want, you can
make that even smaller.
To get to the picture here,
maybe you divide by two,
and then the epsilon ball
around x is
indeed exactly
inside the set a.
However, if we want to have
an open set, we need this
property also for the
point 3
ok, so let's write down an
epsilon ball, maybe with
radius one.
These are all the points
y and x, where the distance
is less than one.
So let's write down that
as an interval.
We already know that the
interval two to three
fulfills this property
here.
And the question is now,
are there any other points
that have distance less than
one from three?
It can't be anything here
in this area because the
points are too far away from
three.
And also in this interval
we don't find any points
because the distance from
three to four is already
one, but four is not
included in
summary.
Indeed, these are all the
points we find in X.
However, this is a subset
of a.
So our conclusion is
indeed A is an open
set.
Okay, so this is an important
thing to get today.
The question openness makes
only sense if you know what
the surrounding universe,
the whole metric space X
is.
Otherwise you won't be able
to calculate the epsilon ball
in X itself.
In this case, the epsilon ball
around three
has only one side.
So it looks like this.
Now, what you can also show
is that the set A here
is also a closed set.
This is what you also should
immediately remember:
Openness and closedness are
not opposites.
Surely you can have both
at the same time.
But it can also happen that
a set is neither closed nor
open.
Okay, so let's do a last
example here.
So this is our set C, one
to two, where two is included.
And I want to calculate the
boundary of C.
So this is our drawing for
the set C.
And you can immediately see
that for all points below
two, you can do the same
thing as before here,
which means you get an epsilon
ball which is completely
inside the set C itself.
So it's not a boundary point.
Which means the only point
we have to consider now is
the .2 itself.
And then you see, immediately,
if we look at an epsilon ball
around two, we will hit
points here on the left and
also on the right.
Now there are points on the
right that's different from
the three before.
Hence our boundary is just
the, point 2 nothing
more.
And to conclude the whole
video, maybe we also write
down the closure of C.
And you see, it's C itself,
which means the set is
closed.
Okay, now I hope you understand
these notions now a little
better.
And in the next video I will
explain how we deal with
them when we use sequences.
So, thanks for listening
and see you next time.
Bye.