Hello and welcome back to functional analysis
and as always I want to thank all the nice people that support this channel on Steady or Paypal.
Today's part 4 is about sequences, limits and closed sets.
So you see, we're still building up the foundations we need for doing functional analysis.
Now, for metric spaces it turns out that one can use sequences to describe the properties of a metric space.
You might already know, a sequence is just an ordered sets of points inside the metric space X,
because we give the points names, we usually see a notation like this
or in short you just write x_n with n in N.
Of course in the formal way you would say, you just have a map from the natural numbers into the metric space X,
because we can measure distances in a metric space, we can also talk about convergent sequences.
A sequence x_n in a metric space (X,d), which means all the x_n come from a set X,
is called convergent if there is a limit point we call x tilde.
So what we want is that the members of the sequence get closer and closer to this limit point x tilde.
Of course we already know how to measure such closeness. We can just use an arbitrary epsilon-ball.
It should be centered at x tilde,
but then no matter how small we choose the epsilon, almost all the members of the sequence should be inside this ball.
More exactly this means we find an index such that members with a bigger index lie inside the epsilon-ball.
Formally this reads then: for all epsilon greater 0,
there exists an index capital N
such that all the other indices greater or equal this capital N
fulfill that the distance between x_n and our limit point x tilde is less than epsilon.
In this case we then write x_n tends to x tilde if n goes to infinity.
Alternatively we also use the limit notation. So we write limit n to infinity of x_n is equal to x tilde.
If you see such notations please remind yourself that these are always given with respect to a metric d
and of course we can use such notations,
because in a metric space there can only be at most one x tilde that fulfills all of these things here.
You can easily show that using the triangle inequality.
Later we will see a lot of examples of convergent sequences. Therefore I would say we start here proving another important fact.
Here we look again at a subset of the metric space X and we can say that this one is closed,
if and only if we can't leave the set from the inside by just using sequences.
More exactly this means that a limit such a sequence could have must lie in the set A.
This is fitting for our visualization, because closeness means that this boundary we see here already belongs to the set A.
Writing that down gives us then: for every convergent sequence a_n,
where a_n is just an element in capital A.
So it's a sequence inside A and usually one uses the sloppy notation writing it down as a subset of A.
The important part here is of course, we have a convergent sequence, but only in the sense of the definition.
So it's a convergent sequence in the space X. So it has a limit inside X.
However for the proposition we need more.
We need that the limit, that we know exists, is also an element of A.
Ok, so this is important because now we have a characterization for closed sets just by using sequences.
Ok, then let's do the proof, where we have to show 2 directions.
I want to start with the one from right to left, because we can just do the contraposition here.
Hence we have to assume that A is not closed.
Hence by definition the complement is not open.
Now please recall open means that for each point inside the set,
you find an epsilon-ball around this point, such that the whole ball is inside A^c in this case.
Not open then means that there is at least one x tilde where this is not the case.
So you find an x tilde here on the boundary such that you can use any epsilon-ball, but you always hit points in A.
Hence we conclude that we can construct a sequence a_n, where each a_n comes from one of these sets here,
where for example we set epsilon as 1 over n.
If we do that then we know that a_n converges to x tilde,
because we get closer and closer to x tilde if we increase the index n.
Ok, so this is our result.
We now have a sequence in A, which is convergent, but its limit is not in A.
Ok, so this was our proof by contraposition. Which means this implication is now finished.
So, let's do the other direction then, where I also want to use a contraposition.
Here we now assume that there is a convergent sequence in A where the limit is not in A
and as before I want to call this limit just x tilde.
So we have the same picture as here.
Now you know by the definition of the limit
you can use any epsilon-ball around x tilde, you will always hit points of the sequence.
So inside A
and this then means that A^c, the complement of A is not an open set.
However then by definition the set A itself is not a closed set
and as you can see this closes our proof here. The proposition is correct.
Maybe we also close the video here. In the next part we will talk about complete metric spaces
and there we will discuss some examples and you'll see why it is helpful to deal with sequences.
So, thanks for listening and hopefully I see you there. Bye!