Hello and welcome back to
functional analysis.
And as always, I want to
thank all the nice people
that support the channel
on Steady or PayPal.
Today's part five is about
Cauchy sequences and complete
metric spaces.
And as promised in the last
video, we start here with
an example.
Our metric space has as a
set the interval from 0
to 3 with the normal
metric for the real numbers.
Hence this is something you
already know.
What you also know is that
the subset 0 to 3, which
is the whole space, is a
closed set inside
this metric space.
For example, you could argue
that the complement which
is the empty set is clearly
open.
Or you can use the fact from
the last video where you
consider any convergence
sequence with members from
the subset. Being a
convergent sequence means
it has a limit which we call
x tilde
and of course, it has to
lie in X.
What we proved last time
was now; the set is closed,
if the limit is also in the
subset. Of course here you
see immediately that this
is true, because the subset
(0,3) is the whole space
X.
Now a question that often
arises with such an example
is the following.
what is about the sequence
1 over N?
Clearly this is a sequence
in X. First member is
1, next one is 1/2
and so on.
You see all the members are
positive, so they lie in
this interval and the
distance between two members
of the sequence.
So maybe let's call them
x_n, x_m.
This number gets
smaller and smaller when
x and m get larger and
larger.
So we could write it in this
way,
but the important thing is
that you see that you get
closer and closer to something
with the sequence.
However, still, it does
not converge.
For our example, this is
easy to see, because the
only possible limit this
sequence could have in the
real numbers would be the
number zero.
However, zero is not in
X, there is no number
zero in our universe
here.
In summary, we found a metric
space which owns a
sequence, which should
converge but there is no
point in the space, where
the sequence leads to.
Therefore, one could say
there is a hole in the space,
but we will say the space
is not complete.
So now we have to give a
formal definition for a
complete metric space.
First, for given metric space
(X, d) sequences
that fulfill this property
here are called cauchy
sequences.
More concretely
this means for all
epsilon greater than zero,
there exists an index capital
N in N, such
that for all indices
n, m greater than
this index N, we
have that the
distance between the members
x_n, x_m is arbitrarily
small, so less than epsilon.
So this is the actual meaning
of this limit before.
What you should be able to
show now is if you have a
convergent sequence, then
this thing is also fulfilled.
The Cauchy sequence is therefore
always a generalization of
a convergence sequence.
So you see there's no limit,
there's no x tilde in the
definition of a Cauchy sequence.
Hence, it would be much nicer
working with this definition
than working with the one
for the convergent sequences.
However, we already know
the problem. This does not
work in general.
Now the nice spaces where
this actually works, we call
complete.
Therefore, we say here all
Cauchy sequences converge.
In other words, something
like above can't happen then
and of course, you already
know how to fix the example
above.
We could change the set X
when we include zero and
three.
Then of course, now the
space is complete.
You might already see the
general result here, because
we consider metric spaces
coming from the real numbers
R with the same metric as
R.
Therefore, as long as the
set X is closed in
R, which means in a
metric space (R, d) in
this case, then what
we get out is a complete
metric space.
However, that is just because
we already knew that
(R,d) is a complete metric
space.
You might already feel that
this should work in general
and you are correct.
If you have a complete metric
space, you can form new
ones just by considering
the closed subsets with the
same metric.
However, that's something
we can prove later.
Let's first look at another
example.
Now we don't change the set.
We still consider the interval
0 to 3 where we exclude
zero and three.
But now we change the metric
and I want to choose the
discrete metric.
So this is what we defined
in part two as a discrete
metric.
Now my claim is this is
also a complete metric
space.
Indeed, that's not hard to
show we just choose an arbitrary
Cauchy sequence here.
Then we know this whole thing
here holds for all
epsilon so that I can just
take one and I want to
have epsilon as one half.
Then we know there is a
capital N such that
all indices that are
created than N fulfill this
one.
This means that the distance
between x_n and x_m is
less than epsilon or in other
words, less than one half.
However, now we see in the
definition of the metric
that less than one half is
only possible in the bottom
case.
Therefore, the distance is
indeed zero,
which again means that x_n
is the same as x_m.
So please note this works
for almost all indices here.
Only finitely many before
could be different.
Hence, it tells you that
the sequence is indeed constant
after the index N
OK, maybe let's look at the
graph where we have here
the indices and here the
space X. At
the beginning the sequence
is allowed to do something.
However, the value it reaches
with the index N is then
fixed for the entire time
of the sequence.
So you could say this is
quite a boring sequence because
it does not change anymore.
However, for such a sequence,
it's easy to show that it
is a convergence sequence
with the limit x tilde
as exactly this constant
in the end.
And now we have seen that
these are indeed the only
possible convergence sequences
in a discrete metric space.
And of course, we have also
shown that this one is indeed
a complete metric space.
OK.
Maybe that's good enough
for today.
In the next video, we will
look at some important complete
metric spaces.
So I hope I see you there
and goodbye.