hello and welcome back to functional analysis and
as always I want to thank all the nice people that
support the channel on Steady or PayPal today's
part 6 finally is about Banach spaces. We will
later see that a so-called Banach space is indeed
one of the most important objects in functional
analysis. In its core it's just a vector space but
with more analytical structure on it. In order to
understand such a Banach space we first have to
define what a norm is. For this, I will use the
letter F to denote a field of numbers. However here
it will always be the real or the complex numbers.
Of course, this makes our life easier because we
don't have to write down the definition two times.
Now we have a set X that also carries some
operations such that it is a vector space.
F Vector space always means that the scaling
of vectors is done with numbers form F. This
means if F is R you can scale with real numbers
and in the case that F is C you can scale even
with complex numbers. The usual visualization for
points in a vector space is given by arrows. It's
a good idea because you see the two operations
scaling and adding two vectors immediately.
However from the analytical point of view it would
be also nice to know how long such an arrow is.
Measuring such a length is what we
call in the abstract sense and norm.
The symbol one uses for a norm are just two
lines on the left and two lines on the right.
And because we are measuring a length, the only
possible values should be non-negative numbers.
This means that each Vector in X gets
a number which is positive or zero,
and this map we get we call a norm
if it fulfills three properties.
Since you already know metrics you might
easily guess some of the details here.
For example in (a) we find the positive definite
part which means if we have the length 0,
then this is equivalent for having the
zero vector, or in other words the zero
vector has length 0 (which makes sense)
but it's also the only one with length 0.
Now Part (b) explains what happens to the length
when we scale a vector. Scaling here means we
have a vector x and multiply it from the
left with a scalar so a number in F. In the
picture you always visualize that with the arrow
getting longer or smaller depending on Lambda.
Hence the norm has to satisfy this which means the
length gets also multiplied by this Factor Lambda.
However Lambda could be a negative number or
even a complex one such that this only makes
sense if we consider the absolute value of Lambda.
Now depending what F is, R or C, we have here the
absolute value in the real numbers or in the
complex numbers. Therefore this part (b) now tells
you that the norm is always absolutely homogeneous.
So you can always pull out scalars but outside of
the norm they always get absolute values. Okay so
we are in a vector space we have two operations
the scalar multiplication we had in (b) and now in (c)
we have to explain what happens under the addition.
So let's look at two vectors x and
y. You already know how to visualize
the addition in a vector space: you just put
the two arrows together to get out the sum.
Then you see the triangle here and you think
that the length the norm should fulfill the
normal geometry in this sense this means
that it satisfies the triangle inequality.
It looks similar what we have for the metrics but
keep in mind here's with respect to the vector
addition. Therefore the norm is not a linear map in
general because you can pull out the addition but
what you get is only an inequality. Now you might
already guess that a vector space together with a
chosen norm gets a special name and you are right.
This pair is what we simply call a normed space.
So what we have is a real or complex vector space
where we can measure the length in a meaningful
way. Now you might ask what is the connection
to the metric spaces we defined at the beginning
s
of this video series. Since the property (a)
and (c) look very similar, the norm could be
a special case of a metric. Indeed this one is
an important fact you always should remember.
If you have a norm for the vector space X, you can
immediately define a metric. So maybe let's put the
norm in the index of the metric and then we can
define the distance between two points x and y.
If we look at the elements of the set X, we
should think of the end points of the arrows,
and then the distance between the two points
should be given by the connection vector which
is x minus y and then we take the length of it.
In fact, this then defines a metric for the set X.
This one is not hard to show.
I advise you to try it out.
So proving the three properties of the metric
by just using the three properties of the norm.
Now the most important thing to remember here is
because we always have this definition in mind and
a normed space is indeed a special case of a metric
space. In particular all the definitions we have
for metric spaces also work for normed spaces. So for
example closedness, openness and so on. And with this
in mind we can now eventually define what a
Banach space is. So it could happen that our new
metric space here (X,d) is a complete one. This one
is a very nice property which we discussed in the
last video. All the Cauchy sequences converge. We
don't have holes in this metric space. In this case
then the original normed space, X with its norm,
gets a special name: we call it a Banach space.
Okay so now you know the definition of one of
the most important objects in functional analysis.
So you see we have ingredients from the algebraic
side and also from the analytical side. On the one
hand we have a real or complex vector space and
on the other hand we have a complete metric space.
And the thing that connects both
sides very smoothly is our norm.
So please keep that in mind we don't have any
metric here we have the metric that comes from
this norm and by definition the norm can
deal with the algebraic operations. So this
is how I see a Banach space in the abstract
sense to get more concrete we will look at a
lot of examples in the next video so thanks for
listening and I hope I see you there bye [Music]