Hello and welcome back to
functional analysis.
And as always, I want to
thank all the nice people
that support this channel
on Steady or paypal.
Today we have part seven
where we discuss examples
of Banach spaces.
Please recall the picture
from the last time where
we learned that the Banach
space is on the one hand,
a real or complex vector
space.
And on the other hand, a
complete metric space where
the connection is given by
the norm.
Of course, now we can find
a lot of examples.
Let's start with the simplest
one, you can just consider
the real number line.
Therefore, we already know
it's a one dimensional real
vector space.
And we also know that we
can calculate lengths
if we consider the absolute
value in the real numbers.
Indeed with our
definition, this is a
norm and then
you should know the associated
metric is given by this
formula.
And that's just the normal
metric we have in the real
numbers.
And now from real analysis,
you should know that all
the Cauchy sequences indeed
converge in R.
In other words, are together
with this norm is a Bana
space.
So this is our first.
And as you can see a very
simple example,
however, we can consider
even a simple example.
And you might already guess
instead of a one dimensional
vector space, we choose a
zero dimensional vector space.
This means that the zero
vector is the only vector
in the space.
And of course, there's only
one norm we can define
here because the zero
vector has to have length
zero.
Hence everything we need
here is fulfilled.
We have a Banach space.
Of course, this is a very
boring one and not very
helpful.
Indeed, often it's a
pathological one which means
that some theorem we prove
later for Banach spaces will
not hold for this particular
one here.
Please keep that in mind
if you want to use the zero
Banach space as your example.
However, now let's continue
with one of the most important
examples.
This is the LP space written
as LP
NF
and denotes the natural numbers
and F is our field.
So the real or complex numbers
and P is a real number
greater or equal than one,
but it could also be infinity.
However, infinity is a special
case we consider later.
So here I exclude it.
Now, as I said, this
LPN F is defined
as all the sequences in
F that fulfill one condition.
So you immediately see the
notation here makes sense.
This is the domain and this
is the co domain for the
map given by the sequence.
And Now this condition is
given by the series where
you add up all the sequence
members and we do it in the
absolute value and to the
power P.
And if this series now
converges, which means it's
less than infinity, then
the sequence is an LP.
Often from the context, it's
clear if we are dealing with
real or complex numbers and
what the index set of the
sequences is.
And therefore one just writes
LP in this case.
Now, the first thing you
should note is that if we
ignore this condition and
just consider the sequences,
then they form a vector space
because adding and scaling
is just given in a component
wise sense.
Therefore, here we just have
to show that LP is a
subspace of this bigger vector
space.
However, what we also want
is a norm for this vector
space and
usually one just uses a
P as an index.
Now if we give the whole
sequence, the name X,
then we can calculate
the P norm of X
by using this number because
we know it's finite.
However, you might already
see that the second property
of a norm is not fulfilled.
In this case, we also need
the PEF root outside.
If you set P equals to two,
you will recognize something
similar to the Euclidean
norm in RD.
Indeed, with similar arguments,
we can show that this now
gives us a norm.
I emphasize that this is
not trivial to show that.
And indeed, I skip that here,
but we will do it later
here.
In this video, I want to
focus how we get the completeness
of the space.
Hence, our claim is
LP together with this
norm is a Banach space.
The first part of the proof
has to be that LP is an F
vector space and that this
P norm is indeed a norm
on it.
I already told you we don't
do it here.
We assume it, we will prove
it later.
That's just because we need
a lot of technical details
for this.
And I think it will distract
us from the important completeness
part of the proof here.
Now, in order to show the
completeness, we have to
choose an arbitrary
Cauchy sequence.
So this might be hard to
understand.
Now the queen X is
a sequence in F and
now we have to consider
sequences of
sequences.
Therefore, I choose here
an upper index K to
denote the different sequences
we have in our Cauchy sequence.
And now we have to show that
all the sequences here in
a row converge to another
sequence, a limit.
OK?
To get the right idea, let's
write down some of the sequences.
So here you see our Cauchy
sequence which goes from
top to bottom.
Now, for example, our X one
is a sequence in LP.
So it consists of real or
complex numbers in a row.
And the same we can write
down for X two X three and
so on.
Now, if you look at this
picture, you see a lot of
numbers in F in two different
directions from left to
right and from top to bottom.
And please keep in mind in
the end, we want the limit
here on the left.
In order to find this, we
can just look at the different
sequences we have here from
top to bottom.
So maybe you just take the
fourth column here and then
we look at the difference
between two members of the
sequence.
So maybe we use K
and L for the corresponding
index.
Now we want to put in the
information we already have,
which means we consider here
the absolute value to the
power of P.
And then we know this is
less or equal than
summing up all other
possibilities.
That just means that we have
here all the other
columns as well.
Of course, we do that because
here we have our P
norm to the power P
and there we find our original
sequences again where we
know that they form a Cauchy
sequence.
Don't worry, I'll remind
you what it means to be a
Cauchy sequence here.
For all epsilon greater zero,
we find an index and
maybe we call it capital
K such that
for all indices
afterwards K and
L we have that
the distance between two
members here is less than
epsilon.
Now, if you look at the inequality
above, you see that this
thing here is always greater
than just looking at the
absolute value in one column.
Let's put that in here.
And then you can see this
sequence here of normal
numbers in F.
So this column here is
also a Cauchy sequence in
F.
The value is just the normal
norm in F.
So the real numbers or the
complex numbers.
And we already discussed
this in the first example,
this is a Banach space.
In other words, this
sequence has a limit
and a suitable name should
be x tilde with an index
four.
And this limit in F is what
we find if we go from top
to bottom in the fourth
column, of
course, the four was just
an example.
You can do all the things
here with another column
as well.
So we can introduce an
index M for example,
and then I can change it
here everywhere.
Now, this means for all the
columns here, we find the
corresponding limit X till
the M we have here at the
bottom.
So indeed, what we get here
on the right is a new
sequence with numbers in
F.
Of course, we can and we
should give it the name X
tilde, but we don't know
yet if it's the limit here
on the left.
This is what we still have
to show now.
OK.
So the plan is to show that
XK minus X tilde
in the P norm goes to zero.
Or in other words, for an
arbitrary epsilon, this should
be smaller than epsilon.
OK.
So then let's write down
the P norm again.
So we have this series and
we need the P food again.
But it's easier to write
the power of P.
On the other side.
This just means that we used
to p-th root just in the end.
The first idea now would
be to push the limit process
here outside.
So we write the limit of
N to infinity.
So you see it's completely
the same.
But now we can discuss this
finite sum here on the right.
However, we know that this
X till the N is
also a limit.
Hence, we can push that limit
out as well because the absolute
value is a continuous function
and we just have a finite
sum here.
Now, if you look back, you
will see that this thing
here is what we can keep
as small as we want.
We use again that we have
here the property of the
Cauchy sequence.
Therefore, for our given
epsilon, we choose our capital
K such that we have this
at this point.
In the proof, we can't know
how small this really should
be.
Therefore, to be careful,
maybe we introduce an epsilon
prime and define it later
on.
Now, what we know from above
is that this whole thing
is less than epsilon prime
to the power P
as long as K and L
are bigger than the capital
K.
It's the same reasoning as
here.
OK.
So this is good information
for us because it tells you
we have here the nonne
numbers that are bounded
from above by this constant,
of course, then comes some
limit process.
But we know in the worst
case, this limit is
exactly this upper bound.
So in summary, we know for
all K greater or capital
K, this whole thing
is less or equal
than epsilon prime to the
power P.
And now is the point to take
the pea food because we get
rid of these two peas.
And now to get to the correct
result, we need epsilon prime
to be less than epsilon itself,
which means we can define
epsilon prime, for example,
as epsilon half.
And now in the end, you can
put everything together for
an abitrary chosen epsilon
greater zero, you find a
capital K such that for
all indices after the capital
K, you find the
inequality here, the
distance between XK
minus X tilde is less
than epsilon and there we
have it X tilde is
indeed the limit of
XK with respect to the
p-norm.
The only thing missing is
the explanation why X tilde
is also an element in
LP.
However, this now follows
from all we know we know
here that the difference
is an LP.
And we also know that XK
Therefore, if you write X
tilde in this way, which
means you subtract XK and
add it again.
Then you see the linear combination,
which means here's one part
in LP and here's one
part in LP.
Hence also the sum is an
LP because we are dealing
with a vector space.
That's the part of the proof
at the beginning where we
skip the details.
But here we can use it.
Of course, we will discuss
this even further in upcoming
videos.
But at this point, I really
wanted to show you an important
and non trivial example of
a Banach space.
OK?
I hope I see you in the next
videos where I first explain
more concepts in functional
analysis.
And afterwards we go into
more details for examples.
So thanks for listening and
see you later.
Bye.