Hello and welcome back to
functional analysis.
And as always, I want to
thank all the nice people
that support my channel on
Steady or paypal.
In today's part eight, we
introduce inner products
and Hilbert spaces.
You will see such an inner
product gives the space more
structure.
So maybe let's recall which
structures we already know.
First, we discussed
metrics and we learned
that a metric measures
distances in the space.
Afterwards, we introduced
norms for vector spaces.
And there we learned that
a norm measures distances
as well, but it also
measures lengths of
vectors.
And now an inner product
should do even more in a
vector space.
Besides measuring distances
and lengths, it is also able
to measure angles between
two vectors.
So you see an inner product
gives you a geometry like
you naturally have it on
the plane or the surrounding
space.
The user notation one uses
for an inner product is given
by these brackets.
So what we have is one vector
X on the left hand side and
another vector Y on the right
hand side, a nice
visualization for this would
be to have the vector X on
the horizontal line
and the vector Y in another
direction as an arrow,
which means in this picture,
we find an angle which we
could call alpha.
For example.
Now the inner product should
be a multiplication of these
two vectors where only the
component of Y
interdiction of X is
needed in the
picture.
This would mean that we have
here a wide angle and
only look at this arrow here.
Now, since you're good with
trigonometric functions,
you can easily calculate
the length of this yellow
arrow.
It is simply the length of
Y times the
cosine of alpha.
And this length now should
be multiplied with the length
of the AX.
And this formula now explains
what we want from an inner
product.
However, it does not define
anything yet.
It does not explain what
the norm should mean here
and what the angle alpha
is in a general vector space.
Of course, the correct logic
should be that we start with
an inner product, then we
define norm and then we
define the angle such that
we get a formula in this
sense.
In order to do that, we now
finally state the definition
as usual, we use the letter
F to denote either R or
C and then X
should be just an F vector
space.
Now, the inner product is
just a map where we use these
angle brackets.
Again, the
input is two vectors such
that the domain should be
X times X.
We've already discussed that
the outcome should be just
a number.
So is scalar in F
and there we already see
that if we are in the complex
numbers in a complex vector
space, this formula from
above can't be completely
true.
So let's use some quotation
marks to say that this was
just an informal explanation
at the beginning.
Nevertheless, it can still
guide us through the definition
here.
OK.
Now, such a map is called
an inner product.
If it fulfills three properties.
The first property tells
us that the inner product
should be able to measure
lengths.
This means that if we put
the same vector X into both
sides, then the
outcome should be a nonne
real number no matter if
we are in the real or the
complex case.
On the other hand, you already
know length zero should be
only possible for the zero
vector.
In other words, XX is
zero if and only if
X is the zero vector.
Of course, you recognize
this property, it's called
positive definite.
Indeed, you see it's the
same first property as we
had it for the norm.
Now, the second property
is about what changes when
we exchange the two vectors
in the inner product
having a picture from above
in mind, you see we still
have the same angle.
So it shouldn't make any
difference when we exchange
the two vectors.
So this should be
YNX.
However, this only makes
sense in the case that we
are in a real vector space.
So our F is indeed
R.
Now from complex vector space,
we've already seen that this
equation here can't be the
complete truth.
Indeed, the complex conjugation
has to be involved here.
Please keep in mind that
in the first property also,
in a complex case, we want
to get out a real number
when we put in the same vector
twice.
So therefore, if we exchange
it to vector here, we also
have to add a complex conjugation.
For this reason, we call
this property conjugate
symmetry or just
symmetry if we are in a real
case.
And now the third and last
property should finally be
the linearity.
The linearity makes sense.
If you look at the picture
again, if you scale
Y or if you add another
vector, then you could just
do the same with the outcome
for the formula, we then
need two vectors.
So let's call them why one
and why two and add them
the inner product should
be additive in the second
component, which means we
can pull out the addition
here.
Of course, it should also
be homogeneous, which means
we can pull out a scalar.
So let's call that scalar
lambda.
And then the equation looks
like this, which means
that on the right hand side,
we just have the multiplication
of two numbers in F.
And indeed, that's the part
that only works in the second
component because if you
want to do that in the first
component as well, you have
to use property two.
And that one tells you you
don't have any problem in
the real case.
But in the complex case,
you get out lambda bar
instead of lambda.
So please keep that in mind.
Both sides are not the same.
And here we have chosen the
second part to be the linear
one.
I emphasize that because
there are other people that
choose the first part to
be the linear one.
Therefore, please be careful
there.
OK.
So that's the whole definition
of an inner product.
And the vector space X
together with an inner product,
we just call an inner product
space.
Now, an important part we've
already mentioned is that
in an inner product space,
we can measure lengths
and we can do that simply
by defining a norm.
And we do this by using the
formula from above.
So we set the norm of X
to be the square root of
the inner product
by using these three properties.
It's indeed easy to show
that this defines a norm.
And if we need to be careful
which norm we talk about,
we can set the inner product
as an index here.
Now, to close this video,
I tell you now what a Hilbert
space is an
inner product space, which
means X together with an
inner product, it's
called a Hilbert space
if X together with the
corresponding norm is a ban
of space.
So this means we have a vector
space where we can measure
lengths and angles and it's
also a complete metric space.
OK?
I think that's good enough
for today.
I see you next time when
we discuss examples of Hilbert
spaces.
So have a nice day and see
you then.
Bye.