Hello and welcome back to
functional analysis.
And first many thanks to
all the nice people that
support me on study or
paypal.
And I can also tell you that
now you find the PDF
versions of all new videos
in the description below.
So this is part 10 today
and we will still talk about
inner products.
In particular, I want to
prove the Cauchy Schwarz
inequality
depending where you come
from.
The equality is known by
different names.
But I stay here with the
most common one.
And here it is named after the
French mathematician Cauchy
and a German mathematician
Schwarz.
Indeed, this inequality is
very important because it
holds for all inner products.
Therefore, let's choose an
F vector space X and an
inner product.
And we also consider the
corresponding norm which
is the square root of the
inner product.
And then with these notations,
the following inequality
holds, we
look at the inner product
X with Y.
And because it could be in
general a complex number,
we need the absolute value
here.
And then we can say this
is less or equal than the
two norms multiplied.
And that's the whole Cauchy
Schwarz inequality.
Now we can visualize it with
the same picture we had when
we started with the inner
products in this
multiplication X with
Y only the parallel
part of Y, the yellow part
here should matter.
Then this picture tells you,
yeah, of course, the length
of the yellow part is less
or equal than the length
of the wet arrow here.
With this in mind, we also
get a result in which cases
the equality here holds
indeed, this should only
be the case when the arrows
go in the same direction.
In other words, X and Y
are linearly dependent
vectors.
OK.
Now the picture gets us in
the correct direction, but
we don't have any choice.
We need to prove the inequality.
Now.
OK.
So let's start with an easy
case, let's call it the first
case where X is the zero
vector.
Of course, there we know
the left hand side has to
be zero
simply by the linearity,
we can just pull out the
factor zero.
And of course, the right
hand side is also zero
because the norm of X has
to be zero here.
In particular, the general
inequality is
obviously fulfilled for this
simple case.
Now you might already guess
the actual interesting case
would be the second one
here X is not a zero
vector, which means we can
divide by the norm of X.
And that's what we do immediately,
I want to define X hat
as the normalized vector
X, this means
that X hat has length one.
So it just gives the direction
of the vector X and
then we calculate the inner
product with X hat and
Y and go into the
direction of X hat.
Now, you might recognize
that because if we have
considered the normal Euclidean
geometry in the plane, this
picture would be completely
correct.
And this expression is
exactly this orange line
by our abstraction.
This should be the same here.
So let's call the orange arrow
just y
parallel in the
Euclidean geometry.
This is known as the orthogonal
projection of Y on to
X.
So it makes sense to do the
same for a general in our
product.
Now the gray line here is
the orthogonal part which
we also can calculate.
Now this is
simply given by Y
minus the parallel part.
OK.
So we defined some vectors
we want to deal with.
But now we need an idea how
to get to the inequality.
Indeed, the whole idea is
that we can calculate the
length or the norm of
this or formal part
simply because we know the
norm can't be negative.
Now, on the line we can put
in the definition and then
of course, also the definition
of Y parallel.
Now if you see something
like this calculating norms,
but you have an inner product,
it's better to use squares.
So square everything and
the square roots will vanish.
And now you can see on the
right hand side, we have
this long vector in the middle,
in both components of the
inner product.
So it looks like this.
And in order to simplify
this, we will use the
linearity.
And this linearity in the
second component means we
can pull out this minus
sign here.
So we have here a product
with Y minus the other
part.
In the next step, we want
to pull out the minus sign
here And here, and we
know we can do that because
the inner product is
conjugate linear in the
first argument.
So minus signs are not a
problem.
And scalars get a complex
conjugation.
So that's the first part
and the second part would
be this vector with y?
And of course, now we do
the same with the second
inner product here.
OK.
Here we have Y with the vector
on the right hand side.
And now we have minus minus.
So plus the rest.
In fact, here we have the
same vector left and right
in the inner product.
Therefore, now comes the
part where we can rewrite
everything.
Again.
The first thing is the norm
of Y squared.
For the two parts in the
middle, we see they are almost
the same, the one is the
complex conjugate of the
other one.
So we can write it in this
way with parentheses, we
put a bar over the second
part.
And finally, the last part
is the norm of this vector
squared.
In the next equality here,
I want to simplify that even
more because you see
here's a complex number plus
the complex conjugate of
this number, which means
this is two times the real
part of this complex
number, which means that
we can write it like this.
And now in the third part,
we can pull out the scalar
which means it comes out
with the absolute value squared,
you see it remains the norm
of x hat where we already
know this is one.
Now, finally, I want to simplify
the middle part here, which
to be honest, we could have
done before.
But then we would have done
it two times.
I want to show you visually
what we want to do.
We pull this scalar out
from the first argument of
the inner product, but
then it gets a complex
conjugation.
So let's fill in the gaps
again.
And then you see we have
the same complex number left
and right.
But the one is the complex
conjugate of the other one.
In other words, it's the
absolute value of the complex
number squared.
And since that is clearly
a real number, we can omit
the real part here.
So in summary, we have the
norm of Y squared minus two
times this number,
but also plus one
times the same number.
Therefore, we can put both
things together and have
a simple result here,
the norm of Y squared minus
the inner product in absolute
value squared.
So this is our right hand
side and on the left, we
have the zero.
Hence, in the next step,
I want to bring the inner
product to the other side.
Now, you can see we are almost
there with our inequality.
The only thing missing is
that we have to translate
back X hat
which is not so hard to do
because we define it as X
divided by the norm of X.
Of course, we do the same
as always, we pull out one
divided by the norm of X.
Hence, that's what we get.
And you see, we just have
to multiply with the norm
of X squared on both sides.
And then taking the square
root on both sides, we get
out our Cauchy Schwarz
inequality.
Well, that's the whole proof
of the inequality.
I will skip the part about
the equality now because
I want to use time to show
you that the symbol we use
here is indeed the norm.
So it fulfills the triangle
inequality.
And we will do that by
using the Cauchy Schwarz
inequality.
In fact, the triangle inequality
is most of the time, the
hardest part of a proof that
something is a norm.
So let's do that very quickly.
Of course, we square the
norm again
because then we don't need
the square root, we can just
write X plus YX
plus Y in the inner product.
The linearity now gets us
to a similar result as before
namely the norm of X and
Y squared.
And in the middle, we get
two times the real part of
the product.
Now, of course, if we use
the absolute value instead
of the real part, it gets
bigger.
And of course, here we now
can use our Cauchy Schwarz
inequality.
And now knowing the binomial
theorem, you see this is
just the square of the sum
of the two norms
taking the square root on
both sides.
You see this is simply the
triangle inequality for the
norm we defined by the inner
product.
The other two properties
for norm shouldn't be a problem
to show.
And therefore now it makes
sense to use this symbol
and call it a norm in an
inner product space.
OK?
I think that's good enough
for today.
In the next videos, we will
talk a little bit more about
the geometry.
An inner product gives the
space and I
already told you if you need
it, you can download the
PDF version of this video
in the description and of
course use the comments if
you have questions.
Otherwise I see you in the
next video.
Have a nice day.
Bye.