Hello and welcome back to
functional analysis
and many, many thanks to
all my great supporters on
Steady and paypal.
You really give me the motivation
to put all this work in making
these videos.
So thanks a lot in
functional analysis.
We've already reached part
12.
And today we will talk about
continuity
to be more precise.
We will talk about continuity
for metric spaces.
For this, we just need two
metric spaces.
So one set X with a
metric d_X and a set
Y with a metric d_Y.
And now we consider a map
from X to Y.
And now such a map is called
continuous.
If the preimages of
open sets are always
open more
concretely, we would write
the preimage of a set
B in Y.
So now this usually denotes
the preimage of B but I
want to make that really
clear.
So I want to use brackets
here.
I think that's helpful because
every time you see the brackets,
you know this is not the
inverse map, it's the pre
image.
OK.
Now we say this set is
open in
X for
any open set B in
Y OK.
So this is the former definition.
And now I can give you a
picture to remember it.
So we have our metric space
X on the left hand side,
on the right hand side, we
have our metric space Y.
And in between, we have the
map.
Now, for any open set
B in Y,
we find the corresponding
preimage on the left hand
side.
Now the property continuous
means that if you start with
an open set here, you'll
also get an open set here
by thinking about boundary
points.
This means that if you don't
have any boundary points
in this set, you also don't
in this set.
In fact, you can also read
that from left to right
by looking here at an input
and you change the input
a little bit by a small distance.
You know, this is always
possible because you are
in an open set.
And then you know, on the
right hand side, the output
is also only changed
inside this open set.
Of course, this notion seems
a little bit abstract.
Therefore, now we look at
something we call sequentially
continuous.
As the name tells you this
has something to do with
sequences.
In some sense, I can repeat
what I told you before we
choose any output on the
left hand side.
And let's call it X tilde.
And also let's look at any
sequence XN that
converges to X tilde.
And then it should hold that
the new sequence F of
XN is convergent
to F of X tilde.
In other words, every
convergence sequence on the
left hand side gets
translated into a convergence
sequence.
On the right hand side,
you might already guess for
us, it might be easier to
work with the notion sequentially
continuous because we just
have to deal with sequences
there.
Now, the good thing is that
for metric spaces, both
terms mean indeed the same
thing.
In other words, one can prove
that they are in fact equivalent.
For that reason, we will
simply use the word continuous
but often mean this
characterization with sequences.
However, I wanted to show
you both definitions because
if you don't work in magic
spaces.
But in general topological
spaces in general,
both notions are not
equivalent.
OK.
So I write down the fact
and then we can look at examples.
OK, maybe you already know
a lot of examples.
So let's look at some simple
ones.
The first one would be choosing
XDX as the
discrete metric space.
So where X is any non
empty set?
Now, on the right hand side,
it does not matter which
metric space we choose.
So let's say it's any metric
space.
Now let's look at the map
F from X to Y.
And then we can conclude
that this one has to be
continuous.
This is simply the case because
all subsets in a
discrete metric space are
open sets.
This means that checking
the definition of continuity
is immediately given here.
So keep that in mind, whenever
you see a discrete metric
space on the left hand side,
now another general example,
like this would be to consider
a constant function.
For this, we can choose X
and Y as general metric
spaces and then
fix A Y zero.
And Y.
In this case, then we
know that the map
F that sends all the
X to Y zero
is always continuous.
Indeed, this is what you
see immediately by looking
at the definition of sequentially
continuous.
Simply by looking at this
part where you know this
is always fulfilled.
The left hand side is always
Y zero.
The right hand side is always
So we stay at the limit point
for all N OK.
With this in mind, let's
go to two other examples.
I find very important
for the first example, I
want to look at a norm space.
Of course, we always have
the induced metric space
in mind.
And Y should be just R
with the standard metric
given by the absolute value?
And now the map I want to
consider is F given
by X to R
where an element X is
sent to the norm of
X.
And now our claim is that
is always continuous.
OK.
So for this, let's write
down a proof.
So we check that the map
is indeed sequentially
continuous.
Hence let XN be a
sequence in X with
limit point X tilde.
And then we look what happens
when we apply the map F.
Of course, F of XN is just
by definition the norm of
XN.
Now we have to bring in the
limit point because that's
the only thing we know about
the sequence, it has a limit.
So what I do is subtract
the limit and add it again.
So we add a zero here
inside the norm, we
do that because then we
can apply the triangle
inequality.
So I write X and minus
X tilde in the norm
plus the norm of XT.
And then we know the first
part is just the distance
between XN and X
tilde.
And the second part is just
F of X tilde.
By assumption we now know
that the distance between
XN and X tilde goes to
zero when N goes to
infinity.
Hence doing a limit on both
sides.
We get that the limit of
F of XN is less or
equal than F of X til
OK.
So you see that's already
half of the work we have
to do.
So now let's go from the
other side and show the other
inequality.
Therefore, we start with
F of X tilde, which is just
the norm of X tilde
doing a similar thing than
before we just put in
XN.
So subtracting and adding
again, of course,
now we doing the triangle
inequality gives us X tilde
the minus XN in the
norm plus the norm of
XN, which is a
similar result as before
because we have XT the
XN in the metric
plus F of
XN.
Now, I don't have to tell
you applying the limit on
both sides.
We get the inequality the
other way around.
And with that, our proof
is finished because we have
shown that the sequence F
of XN converges
with respect to the metric
in R to F of X tilde.
So we conclude the norm is
always a continuous map.
OK.
So you might guess with the
next example, we go to an
inner product space.
So let's choose X as an inner
product space where we already
know it's also a metric
space.
And why should we just the
complex numbers with the
standard metric given by
the absolute value?
Now, since an inner product
has two entries, I want to
fix the first one with a
given X zero.
Now the map we consider is
F defined from X to
Y.
So C and the
vector X is sent to the inner
product X zero with
X.
And the claim is again, this
map is a continuous one.
As before, I really want
to show you a proof of this
statement.
Of course, the procedure
should be the same as before
we consider any point X
tilde and a sequence that
is convergent to this point.
However, now, maybe we can
do it in one step when considering
the absolute value of F of
XN minus F of X
tilde.
In other words, this is the
inner product X zero with
XN and X zero with
X tilde using
the linearity, we can put
that together.
So we have just one in a
product.
Now, every time you see something
like that, you know, you
can apply Cauchy Schwarz,
this means that we have the
inequality I will abbreviate
with CS
and it tells us we have the
norm of X zero times the
norm of XN minus
X tilde.
Since this last part is the
distance between XN and X
tilde, we know this goes
to zero when N goes to
infinity.
Moreover, the whole right
hand side goes to zero
when N goes to infinity.
In conclusion, also the left
hand side goes to zero because
it was non negative from
the beginning.
And then we know the sequence
FX N converges to F
of X til
OK.
So we have shown that the
inner product is a continuous
map in the second argument.
And by symmetry or using
the same argument as here,
we can also show that it
is a continuous map in the
first argument.
This is important to know
for a lot of proofs we will
do in the future.
And I'll show you one.
Now indeed,
this is the cliffhanger from
the last video.
So we have an inner product
space and a subset U
and then U perp the orthogonal
complement of U
is always a close subset
proving this is not hard
at all because now we know
all the things we need.
Now please recall part four
of the series where I
described close sets with
the help of sequences.
So what we have to do is
choose a sequence in the
set itself where we know
it's convergent.
But first just in the space
X, now when we can
show that the limit X tilde
is also in U perp then
we know U perp is closed.
OK.
So now we just have to use
the definition of U perp
which means that inner product
of XN with U is
always zero, no matter
which U we choose.
Since this equation holds
for all N, we can look at
the limit and know this is
also zero.
And now we know we can pull
in the limit here because
this is just the continuity
of the map G we stated before.
In other words, we just have
X tilde with U is equal to
zero.
And since this holds for
all u in U, you see
this is just the definition
of U perp X tilde is
also in U perp.
And this is exactly what
we wanted to show the a formal
complement is always a
close set.
And you have seen this immediately
comes from the continuity
of the inner product.
OK?
I think that's good enough
for today.
Thank you very much for listening
and please check out the
PDFs if you want of
course, I hope I see you
next time when we go further
into the topic of functional
analysis.
So have a nice day and see
you then.
Bye.