Hello and welcome back to
functional analysis.
And as always, many thanks
to all the nice people that
support this channel on Steady
or paypal.
Today in part 13, we
talk about operators
between non spaces.
So the picture should look
like this.
We have one norm space on
the left hand side and one
on the right hand side.
Now an operator T is just
a map that conserves some
structures of our spaces.
We don't call T a function
but an operator simply
because often we have a
space of functions as a domain
or the co domain.
So every time you see the
notion operator, you know,
it's just another name for
a special map.
Now the first property that
T should conserve is the
algebraic structure, the
linear structure given in
the vector space.
In other words, the map should
be a linear map.
OK.
There we have one half of
our functional analytical
world and the other half
should be the topological
structure.
This is what we already know
because in a metric space,
we have a notion of open
sets.
And the property that conserves
these open sets is what we
learned in the last video
and is called continuity.
Of course, this seems a little
bit abstract.
But we will now see that
for non spaces as we have
it here, we can define
another property we call
bounded.
And we will see that together
with the linearity, this
is indeed equivalent to the
continuity in the
sense one often speaks of
linear bounded operators
between two norm spaces.
OK.
Then let's start with the
definition of the notion
bounded as before we
have two norm spaces and
a linear map T
of course, linear always
means it conserves the vector
addition and the scalar
multiplication.
This means that we have these
two formulas.
And maybe you also recognize
another common notation here
for linear maps, we will
omit parentheses if
possible.
Now what we want is the
length of this linear map.
So we want a norm for the
operator.
Hence this is then often
called just the operator
norm of T.
And if we want to emphasize
the spaces, the map acts
on, we have to put them in
the index.
However, most of the time
we will omit them there because
the corresponding normed spaces
are known from the beginning.
OK.
But we still don't know how
to measure this length.
So let's start with an idea.
Now, imagine we have our
norm space X on the left
hand side and Y on the right
hand side, let's pick a
vector X.
And we know we can measure
the length of X.
And now we know the map T
acting on this vector will
give us a new vector.
And why?
So here we have the vector
TX with length
norm of TX.
Of course, here we have to
measure the length with the
Norman Y.
And here we have to measure
it with the Norman X.
What we now can put in relation
is how much did the length
change from left to right?
In other words, what is the
quotient of the length of
TX divided by the
length of X?
Of course, this is now a
number we could use as a
definition for the norm
of T.
However, of course, this
can only be meaningful if
we look at all possible inputs
on the left hand side.
So we're looking at all possible
ratios that can come out
by going through all the
xs.
Obviously, the only exception
should be the zero vector
because this one is the only
one with lengths of zero.
Now, you might already see
that the norm of T should
be the biggest ratio we can
get out here.
So the maximum of the set,
however, we can have an infinite
dimension in X.
So we have infinitely many
directions we can look at.
Therefore, it can happen
that the maximum does not
exist.
So what we need here is the
supreme of this set.
We are in the real numbers.
So we know the supreme always
exists in the worst case
it would be the symbol infinity.
And there we have our notion
if this norm of T is
finite, we call T
bounded.
And I already mentioned that
non bounded linear operators
can only happen if X is
of infinite dimension.
And please note that this
notion of bounded for linear
operators is different than
the notion bounded for normal
functions in R for example.
So please don't get confused
there.
Now, with the definition,
out of the way, let's go
to the proposition that connects
this to the continuity.
Here.
Again, we have a linear map
between two norm spaces.
So the same thing as before
and then we know the following
three things are equivalent.
The first is that T as a
map between metric spaces
is continuous.
Now B is similar but
here T has only to be
continuous at one point
when we choose the origin
at this point.
And the last one is that
T as a linear operator
between norm spaces
is a bounded operator.
So this is the fact I already
told you at the beginning
continuity and
bounded this exactly in this
sense are equivalent terms
for linear operators.
And of course, this is so
important that we should
write down a proof.
The first implication we
should show is A to
B which is obviously
immediately fulfilled because
being continuous at all
points implies being
continuous at zero.
So let's go to the next one
which would be the implication
from B to C.
Here we really have to do
something.
So let's start by writing
down what it means to be
continuous at zero.
As often we want to use the
characterization with sequences.
So here we consider convergence
sequences but only with
limit 0.0.
The continuity then implies
that the images also
converge.
And because we have a linear
map, the limit point is also
zero.
However, here it might be
easier to work with an epsilon
delta characterization for
the continuity.
So let me write down the
claim we need here.
The formulation before which
we call star now implies
there is a delta
such that the norm of
TX is always less
than one for
all x with length less
than delta.
If you know continuity, you
already know that you already
believe that.
But for the sake of completeness,
let's write down the proof,
let's do a proof by contra
position.
So let's call the whole right
hand side here.
Just star in wet
the negation of the red star
then implies
that for all N, we
find an XN
with length X and
less than one over N,
the one over N corresponds
to the delta here.
So we say there is no such
delta.
So we can do that for all
N here, which also
means that the norm of
TXN is greater or equal than
one.
And there you see we found
a sequence that converges
to zero.
But the images don't converge
So this applies then
not green star.
And by contraposition,
this proves the claim we
want to use.
Now
we call that we want to
calculate the quotient of
the norm of TX
divided by the norm of
X.
However, at the moment, we
can only say something about
the vector X that have length
less than delta.
Of course, this is something
we can use here because we
could multiply with delta
half, which is less than
a delta times
one over the norm of X.
So why do we do that?
Simply because with that
factor, we can scale the
length of the vector X
since you know the properties
of the norm, you know, we
can push that inside the
norm.
And you also know that T
is linear.
So what we get in the
denominator is a vector
that has exactly length
delta half.
And that's something that
reminds us of our red star
property.
The vector has length less
than delta.
So the corresponding image
has length less than one.
Hence, the numerator is now
less than one, which means
the whole thing is less than
two over delta.
So the only thing that remains
is applying the supreme
on both sides now,
since we exclude the zero
vector, we know this all
works also the supreme
has to be less than two over
delta.
The important thing is of
course, this is not
infinity.
Well, this was B to C
continuity at zero
implies bounded.
And now the last part is
a bounded operator is
continuous everywhere.
So let's consider any point
X tilde in X and any
sequence that is convergent
to this point.
And then we want to look
what happens to the images.
So we look at
TXN
minus TX tilde
inside the norm of Y.
Then the linearity tells
us that we can apply T to
the difference vector and
then calculate the nom.
And now we can use what we
know we have to find an
operator norm of T
which is by definition the
largest possible scaling
for the length of the image.
In other words, we know this
is less or equal than the
operator norm times the
length of the input.
And that's XN minus
X tilde.
Since we already know this
is convergent, we know this
goes to zero when N goes
to infinity.
So the whole right hand side
goes to zero.
Hence also the left hand
side which tells us that
also the images converge
and that's by definition,
the continuity.
So our proof is finished.
OK.
So this was our first important
result for linear
operators between norm
spaces.
What you can do for yourself
now is showing that this
operator norm be defined
is indeed a norm in the
usual sense with
that.
I think it's good enough
for today.
Thanks for listening.
Thanks for supporting me
and see you next time.
Bye.