Hello and welcome back to
functional analysis.
And many, many thanks to
all the nice people that
support me on Steady or paypal
today.
In part 14, I want to show
you one example how to
calculate the operator norm.
In this example, our norm
space X should be given by
the continuous functions.
The domain of the functions
should be the unit interval
and the co domain, the complex
or real numbers.
And the common norm for the
space is this a premium norm.
And the second space Y should
be just the complex or real
numbers together with the
absolute value.
Hence today, we will consider
a map T that sends a
continuous function to just
a number.
In order to define this
operator, I want to fix a
continuous function G
to make our life a little
bit easier.
The function G shouldn't
have any zeros.
Now, for each such G, we
define an operator T and
therefore I put an index
G to it.
Now the operator sends a
function F to a number.
By the following definition,
it's the integral of the
function G multiplied
with the function F
now because we are only dealing
with continuous functions.
You can read this as an Riemann
integral or an leak integral.
It does not matter the
question for us is, is
this a bounded operator
or a similar question?
What is the operator norm
for this?
Please recall that the operator
norm of TG is
given by a suprema
more concretely we have the
norm of the output
divided by the norm of the
input.
And then we go over all functions
of X with the exception of
the zero vector.
So what we can always do
is apply the scaling as we
did it last time we can
do that such that we only
divide by one.
So we consider only functions
with supreme norm
one.
Of course, you don't have
to do that, but it makes
our life easier because we
don't have to write down
a fraction here.
In the next step, we just
fill in what we know from
the image we have here.
The absolute value of this
integral.
This integral is of course
what we need to calculate.
But maybe a better first
step would be to find an
estimate.
Now, I want to use the knowledge
that pulling the absolute
value into the integral
only makes it bigger or it
stays the same.
And then we just use the
multiplicativity of the absolute
value, which means we can
pull out the multiplication
sign.
Then in the next step, we
see that we have here the
absolute value of F at some
point T.
However, this can't be bigger
than the largest value, which
is given by the supreme norm,
which means that we have
here constant.
And we already fixed that
to one.
In summary, the supreme can't
change anything anymore.
So we know the operator norm
can't be bigger than the
integral of G.
And we already know this
is a finite number because
we have a positive continuous
function inside the integral.
So indeed, this is a bounded
operator.
The last question that remains
is what exactly is the
operator norm of TG?
Do we have in fact an equality
sign here or is the
operator norm really less
than this integral?
In order to answer this question,
it's always good to look
at some examples because
then you get a lower bound
for the whole supreme.
And if you do that, you might
find that you also can use
the function G as an input.
However, then we can't use
this line here because
here we need that the supreme
norm of the function we put
in is exactly one.
But of course, you know,
we could change the function
G in such a way just by
dividing by the absolute
value of G.
So let's call this function
H and I also want to
add a complex conjugation
here which will be helpful
later.
Now it's easy to see the
supreme norm of age is
exactly one.
Now putting this function
into TG and looking
at the absolute value.
Then we know this has to
be less or equal than the
operator norm itself.
On the other hand, we know
this is the absolute value
of the integral where we
have to function G times
H.
And now you see why we added
the complex conjugation before
because now we have the absolute
value squared in the numerator,
we can omit the absolute
value outside because everything
is positive here.
And we also can just
cancel out one absolute value
of GT.
And then what remains is
exactly the same integral
as before.
And now we can put both
inequalities together and
find out that the operator
norm of the operator TG
is exactly this
integral.
OK.
So this was one quick example
of calculating the operator
norm of an operator between
two norm spaces.
In the next video, I want
to start talking about operators
between Hilbert spaces.
So thanks for listening.
Thanks for supporting me
and see you next time.
Bye.