Hello and welcome back to
functional analysis.
And as always, I want to
thank all the nice people
that make this video possible
by supporting me on steady
or paypal.
Now, we have reached part
16 in our course.
And we'll talk about compactness
today.
The word compact you find
very often in functional
analysis.
However, here we first go
back to metric spaces.
It's a property we define
for subsets in a matrix
space and it should
extend the finite.
So a finite
set should always be
compact.
Then for an infinite set,
the compactness would say
that your movement is still
restricted in a similar way
to get an idea of what this
actually means.
Let's look at a subset in
RN.
Of course, we have our N
with our usual Euclidean
me.
Now, you know what it means
to say that A is a closed
set, the
whole boundary should belong
to the whole set itself,
which means you can't leave
it from the inside by using
a sequence.
So you see this is one restriction
you have for your movement.
And another one comes in.
If you look at a bounded
set, this
simply means that there is
a maximum distance you can
go, you are not allowed to
go to infinity.
Now, you might already know
these two things together
is what we can shorten to
compact.
However, please be careful.
Actually, this is not a
definition.
This is a fact we only have
in RN or if you
want also in CN
together with this standard
metric.
Therefore, the correct question
here would be how can we
define compact in
general such that we get
the correct notion for infinite
sets?
Of course, this is now what
we will do.
So let's fix a metric space
XD in the
same way as before, let's
consider a subset of this
space.
And now we define this as
a compact set or more
concretely as a sequentially
compact set.
Maybe you already recognize
the same thing that happened
in the continuity definition.
There are two terms you could
define one with sequences
and the other one without
sequences.
And then the result for metric
spaces is they are
equivalent.
It's the same thing here,
but I don't want to bother
you with the actual compact
definition.
The term sequentially compact
is just easier to understand
and we just call it compact.
Now, however, please
keep in mind when you're
not working in metric spaces.
But in general topological
spaces, you have two terms
that are not equivalent
for us.
It's not a problem here.
We call a compact if
for each sequence in a,
we find a convergent
subsequence where
the limit X tilde
still lies in the set
A.
So you see there's a lot
going on here, you start
with a sequence, then you
omit some members,
which means that you get
a subsequence, which is
also convergent where the
limit still lies in a,
in the picture.
This would mean inside a
set A, we have
infinitely many points
given by the sequence
XN.
Of course, a lot can happen
for this sequence.
But compact now means
that you can choose infinitely
many points in the sequence
such that you get a limit
out.
For example, here, only one
part remains where we have
convergence to a point X
tilde.
And this should work no matter
which sequence you started
with.
Now, if you go back to our
end with this knowledge,
you immediately see this
excludes unbounded
because if you tend to
infinity, you can't find
such a convergence subsequence.
Also the set has to be closed.
Otherwise you can just choose
a sequence that has a limit
outside of the set.
A.
Then of course, you can't
add a new limit with a
subsequence.
OK.
Next, let's look at some
examples.
For the first example, let's
choose a more concrete one
than the one from above.
So this should be just the
real number line together
with the standard metric,
the Euclidean metric which
is given by the absolute
value.
And the set A should be given
as the unit interval.
Now, in this one dimensional
case, you should see that
the formulation with the
sequences and the convergent
subsequence is
exactly what you learn in
analysis.
It's the famous Bolzano
Vastra theorem.
Then with this in a tool
set, one can easily show
the equality here for RN
or CN with the standard
metric.
Therefore, let's now look
at the same set together
with another metric.
So again, the real number
line, but now with the discrete
metric, now you might
already guess in this
case, the unit interval is
not compact.
In order to show this, you
just have to find one sequence
which has no convergence
subsequence at all.
Hence, let's simply do that.
OK.
So let's choose to sequence
XN by setting
XN as one over
N, it's a
sequence inside the unit
interval but it's not
constant.
Hence, we already know what
the distance is between two
members of the sequence
we are in the discrete metric
space.
So we get always one or
two different points.
However, this now means that
we could omit a lot of members
in the sequence, but we never
get the one down to zero
here.
In other words, there can't
be any convergent subsequence.
In conclusion, the unit interval
is not compact with
respect to the discrete metric.
OK.
So please keep that in mind,
always emphasize the
corresponding metric when
talking about compact sets.
Now for the end of the video,
I want to show you a nice
proposition which generalizes
the results from above,
we have our metric space
XD and a compact
set A then
we can conclude.
So it's an implication not
an equivalence
that A is closed
and bounded.
So in general, we still have
the result that closeness
and bounded is needed
for the compactness.
It's not the other way around
compactness in general is
more.
But this can still be helpful
before writing down the proof,
we should first define what
we mean by a bounded set
inside the metric space.
Of course, this is not so
surprising if you have your
set a here, it
simply means that you can't
find a large enough epsilon
ball such that the whole
set lies inside this
ball.
So we just have to find a
middle point X
and a radius epsilon.
And then we want that the
open Epsom ball around
X is a superset for A
and this is what we mean
when we say bounded,
it simply means that there
is a constant such that any
two points have distance
less than this constant.
And here you see this constant
would be just too epsilon.
OK.
By knowing all the terms
in the proposition, we now
can write down the proof
starting from a compact set,
we have to do two things.
First, we want to show that
A is closed.
So let's choose a convergence
sequence in a.
Hence we know there is a
limit X tilde in
X.
Now we call, if we can show
that X tilde is actually
in a, then A is closed
using the compactness, we
immediately get the result
for a subsequence.
Hence, we have a convergent
subsequence with limit
in A.
And maybe we call this limit
X tilde tilde.
Of course, this is not necessary
because we know we already
started with a convergence
sequence.
And we know the limit is
always unique.
You can't find another limit
with a subsequence.
Hence X tilde and X tilde
tilde do coincide.
So we know X tilde lies
also in a, this is
exactly what we wanted to
show.
Therefore A is closed.
OK.
Then the next step is showing
that A is bounded.
We do this with a proof by
con interposition.
This means that we start
with a being not
bounded and we want to end
compact.
Now, if A is not bounded,
we know that we can find
distances as large as
we want.
Hence, for given point A
in the set A, we
find infinitely many points
XN in A
such that the distance to
A is larger than the
natural number N.
With this, we have one sequence
XN in A where we can look
at all possible
subsequence.
Now, if A was compact,
we would find a subsequence
with a limit.
Therefore, let's look at
all possible limit points
as well.
Hence, we would be interested
in the distance between the
limit point B and the
sequence X and K
simply because if the sequence
was convergent, this would
go to zero.
However, the only distance
we know at this point is
the distance between A and
XN.
And using the subsequence,
we know this is larger than
NK.
Then on the right hand side,
we simply can use our triangle
inequality.
We just put B in the middle,
then bring the one part on
the other side and we get
the following inequality.
So we conclude the distance
between any point B and a
sequence number X and K is
always larger or
equal than this part here.
However, seeing the NK here,
you know, you can make the
left hand side as large as
you want.
Hence, our conclusion is
no matter which point B you
choose.
If you send K to infinity,
this will never go to zero.
So there can't be any limit
point for the subsequence.
If you fix a point B here,
you will always run away
from it.
And therefore A is not
compact because we found
a sequence which does not
own any convergent subsequence.
And by contras position,
we finished our proof, a
compact set is always
bounded.
OK.
So now you know the notion
compact for metric spaces
and in the next videos, we
will extend this to
operators.
So I hope I see you there.
Thanks for listening and
bye.