Hello and welcome back to
functional analysis
and as always many, many
thanks to all the nice people
that support me on Steady
or PayPal.
We've already reached part
18 in our course
and today we want to talk
about compact operators.
As the name suggests, this
has something to do with
the compact sets we've already
studied.
Therefore, recall that the
idea of compactness has
been to extend the notion
of finiteness a little bit.
A similar thing we will now
do for operators
Here
the analogue of finiteness would
be linear operators between
finite dimensional vector
spaces.
So let's look at an operator
from F^n to
F^m. On both sides,
we can just choose the normal
Euclidean norm, the standard
norm.
However, everything I say
now does not depend on the
norm.
It holds no matter which
norm you choose here.
The first step is not so
hard to show, it tells us
that the linear operator
between finite dimensional
normed spaces is always
continuous
and of course, you already
know continuous means the
same as bounded for linear
operators.
In other words, the image
of the unit ball under T
is a bounded set.
Now, this is a bounded set
in our finite dimensional
normed space F^m
and there you know this is
one half of the things you
need for being compact.
However, the second ingredient
we just get when we form
the closure of this set.
This means that we just can
use a bar over the set
and then we get a set that
is always compact in
F^m.
With this essentially, you
now know what a compact
operators is.
When we look at the image
of the unit ball and form
the closure
and this set is compact,
we speak of a compact operator.
Of course, this always holds
in this case, but not in
general.
In order to see that let's
consider the identity
operator
in l^p.
Of course, identity operator
just means we take a sequence
x and send it to itself.
Therefore, calculating the
image of the unit ball is
not so hard. It stays the
unit ball.
Now we are interested in
the closure of the set.
So we use the bars again.
So what you have on the right-
hand side is just a closed
unit ball in l^p
and there we know from the
last video it's closed and
bounded, but not compact.
Hence, we have something
here,
we would not call a compact
operator, because the image
is just too large in this
case.
So you should always remember
compact operators is what
we get when we extend the
finite dimensional operators
here a little bit.
OK, then let's write down
the formal definition.
So we need two normed spaces
and often there will be Banach
spaces. Then a
bounded linear operator
T from X to
Y is called
compact,
if we have the thing we discussed
before, that this set
here is compact
in Y. Therefore, in the
case that Y is a finite
dimensional normed space, this
here is nothing special.
However, in the infinite
dimensional case, it really
is.
Hence, I would suggest that
we now look at a common
example. Let's
look at an integral operator
defined for the continuous
functions.
So it should take a function
defined from 0 to 1 and
send that to another function
in the same space
and as often the space of
continuous functions should
carry the supremum norm.
So what we can do is apply
the operator T to a function
f and then we get out a new
function.
Hence, we can look what the
function does at a given
point s, where s comes from
the unit interval.
Now the number that comes
out here should be given
by an integral from 0 to
1 where we have the function
f involved, but
also a fixed function
k
and this function should
get the variable s and also
the integration variable
t.
So we have a function with
two variables and for us
it should be also a continuous
function.
So we have it from C defined
on the unit interval times
the unit interval.
Now, since the function k
goes into the definition
of T, I put it into the
index here.
OK, then let's check if
T_k is indeed a
compact operator.
An important fact we will
need here is that the function
k is defined on a
compact set.
So it's not just continuous,
it's uniformly continuous.
To refresh your memory,
let's write down what this
exactly means.
For all epsilon greater zero,
there exists a delta greater
zero such that for
all points we put in and
now we need two variables
and for them, it should hold
if the distance is less than
delta, the distance of the
images should be less than
epsilon.
On the left-hand side, we
measure the distance with
the Euclidean norm in R^2
and on the right-hand side,
we measure with the Euclidean
norm in R^1, which is the
absolute value.
Why we need the uniform continuity
here, we see in a moment.
The first step we have to
do when we see such an integral
operator is to check if
this integral defines
indeed a continuous function.
Simply because otherwise
the operator wouldn't be
well defined.
It really should map continuous
functions to continuous
functions.
Checking the continuity
then means we look at the
difference of the images
when we put in different
points.
So this should be small when
the points s_1 and s_2
are close together.
Therefore, we first calculate
and then we can look what
happens.
Now, the first thing you
should see here is that we
can put that into one
integral.
So use some parentheses here
and delete this integral
here.
Then of course, we pull in
the absolute value. Then we
get an inequality
and with this, we have everything
we need, because this one
here is less than a supremum
norm of f
and this one by the uniform
continuity of k can be as
small as we want
and exactly this is what
we should formally write
in front of the whole calculation.
So for a given epsilon greater
than zero, we choose the
delta in such a way that
this whole thing holds.
Therefore, we can choose
s_1, s_2 from the unit
interval such that the distance
is less than delta.
For this s_1, s_2 here
and the same t on both sides,
we can apply what we know,
that this is less than epsilon.
By using also that this one
is less than the supremum
norm,
we are finished with the
whole integral. It's
simply less than epsilon
times the supremum norm
and because the supremum norm
of f is just a constant in
the whole calculation, we
now know that this function
is indeed continuous.
So we can note, our
operator as written as
here, is well defined.
However, our calculation
here shows us even more.
If we define the set A
as the image of the unit
ball, then we see
by this whole estimate here,
that the set A is
uniformly equi
continuous.
If you don't know what this
means anymore, let's write
it down again.
It just means that for all
epsilon greater zero, there
exists a delta such that
for all s_1, s_3 and all
g in A, we have the
uniform continuity
implication here.
From the definition of the
last video, I only had to
change some names.
I used the name g for the
function here, because we
already had a function f
and of course, we needed
the names s_1, s_2 for
the variables.
However, what you should
see is that this one is the
definition of a being
uniformly equicontinuous
and it's the same thing as
we have written here.
In other words, with the
calculation above, we have
proven that A is indeed
uniformly equicontinuous
at this point. You might
already guess that we want
to apply the Arzelà–Ascoli
theorem here.
Therefore, another step we
have to do is showing that
the whole set is bounded.
Or in other words that the
operator is bounded.
Hence, let's calculate the
operator norm.
So we have the supremum of
all the norms of the images,
where f has norm one
by the definition of the
supremum norm.
This is the supremum over
all s, where we calculate
the absolute value of the
integral.
As often, we can just pull
in the absolute value into
the integral and get an inequality
out
and with this, we are almost
finished, because the last
part here is less or
equal than the supremum norm
of f
and this is by assumption
just one. This
means that we don't need
the outer supremum anymore
and can just write down
everything is less or equal
than this integral.
However, this is also less
or equal than the supremum
norm of our function k.
As often, it's not important
what the number here is exactly.
It's only important that
it is constant, because then
we know that T_k is a
bounded operator
and now finally comes our
conclusion, we can apply
Arzelà–Ascoli.
This set, the image of the
unit ball is uniformly
equicontinuous and bounded.
Therefore, both things also
hold for the closure of the
set
and by Arzelà–Ascoli, we now
have a compact set
and by our definition, we
also know T_k,
the integral operator is
a compact operator.
So you see this was a long
example, but it is a standard
example for a compact
operator.
Of course, we will talk about
compact operators in later
videos even more.
Therefore, as always, I hope
I see you there.
Bye.