Hello and welcome back to
functional analysis
and as always, I want to
thank all the nice people
that support this channel
on Steady or PayPal.
In today's part 19, we
will go back and prove Hölder's
inequality.
There are a lot of different
inequalities named after
Hölder and indeed, they are
all related,
but here we look at the simplest
one. It's the one that
holds in F^n
and for p greater than one.
For each such number p, there
is a Hölder conjugate which
we call p prime.
The definition is what you
should really memorize.
The reciprocals should add
to one.
This is an important relation,
because every time we use
p prime, this is what we
mean. Instead of p
prime, a lot of people just
use q.
However, here I want to use
q as another variable to
tell you again what the p-
norm was.
Or today, I would better
say the q-norm of a vector
x.
It's defined by the sum over
the entries in the absolute
value to the power q
and then we take the q-th root
of the whole thing
and this is what we do for
all q between one and
infinity including one.
Now Hölder inequality will
connect the p-norm the p
prime-norm and the 1-
norm. Indeed, it's one
nice short formula,
you always should remember.
I will now use a possibly
strange notation to help
you to remember the important
inequality. Putting two
vectors together just
denotes a new vector which
has the product in the components.
So x_2, y_2 in the
second component and
x_n times y_n
in the last component.
Then for all vectors x and
y, we have that the 1-norm
of the vector xy
is less or equal than the
p-norm of x times the p
prime-norm of y
and that's what we call
Hölder's inequality.
Often you see it written
with the sums, but I think
it's better to write it immediately
in this way. On the one
hand, it's easier to remember
and on the other hand, we
will generalize the whole
thing later on.
Indeed, there we will have
the whole inequality for
functions defined on an abstract
measure space.
However, that's not what
we do today. Today
we prove it for vectors
in F^n.
In order to prove Hölder's
inequality, we first need
another inequality which
is known as Young's
inequality.
In fact, this one is very
simple.
We just look at positive
numbers a, b and
then we conclude that the
product of ab is
always less or equal than
the following sum.
So what you should see here
is that p greater than one
goes in and the Hölder
conjugate.
So as before you can choose
p greater one as you want,
but then p prime is fixed.
For example, for p equals
to two, we have p prime equals
to two.
However, in this case, you
already know that the inequality
here is correct.
So please check that,
but for all other cases,
we have to write down a proof.
What we can use here is that
the common exponential function
is a so called convex
function.
This means that when you
look at the graph,
then you can choose any two
points
as you want.
The direct connection would
be always above the graph.
This property is called convex,
because the red line is the
convex combination of the
two points.
Therefore, we can easily
put that into a formula when
we call the function just
f.
Now, by denoting the two points
by x and y, we can form a
convex combination of x and
y and put that into the function
f. Which means we get out
the blue line here.
Please recall a convex
combination is just a special
linear combination, where
we only have one lambda which
comes from the interval
0 to 1.
Now with the red line, we
also get a convex combination
with the images. Which means
we have here instead of x
and y, just f(x)
and f(y).
Therefore being always above
the blue graph means we have
here our inequality.
Which we now want to use
for some special numbers.
Lambda should be one over
p and then one minus
lambda should be one over
p prime.
Maybe that's not so clear
but for x I want to put in
the natural logarithm of
a to the power p
and the similar thing for
y but now with b and p
prime. Of course, this
all fits together, because
by applying the logarithm
rules, we can bring this
power in front, where it cancels
out. Hence,
on the left-hand side, we
have the two logarithms in
the function f.
Now using the next logarithm
rule
and the fact that the exponential
function is the inverse function
of the logarithm, we have
just ab on the left-hand
side
and now you see the idea
of the whole proof. We want
to show this one and we're
already finished with the
left part.
Regarding the right-hand
side, we just put in all
the numbers we already know.
Now this looks more complicated
than it really is, because
we have again the inverse
function of the logarithm
here.
Hence this all vanishes
and what remains is what
we wanted to show.
So Young's inequality is
correct and we can use it
to prove Hölder's inequality.
Starting with the proof,
let's first consider the
simplest case.
What I mean by that is that
we look what happens when
x is the zero vector or
y is the zero vector,
but of course, this is not
a problem for us, because
by the definition of all
the norms here, we have that
the left-hand side is zero
and the right-hand side is
zero.
So the inequality is fulfilled.
Therefore, for the second
case, we can divide and bring
everything to the left-hand
side.
Of course, now we want to
bring this inside the norm
and divide x by its p-
norm and y by its p prime-
norm.
However, since I use this
strange notation here, I
bring in now the whole sum
of the 1-norm. Here we have
it and we can pull in the
norm into the sum and then
into the absolute value
and there you should see
now, that we have two positive
numbers, which we could call
a and b and then apply
Young's inequality inside
the sum.
So at this point, we get
the inequality sign in.
OK.
The first term is one over
p times x_j
to the power p divided by
the p-norm to the power p.
The second term looks similar
and I already distributed
the sum over both parts.
So here we just have p prime
and j instead of x.
However, that's not so important.
The important thing you should
see is what we have in
the numerator together with
the sum, is the same as the
denominator and the
same in the second part.
Hence, the only things that
remain is one over p here
and one over p prime here
and by the definition of
the Hölder conjugate this
is simply one
and with this, we have proven
Hölder's inequality, because
you can bring this one on
the right-hand side again,
if you want.
So you see the proof was
not so hard, but we will
need Hölder's inequality to
prove another inequality
and this one will be the
so called Minkowski
inequality.
Essentially, it's just the
triangle inequality for our l^p
space.
Therefore, I hope I see you
in the next video.
Thanks for listening and
see you then.
Bye.