Hello and welcome back to
functional analysis.
And as always, many thanks
to all the nice people that
support this channel on study
or paypal.
This is part 26.
And I still want to show
you more main results in
the topic of functional analysis.
Today, we will talk about
the so called open mapping
theorem, also known as the
Banach Schauder theorem.
As the name suggests, the
theorem is about open
maps.
Therefore, I first want to
start explaining what an
open map is the
notion openness we define
for metric spaces.
So therefore, let's choose
two metric spaces X and
Y.
Of course, now we want to
consider a map from X
to Y.
Now such a map F gets the
name open if it sends
open sets in X to
open sets in Y.
In other words, if we take
any open set A in
X, then the
image F of A should
also be an open set.
However, please don't forget
the notion openness is always
given with respect to the
corresponding metric space.
OK.
So this looks like a natural
notion.
Therefore, let's immediately
look at some examples.
First, a very general example
because you might already
recognize the connection
to the definition of continuity
here.
So let's fix a bijective
map, which means we have
an inverse map F to the
power minus one.
Of course, this one now goes
from Y to X and we
also choose it to be a continuous
map.
Having these two assumptions.
The map F from X to Y
is indeed an open map.
This is easy to see when
you look at the definition
of the continuity of the
inverse map.
It simply means when you
have an open set on the right
hand side, the pre image
on the left hand side is
also an open set.
Of course, everything looks
very similar here.
You see we have the inverse
map from Y to X.
Then we take a subset A in
the space X which is on the
right hand side of the inverse
map.
But on the left hand side
in the picture, so don't
get confused here.
Then we go to the pre image
which is here again denoted
by the power minus one.
OK.
You could think this is an
overload for a notation but
indeed it fits together
because this is simply
the image of A and
F.
This comes from the 1 to
1 correspondence we have
by our bijective map
F.
Now with this example, you
should see that the definition
of an open map looks
similar to the one of a
continuous map.
However, it's completely
different because it goes
the other way around.
OK.
Then let's write down some
concrete examples of open
maps.
Maybe a simple example would
be to look at a normal function
between the real numbers.
Of course R is just given
with the standard metric,
which means the absolute
value.
And I want to send X to
X cubed.
This has to be an open map
because F is bijective
and the inverse is
continuous.
In the same way, we can construct
a counter example.
Just look what happens when
we send X to X
squared.
Of course, we can't use the
general example here because
it's simply not bijective
but still it could be an
open map.
Of course, this is not the
case, it's not an open map.
As you can see when
considering the open
set as the open interval
minus 2 to 2.
Then the image is simply
the interval 0 to
4.
And there you see this is
not an open set in R
Now with your new knowledge,
what an open map is, we can
finally state the open mapping
theorem.
The important ingredient
you always should remember
here is that we need Banach
spaces on the left and the
right hand side.
So the completeness of the
spaces is essential here.
Now for bounded linear
operator T, where I use the
notation with the curved
B again, we
have that it is
surjective
if and only if
T is an open map.
And that is the famous
open mapping theorem.
It just tells you that
surjectivity for a linear
bounded operator between
Banach spaces is a strong
property because
it implies the openness.
Indeed, the implication from
right to left is not so
surprising and easy to
prove the actual work
one has to do from the left
to the right hand side.
Therefore, the proof of the
first implication is a good
exercise for you.
But for the other one, we
need a whole other video.
However, before we do that,
I want to use the next video
to show you an important
consequence of the open mapping
theorem.
It's called the bounded
inverse theorem.
Hence please watch the next
video because this consequence
is very important in a lot
of applications.
So have a nice day and see
you then.
Bye.