Hello and welcome back to
functional analysis.
And there's always many,
many thanks to all the nice
people that support this
channel on Steady or paypal.
Today.
In part 28 we will talk
about the spectrum of a bounded
operator.
The spectrum comes in as
a generalization for the
eigenvalues of a matrix.
For this.
Please recall when we have
a square matrix A
which means we have N rows
and N columns and the entries
can come from the complex
numbers.
Then we are able to talk
about the eigenvalues of
a.
In particular, we call a
complex number lambda an
eigenvalue.
If we find a corresponding
eigenvector more
concretely, this means there
exists a vector X
which is not the zero vector
and it fulfills that
AX is equal to
lambda X.
In other words, the matrix
multiplication for this vector
X is reduced to a scalar
multiplication at this
point.
It's a good idea to rewrite
this equation.
For example, we can just
bring lambda X to the left
hand side by using the
identity matrix.
Now we have a new matrix
that sends this vector X
to the zero vector.
However, this then means
that the kernel of this matrix
contains more than just a
zero vector.
Please recall in the kernel
we find all the vectors that
are sent to zero.
Of course, we can also see
this matrix as a map.
So a map that sends a vector
X to the vector A
minus lambda
IX.
Now having the kernel be
bigger than the zero space
is equivalent to say that
this map is not
injective.
OK.
This might be a good time
to refresh your linear algebra
knowledge and talk about
the rank nullity theorem.
It holds for all matrices
M where the important thing
is that we have the number
N for the columns.
This number N is the
dimension we have as an
input for this map here.
And in the following sense,
this dimension is
conserved.
The new dimension we get
out on the right hand side
is given by the dimension
of the range of M.
Therefore, this number can't
be bigger than N.
And in the case, it is less
everything else has to go
into the kernel of M.
In other words, both dimensions
have to add up to the original
dimension we put in.
Now because this formula
connects the range and the
kernel, we immediately get
for square matrices.
And this map that
injectivity
bijectivity and surjectivity
are indeed the same thing.
Hence, here, we could also
say this map is not
surjective or simply the
map is not invertible.
However, if we leave the
finite dimensional case,
this W nullity theorem will
not hold any more.
For this reason, we immediately
get different possibilities
for which the invert of this
map can fail.
Now, for the rest of the
video, let X be a
complex Banach space
and T from X to X
should be a bounded linear
operator.
To put it.
In other words, X is the
generalization of CN
and T for the matrix A.
Therefore, the spectrum of
T should be the generalization
of the set of all
eigenvalues.
So it should be a subset
of the complex numbers.
And usually it's denoted
by the lower case Sigma.
Now inside this set Sigma
T we have all the
complex numbers lambda
such that T minus
Lambda identity is
not bijective.
Therefore, if we consider
a finite dimensional vector
space X, we are in this
case again and get out a
set of all the E
values.
However, for the infinite
dimensional case, we will
see that we can split up
this set into three parts.
Before we do that, let's
also define the so-called
resolvent set of T.
And this one is denoted by
a lower case W
the set looks very similar.
But now we look at all the
complex numbers lambda where
this map is indeed bijective
and the inverse is bounded.
So in some sense, these are
the good points because there
we can invert our bounded
operator.
Of course, at this point,
you know a lot of functional
analysis.
And therefore, you see we
are working in a Banach space
and therefore we can use
the bounded inverse theorem,
which simply means when we
have the bijectivity this
immediately follows.
So we can just say
Sigma is the complement
set of
rho. With this, you see
why we need to work in Banach
spaces because only
there we get out the
inverses as bounded
operators and we
work with complex vector
spaces because as we will
later see, this spectrum
gives us more information
in this case.
However, of course, all the
definitions here also work
with real vector spaces.
When you substitute C with
R. Knowing all
this, I can show you now
how we can split up the set
sigma T.
The first one is the so-called
point spectrum of T.
Indeed, this is the only
set we have for the finite
dimensional case.
However, in the infinite
dimensional case, we also
have a set, we call the
continuous spectrum and a
set we call the residual
spectrum.
Now, from the discussion
above, you might already
guess that we can split up
the bijectivity here into
injectivity and
surjectivity.
In fact, that's what we can
do.
And in the case that this
operator is not injective,
we define the point spectrum
of T.
Please recall we learned
above that not injective
means this operator has a
nontrivial kernel which
means we have eigenvectors
in the sense, these points
are indeed the classical
eigenvalues.
OK.
Now, you should see to get
a disjoint union, we also
have to include the injectivity
here.
So in this sense, we could
actually do it, but it turns
out we can distinguish the
points even more.
Now, not surjective, simply
means that the range of the
operator is not the whole
space X.
However, it would be a nice
property to have almost a
space X.
And this would mean that
the closure of this set is
X.
Now these points lambda form
the continuous spectrum by
definition, both names
are chosen in this way because
for important examples, the
point spectrum consists of
individual points in C
and the continuous spectrum
forms whole intervals.
This also explains the last
name.
The residual spectrum just
gets all other points
here.
The operator is injective
but not surjective.
And even the closure of the
range is not X.
Here, I can tell you for
the property that the closure
is the whole set X.
We simply say the range
lies dense in X.
Later, you will see that
for many important
examples, the last set is
indeed empty.
This is not always the case,
but for these examples, we
only have to deal with these
two sets here.
OK.
Then let's use the next video
to look at some examples.
Therefore, I hope I see you
there and have a nice day.
Bye.