Hello and welcome back to
functional analysis.
And first, I want to thank
all the nice people that
support this channel on study
or paypal.
This is the second part in
our spectral theory.
And we will talk about
examples.
The overall assumption here
is that we have a complex
banner space X and a
bounded linear operated
T.
For this, we define the set
sigma T, the so-called
spectrum of T.
Now you already know lambda
is an element of Sigma T
if and only if
T minus lambda
identity is not
invertible as a bounded
operator.
The first new thing I can
tell you today is that
usually we will omit the
identity in our notation.
One can ignore the identity
here because everyone knows
what it should actually mean
and we save space every time
we use this expression.
And of course, when we talk
about the spectrum, this
operator here occurs a lot.
OK.
Then let's go immediately
to our first example.
A good start would be to
look at a simple finite dimensional
example.
Therefore, our B of space
X is then given by
CN and
our linear operator T should
act on any vector
X like the
diagonal matrix with
entries lambda one, lambda
two and so on, on the
diagonal.
In other words, the result
of TX is simply the
vector lambda one X
one until lambda
NXN.
And here you see merely that
the set lambda one to lambda
N is exactly our
spectrum of T.
Now, please remember that
we learned in the last video
that in the final dimensional
case, all the points in the
spectrum are eigenvalues.
So the spectrum is equal
to the so called point spectrum.
Indeed, in this simple case
here, we can immediately
wipe down the eigenvectors.
They are just given by the
standard basis in CN.
OK.
I think that's enough, we
can say in finite dimensions,
the interesting things happen
of course, in an infinite
dimensional case for
this, let's choose the LP
space.
We've already proven that
this is a banner space for
P between one and
infinity.
So here you should see this
is a straightforward generalization
of our CN.
The only difference is that
a chosen vector X here does
not have an end.
Otherwise I want to have
the operator T to do the
same as before.
Therefore, we could write
this as a one sided infinite
matrix.
So you see this is the overall
idea to find the generalization
of the finer dimensional
example from above.
But of course, we really
should state the formal definition
of the operator T.
So we take complex numbers
lambda one lambda two and
so on with the proper, that
they form a bounded set.
And this can be stated that
the supreme of the absolute
values is finite.
With this, we then define
T as a bounded linear
operator from LP
into LP
simply by setting the J component
of TX as lambda
J times XJ.
Of course, this fits in with
our definition from above.
But now you see we need this
condition to get a bounded
operator.
OK.
At this point, you should
see what we did in the final
dimension example, still
works in this infinite dimensional
example.
In particular, we find simple
EIG vectors such that all
these values are
eigenvalues.
So let's immediately write
that down.
For example, E one, the
sequence
100 and so
on is an EIN vector
corresponding to the EIN
value lambda.
One of course, in the
same way we have a two
with one at the second
position as an eyeing vector
with corresponding eyeing
will you lambda two?
Hence, you see we continue
this for all our
lenders.
Therefore, we have shown
now that all these lambdas
lie in the spectrum of tea.
In other words, at least
we have a subset relation
here.
On the other hand, we immediately
see any other complex
number can't be an eigenvalue
of T.
Therefore, this set is indeed
the point spectrum of T.
However, you already know
this is in general not the
whole spectrum of T.
Indeed the important thing
that could happen is that
this set is actually
infinite and then
it has an accumulation point
which is something that cannot
happen in the finer dimensional
case.
OK.
Then in the next step, let's
consider such an accumulation
point.
So let you be a complex
number with the property
that it is not in the set
itself but
in the closure of the set,
OK.
Maybe an example is very
helpful here.
So it could happen that Lambda
J is given as one
over J, then the
only possible accumulation
point would be mu as
zero.
Hence, in this example, we
would have our eyeing wills
as one over J.
So they tend to zero but
zero itself is not an eye
value.
In fact, this is the general
result T minus
mu is always
injective.
Now, at this point, you might
already guess in the next
step, we want to show that
this operator is not
subjective.
Now, with this result, we
know that Mu is in the spectrum
of T as well for
showing this, let's use a
proof by contradiction.
Now assuming that the operator
is rejected, then we know
it's also by ejective.
Please remember the inject
deity was not a problem at
all.
OK?
And now we can use the famous
bounded inverse theorem to
conclude that the inverse
of our operator is also
bounded.
Knowing this, let's try
calculating the corresponding
operator norm.
At least we know this is
greater or equal
than the norm.
When we put in one of our
EJS,
please recall, this is just
a sequence of zeros with
the exception that at the
J position there is a one
for this reason, the acting
of the invoice operator is
easy to calculate.
We just gave the inverse
of the number lambda J
minus mu.
Also very simple is then
calculating the P norm we
just get the absolute value
of this number.
OK.
And at this point, you should
see a problem here.
This estimate we have shown
holds for all natural numbers
J.
And that's a problem because
we know with the Lambs,
we can get as close as we
want to mew.
In other words, the reciprocal
here will explode
or more formally, you can
choose a subsequence of the
natural numbers here.
And then this sequence goes
to infinity.
So no matter how we put it,
this number here can't be
finite.
And that's the contradiction
because we know it should
be bounded.
Therefore, our conclusion
is it's not subjective.
OK.
Let's summarize what we have
found.
The spectrum of T contains
our lender values
and also the accumulation
points.
You now it's not
hard to show that these are
indeed the only possibilities
for the spectrum.
So this is what the spectrum
of the operator T looks
like.
The first part is the point
spectrum of T, the Eion
values.
And the second part is the
continuous spectrum together
with the residual spectrum
in fact, later, we will be
able to show that for P
less than infinity, the
residual spectrum is indeed
empty.
Therefore, in our case, this
is actually the continuous
spectrum.
OK.
I think that's good enough
for this example today,
let's use the next videos
to talk about general results
about the spectrum.
Therefore, I hope I see you
there and have a nice day.
Bye.