Hello and welcome back to
functional analysis.
And there's always many,
many thanks to all the nice
people that support this
channel on study or paypal.
In today's part 30 we are
still talking about spectral
theory.
This means that we still
analyze the set sigma of
T which is the spectrum
of the operator T.
So we have all complex numbers
lambda such that T
minus lambda identity
is not invertible.
On the other hand, we have
the complement the resolvent
set of T which is denoted
by a row.
Now please remember in this
context, we will always omit
mentioning the identity operator
here.
It's simply shorter in this
way.
Also don't forget we do
everything in a complex Banach
space X
and for a bounded linear
operator T from
X to X.
OK.
Now, in this context, we
have some nice results about
the spectrum.
So let's summarize some facts
in one proposition.
First, I can tell you that
the resolvent set is
always an open set.
In conclusion, this means
that the spectrum is always
a close set.
Therefore, the visualization
should always be that you
are in the complex plane
and you have some close set,
which is the spectrum of
T and everything
outside is an open set,
which is the resolvent set.
Later, we will also see that
the spectrum of a bounded
linear operator is also
a bounded set or in
other words, this spectrum
is compact.
OK.
Now, for part B let's take
an element from the resolvent
set.
So here we just have a complex
number lambda.
Now, the good thing we know
is that the operator T minus
lambda has an inverse.
So writing the power minus
one here makes sense.
And we can also calculate
the operator norm
which is always greater
or equal than
one divided by the
distance of Lambda to the
spectrum in the picture.
This means what is the shortest
distance we have to go until
we reach a point in the spectrum.
And this is simply what we
call the distance from a
point to a set.
So you see the closer
lambda is to the spectrum
of T, the bigger this
norm has to be
OK.
Here we observe that we can
have different operators
when we have different, values
lambda.
Hence, we can look at a map
that sends lambda to this
operator.
Of course, lambda has to
come from the resolvent set.
But then we get a bounded
operator on X.
So here BX denotes
the space of all bounded
linear operators from X
into X.
And now our result
is that this map is
an analytical map
in short, this nice map is
often called the resolvent.
Of course, at this point,
you should ask yourself,
what does it mean for a map
like this to be
analytical?
The short explanation here
would be just the definition
which tells us this map
locally can be
expressed as a Taylor
series.
What this means exactly.
I will show you in the proof
of this statement.
Therefore, let's immediately
start proving these
things.
First, you should note in
the case that the resolvent
set is empty.
Everything here is trivially
true.
For this reason, let's consider
the case where we have at
least one point lambda
zero in the resolvent set.
This means that the operator
T minus lambda
zero has an inverse.
Then for the next part, let's
consider the operator norm
of this operator,
it's a constant.
I want to call C
and the reciprocal I want
to call epsilon.
OK.
Now, what we want to do I
can visualize in the picture
above.
So here we have lambda zero
and now I want to look at
the epsilon ball around this
point in the complex plane.
Now, when we show that this
epsilon ball is completely
inside the resolvent set,
we have shown that the resolvent
set is indeed an open set.
Therefore, let's take an
arbitrary element from this
epsilon ball.
So it's a complex number
lambda where the distance
to lambda zero is less
than epsilon.
OK.
Now, having this, our plan
is to show that this
operator T minus lambda
is also invertible.
Therefore, let's calculate
a little bit.
Now we want to transform
this to the operator we already
know.
So T minus lambda zero.
Therefore, we have to add
and subtract lambda zero
here or for example,
we can write the equality
in this way.
Then in the next step, the
operator we already know
is invertible.
We can just factor out here.
So here we have the identity
operator minus
lambda minus lambda zero
times the inverse.
OK.
Now I can tell you why this
form here is so helpful for
us.
For this reason, let's call
this operator here.
Just s
first, let's look at
the operator norm of S
where we can just use that
this one is less than
epsilon and this one is in
the operator norm C.
So in summary, this whole
thing is less than epsilon
times C which is by
the definition of epsilon
just one.
So here you should see we
have an operator with operator
norm exactly one where we
subtract an operator with
norm less than one.
And the result is such a
combination is always
invertible.
Indeed, this is called a
Neumann series
an operator I minus S
where the norm of S is less
than one is
invertible.
Because the reasoning goes
like for the geometric series
for numbers, this
means that we multiply the
operator I minus S
with the sum of the powers
of S.
And then it does not matter
if we multiply it from the
right or the left,
we just get the same result
by telescoping the two
sums, which means
I minus S to the
power N plus one.
And now we can use that the
operator norm of S is less
than one, which means that
this sequence here
converges to zero
when N goes to infinity.
And of course, this convergence
is measured with the operator
norm.
Therefore, we conclude if
we have an infinite sum here.
So a series,
then this operator defines
the inverse of I minus
S indeed this
series is well defined as
a limit because the norm
of S is less than one.
And we call it the Neumann
series.
OK.
Now, this nice general
result we can use here
because now we can conclude
that T minus Lambda
is also invertible.
That's simply because it's
the product of two invertible
operators.
And this is true for all
Lambda with this proper T
and also lambda zero
was arbitrary chosen,
therefore row of T
is open.
In conclusion, our spectrum
sigma of T is closed.
So the whole statement in
A is proven
also, you might already see
that we have in equation
above our Taylor series.
More concretely, we have
T minus Lambda is equal
to T minus lambda zero
times the Neumann series.
Or to put it.
In correct words, we get
the Neumann series when we
look at the inverses here.
And don't forget taking
inverses changes the order
of the operators.
Therefore, we have the Neumann
series in front.
OK.
At this point, we can just
substitute our operator S
again.
And then we get the
series where we have this
product to the power K.
So what you should see is
lambda minus lambda zero
to the power K which looks
like a Taylor series.
OK.
Maybe when we combine these
two operators and put them
in formed, then you see this
is exactly a Taylor series.
So these are just constant
coefficients but now they
are operators but
otherwise it looks like a
totally common Taylor series.
And there you see this is
exactly what we call an
analytical map.
And therefore C is also
finished.
OK.
Having this, let's close
the video by proving B.
So if we now take a complex
number lambda from the spectrum
of T, then we know from
above that there's no other
choice than that.
The distance from LAMBDA
to LAMBDA zero is
greater or equal than
epsilon.
And then looking at the reciprocals,
we get that one
over the distance is less
or equal than C.
And they are, please recall
this is simply the operator
norm of T minus lambda
zero inverse.
And with this, we are almost
finished.
Now we just have to go through
all the points in the spectrum.
OK.
Maybe let's write it down
with more details.
So the distance here is just
the infimum where we
simply go through all the
points lambda in the
spectrum.
And now if we pull the infimum
out of the denominator, it
gets a supremum.
And at this point, we can
just use the inequality from
above.
And then we have shown our
claim or in other
words, also be is
shown OK.
With this, I hope I see you
in the next video where I
show you how we can use all
of this.
Have a nice day and see you
then.
Bye.