Hello and welcome back to
functional analysis.
And first, as always, I want
to thank all the nice people
that support this channel
on Steady or paypal.
Today's part 31 is
still about spectral
theory.
In particular, we will talk
about the so called spectral
radius.
For this.
First, please recall that
we work in a complex Banach
space X and
with a bounded linear operator
T there, we have
already discussed that the
spectrum of the operator
T is a subset of the
complex numbers.
Indeed, we have shown it's
a close set.
And as usual, we denote the
spectrum with sigma of T.
Now the spectral radius just
measures how far the spectrum
is away from zero.
And this is what we denote
by R of T.
So by definition simply the
suprema of the absolute
values.
So you see we can immediately
define this number here.
And in this video, we will
show that this is indeed
always a finite number
more concretely.
The spectrum is not the empty
set and also a
bounded set.
OK.
Now let's formulate it and
then prove it.
So we have a theorem with
the same assumptions as before
most importantly, we have
a bounded linear operator
from X to X.
Then our first statement
is that the spectrum of T
as a subset of the complex
numbers is a compact set.
Please recall in the last
video, we have already shown
that it is a closed set.
Therefore, the new thing
here is that the set is
also bounded.
Then our next statement here
is that the spectrum is never
empty.
However, this is not completely
true because there is one
case where this can happen,
it happens when you choose
the smallest possible vector
space.
So when the whole vector
space is only the zero vector,
then there's only one linear
map T and is
always invertible.
Therefore, the spectrum needs
to be empty.
However, when we exclude
this in fairness boring
case, then the
implication is correct, the
spectrum of T is non
empty.
OK.
Then the last part C is about
the spectral radius.
As I already told you the
spectral radius are of
T is given by the
supreme where we go
through all the points lambda
in the spectrum.
And we look at the absolute
value.
Now, one important result
here is that instead of calculating
a supreme, we can look at
a limit and there we take
the operator norm of the
powers of T.
Then outside of the norm
we take the k-th root again,
one additional result is
that this sequence is monotonically
decreasing.
So the limit is equal to
the infimum.
However, most importantly,
we get the result that the
whole spectral radius is
bounded by the operator norm
of T.
Therefore, please always
remember the spectral radius
can never be bigger than
the operator norm.
And this is not something
we can immediately prove
for this.
Let's use the properties
we used in the last video.
For example, the Neumann
series is very helpful here.
Therefore, let's take a complex
number lambda which is in
the absolute value greater
than the operator norm.
And now we want to show that
this number can't be in the
spectrum of T.
And in fact, this is immediately
given by the Neumann series.
It tells us that the identity
operator minus an operator
S is always
invertible if the
norm of S is less
than one.
And in this case, the inverse
that exists is given by this
infinite series.
And now, in our case, of
course, instead of S we take
T divided by Lambda
by assumption this operator
here has operator norm
less than one.
And now you should see it's
a very short way from this
to T minus Lambda,
we just have to multiply
this with minus one
over Lambda.
In the end, we get a very
nice expression for T minus
Lambda inverse.
Of course, the important
result is this inverse
exists as a bounded linear
operator.
Moreover, I would say you
should also remember this
formula here that holds for
Lambda that are large enough.
OK.
Now we conclude this lambda
here is not in the spectrum.
Therefore, this supreme here
is indeed less or equal than
the operator norm of T.
In addition, this implies
that the spectrum of T is
bounded.
And I already told you, we
know from the last video
that the set is closed.
Therefore, we have proven
a additionally, you
see that one part of C is
also already proven.
However, now I want to skip
the other parts of C and
concentrate on B
because there we can also
use immediately some facts
from the last video.
So here we can do a proof
by contraposition.
So let's assume that the
spectrum of T is the empty
set.
No spectrum at all means
that the resolvent set is
the whole complex plane.
So row of T is C
and now you can recall the
fact that the resolvent map
is an analytic map
more concretely the map that
takes lambda and sends it
to T minus lambda
inverse can be
locally expressed by a Taylor
series.
This is what we have shown
last time.
And now we can use it.
OK.
Since you know a lot of functional
analysis at this point, it
shouldn't be a problem for
you.
When we now use the dual
space of BX,
this space of bounded linear
operators is a Banach space.
Therefore, it has a well
defined dual space
which I always denote with
the prime.
Therefore, this L is now
a linear functional defined
on the operators.
And of course, now I want
to apply the L to this
operator here.
Now you see we get a nice
map fl from the resolvent
set into C
because the linear function
in L maps into the complex
numbers.
Also by assumption we know
the resolvent set is given
by the whole complex plane.
So what we have here is a
very nice analytic
function, an
alternative name for this
is the notion holomorphic.
Therefore, now at this point,
you can use everything you
know from complex analysis.
Indeed, what we get is that
FL is a bounded
entire function
here.
The term entire is not so
complicated.
It simply means analytic
together with the domain
C.
So the entire complex
plane is the domain
and that the function is
bounded we can easily show.
Now of course, there we
just have to look what happens
for large lambda values.
And here for us, it turns
out that two times the operator
norm of T is already
large enough because for
these LAMBDAS, we can simply
use our equation star from
above.
More concretely, let's take
fl of lambda in the
absolute value.
Then by definition, this
is less or equal than the
operator norm of L
times the operator norm of
T minus lambda inverse.
And exactly for this norm,
we can use our Neumann series
here.
This means that this is less
or equal where we have one
over the absolute value of
Lambda in front and then
comes the infinite sum of
the operator norm of T divided
by lambda to the power K.
And now, by assumption, we
know this operator here
has an operator norm which
is less or equal than one
half.
So what remains here is just
a geometric series, you can
calculate more concretely.
The value is less or equal
than two.
And because we can also estimate
this one here, we have our
bound, the absolute value
of our function F Lambda
is simply less or equal
than the operator norm of
L divided by the operator
norm of T.
OK.
So this tells us that FL
is indeed a bounded entire
function.
And now from complex analysis,
we can apply Liouville's
theorem, it tells
us that a bounded entire
function needs to be a
constant function.
And please note here this
fact holds no matter which
linear functional L we choose.
OK.
Since we have a constant
function, we can simply
calculate this constant,
we can simply put in one
point into the function.
And of course, the simplest
one would be zero
and there we just have L
of T inverse.
And now this value is the
only value the function can
have.
Therefore, we have this equality
for all complex numbers
lambda.
OK.
Now this is the definition
of the function.
And now I want to put in
what we already know of this
inverse.
As a reminder we often call
this inverse simply the
resolve from the
last video we know this is
analytic.
Therefore, we can put in
the Taylor series we calculated
there.
And it simply looked like
this not so
complicated because here
you see the coefficients
and there we have lambda
minus lambda zero.
And to make it simpler, we
can just put lambda 0 to
0.
So we can simply erase it
here and there.
OK.
Now this is much nicer and
now we can pull in L
and of course, then we get
our Taylor series for
fl so you see
coefficients here and lambda
to the power K here.
OK, maybe still a little
bit complicated.
But remember we know the
function is constant.
Therefore all the coefficients
after the term K is equal
to zero will vanish.
Therefore, for example, the
term that corresponds to
K is equal to one is
zero.
So this means L of T to the
power minus two is zero.
And again, as a reminder,
this fact holds now for
all linear functionals
and now every time you see
something like this, you
should immediately think
of the Hahn-Banach theorem.
And in the case, you don't
remember it.
Look at part 25.
Again, it tells us
that if we put in the same
point into all functionals
and the result is always
zero, then the point has
to be zero as well.
So for us, this means this
operator is the zero
operator however, it's an
inverse.
Therefore, this shouldn't
happen at all.
The only case where this
strange thing can happen
is if we start with the trivial
vector space and
usually we don't do that.
Therefore, the result is
that in all other interesting
cases, especially for
infinite dimensional vector
spaces, the spectrum of an
operator is never empty.
OK.
So this was a lot but I hope
you could follow here.
In that case, I see you in
the next video when we go
deeper into the field of
spectral theory.
Have a nice day.
Bye.