Hello and welcome to this
video about the Weierstrass
M test.
This is a topic from real
analysis, so if you want
to learn more, you should
check out my real analysis
course.
However, before we start
with this M test, I really
want to thank all the nice
people who support this channel
on Steady here on YouTube
or via other means.
And please don't forget with
the link in the description
you find additional material
like PDF versions, quizzes
and other stuff.
Okay.
With this I would say we
can immediately start explaining
the Weierstrass M test.
Now what you should remember
is that this M test is
a comparison test for
series, but for the
uniform convergence for
a sequence of functions.
So it's not so complicated
at all.
And it's called m test simply
because the constants in
the theorem are called
M.
And there I would say we
can immediately formulate
this statement.
And as already mentioned,
the only thing you need here
is to know what a series
is and the uniform
convergence for a sequence
of functions.
And these functions can be
defined on any set.
So let's call it D.
And indeed, often we have
that D is a subset of the
real numbers.
Hence our functions fk
should have D as their
domain.
And now the functions could
be real valued or complex
valued.
So in general we could just
write that they map into
the complex numbers and
then we have a function for
each k in the natural
numbers, so already
a whole sequence of functions
with the same domain D.
However, for the Weierstrass
M test we are interested
in the partial sums, so the
series of these functions.
And to have the convergence
of this series, we
assume that we have constants
with the name M.
And as already mentioned,
this is the whole reason
we call it the M test.
Now we have two assumptions
for these constants.
First, they should be non
negative, and second, the
series should be
convergent.
This means that the limit
of the partial sums should
exist.
In other words, the value
of the series is not equal
to infinity.
And now in addition, the
constants should be always
bigger than the values
of the functions fk.
More precisely, we look at
f k of x and take
the absolute value of this,
and then this should be less
or equal than
M_k.
And indeed we want that for
all k in n and for
all x in D.
So the constants M_k
form a uniform majorant
for the functions.
Ok, so these are the assumptions
we need, and then we get
the result for the series
of the functions fk.
Indeed, by the comparison
test for series we
immediately get that the
sequence of partial sums
converges for every x in
D.
However, we get even more
because we deal with functions.
The term uniform
convergence also makes
sense.
So we get out that the series
is uniformly
convergent.
Moreover, as a side note,
I should also mention that
we have the same result for
the absolute value of the
functions.
So both nice things come
out of the Weierstrass M-
test.
Now, in the case you don't
know exactly what the term
uniform convergence means,
let me refresh your memory
here.
Now, the first thing you
should see here is that we
get a well defined function
we can call S,
and this one has the same
domain D and it sends
x to this series.
And what I mean there is
that we just sum up f
k of x and
this limit should exist.
So we get a well defined
function S.
And moreover, this capital
S is the limit of the
partial sums of the functions
fk.
And when I say limit, I mean
with respect to the supremum
norm.
And please recall, the supremum
norm is usually denoted with
this infinity sign on the
norm.
Now, S is the uniform
limit for the partial sums.
So this goes to zero when
n goes to infinity.
Hence, this is exactly what
we mean by the uniform
convergence stated in the
theorem.
And maybe it's always good
to visualize this convergence
in a picture.
So let's sketch the graph
of the function S,
and let's simply say that
here on the x axis, we have
the domain D.
Hence, for example, the graph
of S could look like
this.
And now what one can do is
to look at such an epsilon
tube around this
graph.
And then the result is, no
matter how small we choose
this epsilon, the graph
of the partial sums
always lies inside.
Obviously, this only has
to hold eventually, which
means n has to be big
enough.
So this is what you can remember.
This is exactly what the
uniform convergence means.
Okay, then the next step
would be to look at the proof
of this statement.
And in fact, it's surprisingly
easy.
We only need the so called
Cauchy criterion for
series.
And you can find that in
my real analysis course in
part 17.
And it simply tells us that
a series is
convergent if and only
if the partial sums form
a Cauchy sequence.
So you see, the Cauchy
criterion simply
uses the completeness of
the real or complex numbers.
Now, more precisely, this
means that for all epsilon
greater zero, we find an
index capital N
such that for all
indices afterwards,
and let's simply call them
lowercase n and
m, we have that
the sum in the absolute value
is less than epsilon,
and the sum has to go from
m to the index
n.
So you could just say this
partial sum is
arbitrarily small
eventually.
And now please recall, in
the assumption of the theorem,
we assumed that we have the
convergence for the series
of Mk, which means
we have the Cauchy criterion
as well.
Hence, for a given epsilon
greater zero, we can choose
a capital N as
above, and then we immediately
get a result for the series
of the functions fk.
So let's simply look at the
partial sums from m to
n as well.
And then we can just use
the standard triangle
inequality.
It's a finite sum, so we
can just pull the absolute
value inside.
And then in the next step
we can just estimate f
k of x inside.
And now the assumption comes
in that we know that each
one is less or equal than
Mk.
However, for the series of
the non negative Mk's,
we already know it's less
than epsilon by the Cauchy
criterion.
In other words, the Cauchy
criterion now also tells
us that this series here
is a convergent one,
which already implies that
the function S from above
is a well defined function.
In other words, it exists
and it makes sense to talk
about it.
And thats what we will do
now, because we want to talk
about the supremum norm
more concretely, we want
to take the difference of
S with the partial sums
in the supremum norm.
And exactly like before,
lets fix an epsilon greater
zero and lets choose the
corresponding index capital
N.
And as always, the lowercase
n should be greater or equal
than this capital N.
Now first, as a reminder,
the supremum norm is given
by the supremum.
So instead of the norm, we
can just write supremum
over x in D.
And then we just look at
the absolute value of the
value of the functions.
In other words, we just put
in x at the correct
positions.
And then in the next step
we can simply substitute
s with the limit
definition.
This means instead of the
infinity symbol here we can
just write limit of
the partial sums.
So maybe let's use a number
m that goes to
infinity.
And now we can simply use
that the absolute value is
a continuous function, which
means we can pull out the
limit.
So it's not a problem at
all to write the limit in
front of the absolute value.
And then you should see inside
the absolute value.
It looks much simpler.
Now we just subtract
finite sums so we know
a finite sum remains.
However, maybe it's not clear
how to write this sum because
we don't know if m or n is
bigger.
But obviously in the case
that m is bigger than n,
we would say that k goes
from n plus one to
m.
And of course, in the second
case, we would just write
it the other way around.
It does not change so much,
because we know that for
both cases, if n and
m are bigger than the capital
N, then this whole
sum is less than
epsilon.
This is simply the cauchy
criterion we have at
every point x.
Hence, the conclusion is,
even with the limit and with
the supremum, we stay lower
epsilon.
The only thing we can lose
here is the strict
inequality.
But obviously, this does
not change anything, because
epsilon was arbitrarily chosen
from the beginning.
And with that, we have it.
This means that in the limit
n to infinity, this
norm here goes to zero.
And since we have the supremum
norm, this is exactly the
uniform convergence.
Therefore, this is already
the whole proof.
And then I would say, let's
look at a nice application
of this Weierstrass m
test.
So let's take an example
of a series with a function
inside.
And if you know something
about Fourier series, you
might recognize that this
one here is an important
one.
So let's take f k from
R to R, where f
k of x is
given as the cosine
of kx
over k squared.
So this is our function depending
on k.
And now we can look at the
absolute value,
and we know that the cosine
is bounded by one.
So this is definitely less
or equal than one over k
squared.
And this holds for every
x in R.
And now you only have to
know that the series of one
over k squared is
convergent to apply the
Weierstrass M test.
And there are different possibilities
to show this, but it's
definitely not too complicated.
And a basic result you definitely
should remember.
And indeed, we can immediately
make use of that with the
Weierstrass M test.
Our conclusion is that this
series of functions is
uniformly convergent.
And indeed, this is really
helpful as a result.
For example, when you want
to calculate the derivative
of this function and
something like that, you
can find in my Fourier
transform series.
In fact, exactly.
This result here plays a
crucial role there.
Okay, then, I think this
is good enough for this video,
and I really hope I meet
you in another one.
So, have a nice day, and
bye bye.