Hello and welcome to Manifolds, a video series
I started for everyone who wants to learn how
to use calculus on surfaces and related topics.
However, before we start I really want to thank
all the nice people who support this channel
on Steady, via Paypal, or by other means.
Now, in part 1 of the course, I give you a short
overview and explain the definition of a topology.
So let's start with a quick explanation what we
will discuss in this course. First, as I've already
mentioned, the notion of a manifold generalizes the
concept of a surface in space. Such a surface we
could visualize like this but the most popular
one would be the two-dimensional sphere.
So this is the boundary of the ball and often called
S^2.  The 2 stands for the two dimensions we have
when we just live on the surface. Now you might
already know some important applications where
it is needed to calculate on the sphere. Especially
in physics, it happens that some constraints force
the motion to happen on the surface. Then questions
like finding a minimum or a maximum of a function
are completely different because we can't
use our calculus for open domains anymore.
Therefore the overall question here will
be how to extend our calculation rules for
surfaces and indeed abstract manifolds. In order
to do this we first have to understand what the
fundamentals of such a surface are. So we start
with a quick overview of the field of topology.
Afterwards we will be able to define
differentiable manifolds as our subject of
study. So you see the notion of differentiability
will be a crucial point in this course. Then next
for these differentiable manifolds we will be able
to define so-called differential forms. At first
glance these differential forms might look strange
because they are just given by one part of an
integral like dx or d omega. However we will
define these objects in a rigorous way and indeed,
in the end, also integrals with these differential
forms will make sense. Okay now the overall goal
I have in mind for this course here is that we
will reach the generalized Stokes's theorem. Indeed
this theorem will nicely form a connection between
a manifold and its boundary by using differential
form. So this is the overview of the course and
i think we are ready to start with the first part
and talk about topology. Now if you already have
a good knowledge of metric spaces you can use
this as a starting point. Indeed a lot of notions
we have in topology are already formulated
in metric spaces. Here please recall: a metric
space needs a set X and a distance function d.
This means when we have to set X we can
measure distances between two points in X
for example here x and y have a
distance given by a positive real number
and this one is denoted by d(x,y). Now in the
case you see this the first time you can watch
the first videos in my functional analysis
course to get familiar with metric spaces
however the important thing here is that you
know how we can define open sets usually this
works when we take so called open epsilon
balls. This means that B_epsilon(x) is a ball
with radius epsilon and middle point x. Now by
using these epsilon balls we can say if a subset
in the metric space is open. Hence here the notion
"open" for a subset depends on the chosen metric d.
But then we can show that the collection of
all open sets fulfills some nice properties.
For example if we take two open sets the intersection
is always also an open set with such properties
in mind we see that for a lot of things we
do not need an explicit measure of distance
just some neighborhood relation between the points
might be sufficient so roughly speaking we just
need to know which points are neighbors of x are
close to x without measuring the explicit distance
indeed the abstraction of
this idea leads to topology
hence we just list all the sets that should be
open and then we deduce everything from them
most importantly in this definition
we don't need a metric anymore
however of course we still have a set X then what
we need is the collection of all subsets of X
which we call the power set of X and denote
by P(X) therefore to say which sets are open
we just have to take a subset of the power
set and this one is denoted by a curved T
in other words this T just stands for a collection
of subsets of X now these subsets should be the
open sets therefore they have to fulfill all the
rules like in the metric space indeed we will
fix three important properties here now the first
one is very simple we just say that the empty set
and the whole space X are open sets. More
precisely they are elements of the collection T
then the second property I already
mentioned. If we take two open sets A and B
then this implies that the intersection is also
an open set finally the third and last property
looks similarly but now for the union however you
might know in a metric space with the union and
open sets we can do a lot. What I mean is it does
not matter how many open sets are in the union
the result is always an open set as well hence
here we can look at the whole family of open sets
so we look at A_i where i goes through any
fixed index set capital I and of course
any subset in the family is an element of
t and then this implies that we can look at
the big union i in i of the sets A_i and we
conclude this union is also an element in T
okay and there you see we condense the
properties of open sets for a metric space
into a new definition. Indeed with this definition
we can work and we don't need a metric anymore
what we now have is a collection of subsets T
and we call it a topology on X and I already
mentioned it a lot the elements of a topology are
called open sets therefore please always remember
in the topology the property open is given by
definition and therefore open only makes sense
with respect to a chosen topology. OK, I think it
will be very helpful when we look at some examples
therefore let's start with the easiest examples so
the question is what is the simplest choice for T
such that all the rules are fulfilled. Of
course in order to satisfy the first rule
we need at least the empty set and X involved
however if we leave it at that we already have
a topology so what you should see is the second
and the third property are immediately satisfied
simply because there are not many choices
for the intersection and the union
hence this means that this is the topology
where all the non-trivial subsets are not open
so maybe not the most interesting topology
to work with ok now you might already know
we can also do the other extreme which means we
have the topology where all the subsets are open
of course the power set of X is a topology
on X because there's no way to violate one
of these rules the power set just contains
all the subsets and now in this topology all
these subsets are open sets, therefore
we often call it the discrete topology.
On the other hand the first example is often
called the indiscrete topology. Of course both
examples are not the most interesting topologies
but they are edge cases you should always have
in mind. Okay maybe that's good enough for the
introduction today. Let's continue in the next
video while working with the open sets. Therefore
I hope I see you there and have a nice day. Bye!