Hello and welcome back to
manifolds.
And before we start, I want
to thank all the nice people
who support this channel
and Steady via paypal or by
other means.
Now, in today's part two,
we continue talking about
the topic of topology,
namely, we introduce notions
like interior, closure
and related stuff
for this
Please recall that the
topology on a set X is a
collection of subsets that
satisfies three rules.
First, the smallest and the
largest subset have to be
involved.
Secondly, you cannot leave
the topology by finitely many
intersections.
And thirdly, you also cannot
leave it with any unions.
So these are the three properties
of a topology T and you
also should remember that
the elements of T are called
open sets.
Moreover, the set X
together with a chosen topology
is called a topological
space.
Hence, it's a space where
the notion of open sets makes
sense.
Of course, we will also discuss
examples of topological
spaces here.
However, before we do this,
we first need more
definitions.
Indeed, in a topological
space points in X
can have special names.
Therefore, here let's fix
a topological space
(X,T) and a
subset S in X
here, please note S could
be an element of the topology
but it does not have to be
OK.
We want to talk about names
for points.
So let's fix the point P
in X.
Now all the names we give
for P are to be read with
respect to the fix set
S.
Therefore, our visualization
should look like this.
We have the whole space X
and inside we have the
subset S
then one possibility for
P is that P is an
element of S.
Of course, this alone is
not so interesting, but we
could have even more.
And then we talk of an interior
point of S.
So what this exactly means
we can now define
indeed what we need is an
open set and maybe let's
call it U here.
Now this open set should
contain the point P and it
should also lie completely
inside the set S
and if we have these two
properties, we call P
an interior point of S.
So you see the crucial thing
here is that we find a suitable
open set from the topology
T OK.
Now, it might not surprise
you when we have interior
points of S, we also
have exterior points of S.
Of course, the name
suggests in our picture
here, the point P should
lie outside of S.
However, as before we
want to lie outside,
even with an open set U.
So visually speaking, we
want some distance in both
cases from the boundary of
S.
Hence, we need an open set
U such that there's no
overlap with S.
Therefore, this exactly means
that P is an interior
point of the complement of
S or with the same
formula as before we find
an open set U such that
P is an element of U
and U is a subset of X
without S
OK.
Now we have two important
terms here.
And you see in our picture,
we have described all the
points inside the set S
and all outside of S.
Therefore, the points missing
are the ones on the boundary
of S.
For this reason, we could
define P to be a boundary
point of S if it's
neither an interior point
nor an exterior point.
However, of course, we can
also immediately describe
this with opens set
U. It
simply means that no matter
which opens set you, we choose,
we always have an overlap
with S and the complement
of S.
Hence, we can write for all
open sets U with the
property that P is an element
of U.
We have U
intersected with S is non-
empty and U
intersected with X without
S is also non-empty.
Then such a point P with
this property, we call a
boundary point of S.
OK.
Now, you might think that
we have all the names, but
I still want to include a
last one.
Indeed, this one is often
important when we want to
deal with limits and it's
called accumulation point
of the set S.
And it simply means that
the point P is not
isolated from the rest of
the set S.
Hence, as before, we can
describe this, when we look
at all open sets U that
contain the point P
and then we want that something
from the set S remains.
Or in other words, the intersection
with the set S should not
be the empty set
Here,
the crucial thing is that
this works no matter which
open set U around P
we choose.
For this reason, you immediately
see an exterior point
can never be an accumulation
point.
OK.
So here we have four important
names for points that are
defined with respect to a
chosen subset
S.
Therefore, I would say please
remember them.
However, now we're having
these names for points, we
are also able to define
names for sets.
But don't worry, these are
not complicated anymore.
For example, for the set
S, we can define
S circle.
This one is simply the collection
of all points P in X
that fulfill that P is an
interior point of S.
Therefore, S circle is
called the interior of
S.
So the interior is defined
for a subset and it gives
us a new subset.
And now it might not surprise
you that we can do a similar
thing for all the other points
here.
Hence, the next thing will
be the exterior of S
However, there, we don't
have a special symbol.
We just write Ext of
S, then we
collect all the exterior
points of S and call this
set the exterior of
S. OK.
The next important subset
will be the boundary of S.
Indeed, this one is denoted
with a curved lowercase
d.
It's the same symbol we would
also use for partial
derivatives.
However, here, dS denotes
a whole set namely the
one with all the boundary
points of S.
And not so surprising, this
one is called the boundary
of S.
Hence, only one set
remains the one about the
accumulation points.
And for this one, we have
a rather strange notation,
we call it S prime.
Therefore, for a set, the
line in the upper index means
that we have all the accumulation
points in the set.
In fact, one often calls
this the derivative of the
set S.
Another term we will use
here is that this is the
derived set of S.
Now I would say what you
should see here is that we
have a lot of labels, you
should know when doing
topology.
Actually, there are even
more than just the four I
showed you here.
And the last one I really
need to show you.
Now, it's an
important one.
It's called the closure of
S.
And you see it has a nice
notation, we just overline
the set.
Now, the definition is not
so complicated, we just take
the original set S and then
take the union with the
boundary and
then the set is what we call
the closure of S.
So I already told you this
is the last definition I
want to show you today
at this point.
I really think it's helpful
to look at an example.
So let's take an example
of a topology which is not
so common.
However, the set X can be
very common.
So let's take the real number
line.
On the other hand, T should
not be the standard topology.
So let's define it in the
following way.
First, we already know the
empty set and the real number
line should be included in
the topology.
However, all the other
open sets should be half-
bounded intervals.
Therefore, each non-trivial
open set is such an
interval that starts with
a real number a and goes
to infinity
here.
Please note it's important
that the left boundary a
here is not included in the
interval.
Now, it's a good exercise
for you to check that all
the three rules of a topology
are fulfilled here.
Then with this knowledge,
we can take a subset S and
look at the sets we defined
above.
In fact, the subset si have
in mind is the interval
0 to 1.
Also here, the zero and
one are not included in the
set.
Now, the first thing we can
note here is that this set
is not open.
So maybe you find it strange
to say this.
But you immediately see this
set is not included in our
collection of open sets.
It's simply not such an interval
here.
Therefore, the next thing
we can see here is that S
has no interior points at
all.
This is simply because we
don't find any non-
empty open subset that
lies inside the set.
S. Here,
Please recall, we need at
least one such U with
this property to have
interior points.
In other words, we can't
fit an unbounded interval
into this interval here.
And therefore, the interior
of S is the empty set.
OK.
Now you might ask, what can
we say about the exterior
points?
And there, you know, we have
to look at X without
S.
So the complement of S which
is simply the interval for
minus infinity
to zero and then the
union of the interval
from one to infinity.
So there you see this is
better for this set.
We find open sets that
are contained in this one
more concretely, this works
for all points except
one here in the second part.
Therefore, the exterior of
S is simply the
interval from one to
infinity.
OK.
Now, with the knowledge of
these two sets, we
immediately know all the
boundary points of S
there.
Please recall these are all
the points in X that are
neither in the interior of
S nor in the exterior
of S.
Hence, it's the interval
from minus infinity to
one including the
point 1.
Again, this might look
strange, but it is simply
because our topology is
chosen in this way,
all open sets stretch from
one point to plus
infinity.
So they can't see what happens
in the other direction to
minus infinity.
And therefore we have the
conclusion that the boundary
of this set is everything
on the left hand side.
OK.
And in order to close this
example here, now we can
also say that the closure
of S is exactly the same
set.
So you see this here is a
nice example in order to
get used to topologies
and please never forget all
the notions we have here
always depend on the chosen
topology.
Then I would say let's go
deeper into the field with
the next videos.
Therefore, I hope I see you
there and have a nice day.
Bye.