hello and welcome to start learning sets
a video course where I give you a quick
introduction into set theory
however first many many thanks to all
the nice people on Steady or PayPal who
make these videos possible now for
learning mathematics set theory is so
important because you can describe
everything in mathematics using just
sets indeed you could see the field of
logic together with the set theory as
the foundation of mathematics
this works as follows in the language of
logic we describe the axioms we want the
axioms of set theory this means that we
have a list of propositions assumed to
be true
then that's our starting point we have
to start somewhere we have to put
something in first
and all the things we logically get out
form our world of mathematics
in this way we then reach our goal we
can do mathematics
however this path is way too long and
needs a lot of time such that you should
never do that at the beginning of your
mathematical career thankfully there is
a very nice shortcut that works so good
that you can do a lot of mathematics
without bothering about the axioms on
this path we just learned a little bit
of propositional logic and something we
call naive set theory okay the name
seems a little bit strange we will just
call it set theory and indeed the only
difference is that we don't write down
all the axioms
with this and the propositional logic we
learned in the last videos we can go to
doing mathematics
Now by having this picture in mind let's
go to the start of set theory
so let's start by saying what
a set is.
one often says a set is just a
collection of distinct objects into a
whole. So the idea would be if we have
some objects
for example here four different objects
then the set puts them all together into
a collection
there see this is not a correct
definition it's just the idea we have in
mind written down
hence it means that by putting the
objects together we get out a new thing
we could call here the set M so what
makes the set M are the objects so we
have a natural relation between the
objects and the set
now in order to make everything easier
we call such an object x inside a set M
just an element of M
or even better we use a short formula
for this
so we use this special e for element and
read it as X in m
so for the example on the right hand
side we would write the circle with A is
an element of M
moreover If x is not such an object of
the collection we write a similar thing
x is not an element in M
there we would use the line through the
e
now on the right hand side for the
example we would write this D is not an
element in M
now at this point because you know some
logic I can say that this new notation
is just a short notation for the
negation of this statement
there you have it we see the element
relations as logical statements
and because a set is defined by these
element relations we can just define a
set by giving all the elements
for this one usually uses the curly
brackets as we did before
so this is a set that has the number two
the number 5 and the number 6 as elements
so inside the curly brackets we have a
list of all the elements and please note
the order does not matter because we
only need the element relation so
there's no order inside the set
now another useful notation we can
introduce now is when I want to give the
set a new name for example A. Then I
would write colon equality
and we would read that the left hand
side is defined by the right hand side
so it's an assignment which should
remind you that the new name a new
variable is introduced at this point
okay now before we go into the details
of set theory I first want to show you
some examples of sets that we use later
the first one is the empty set which is
the unique set that has no elements at all
and the notation we use is just a circle
with a line through it
however other people just use the empty
curly brackets
now the following number sets we will
define later correctly but here I can
already show you the symbols we use for
them
for the natural numbers starting with 1
we use the N as a symbol
and for the natural numbers including 0
I use the same N with an index 0. Ff we
include the negative numbers as well we
call them the integers and denote them
by capital Z
in later videos we will properly define
these sets but for the moment it's a
good thing that we have the number sets
such that we can write down some
examples
therefore I assume that you already know
at least some things about natural
numbers
now later when we are ready for it we
can also Define the rational numbers
denoted by Q the real numbers denoted by
R and the complex numbers denoted by C
okay now the natural question for you
would be how can we define sets without
writing down all the elements
for example for the natural numbers you
already see the problem with this
approach
now in order to efficiently do this we
have to go back to logic and talk about
quantifiers and predicates
indeed I already mentioned what a predicate
is it's something with a variable
for example x and it becomes a logical
statement if we set a value for x
therefore x in N would be a nice
example of a predicate
and quantifiers are just reversed
letters A and E and we will talk about
them in the next video
okay I hope I see you there and have a
nice day bye
[Music]