Hello and welcome! First I want to thank all the
nice people that support this channel on Steady (tbsom.de/s/support)!
Today I want to show you the LU decomposition
for a square matrix. This means that we rewrite
our matrix as a product of two matrices, where on
the one side we have a lower triangular matrix L
and on the other side we have an upper triangular
matrix U. Now in this video I want to show you the
algorithm with the help of one example. I choose
a  4x4-matrix and I call it A. Here you
see this looks like a nice example. However it's
not a trivial one. Now I can immediately tell you
that doing the LU decomposition is basically just
an expanded Gaussian elimination. Therefore please
remember you can do the Gaussian elimination
by just using row operations. And what you get
out is an upper triangular matrix in the end and
this is exactly the U in our LU decomposition.
At this point I can give you a warning: we will not
use row exchanges in this example here. Indeed
it's essential for the LU decomposition that
you don't use row exchanges while applying the
algorithm. This means that if you have a matrix
where you really need row exchanges in the
Gaussian elimination, then you should apply these
all beforehand and then just use the algorithm
I now show you. Okay, then I would say we start with
our nice example here. The first step is always
to include an identity matrix with the right size.
Here it would be 4x4-matrix, so I use 1, 1,
1, 1 on the diagonal and the rest are zeros. And
on the right hand side I just copy my matrix from
before. Obviously, the equality still holds because
we just multiply with the identity matrix.
And now we see: we almost have our LU decomposition here.
We will transform the identity matrix into a
lower triangular matrix, so we will fill in numbers
here but not here, and we will transform this one
to an upper triangular matrix.
This means that we now just use the normal Gaussian elimination on
the right, but now we also memorize all the steps
with the help of the matrix on the left.
Okay, you will see a immediately how this works with the first step.
Okay so I copied the first row because we
won't change it but we will change all the other
rows.
Now in the first Gaussian elimination step we
use this number as a pivot and we want to generate zeros below it.
Therefore to get a 0 here in the
second row we have to use two times the first row.
Hence we can write this as: use the second
row minus (-2) times the first row.
Of course, we could rewrite this as plus 2 times the first
row but for the LU decomposition is always helpful  to use a minus sign here.
This means that we always
subtract multiples of another row.
This is very helpful because this number here we subtract is
the number we will put in the matrix L.
Where to put it is very easy because here we generated a 0.
And at the exact same position we put the
new number in the matrix L. And in the same way,
it works for all other positions here.
Now with the matrix multiplication you see that this is
indeed the correct sign we chose because if you
multiply 2 with (-2) here you get out
indeed -4 as we want.
However still we have to do our calculation here so we do our
Gaussian elimination step which means we have the 0 here as wanted; here we have 1; here we have
also 1; and there we have 2.
OK, now we can do
the same thing for the third row which means we
take the third row and we have to subtract a
multiple of the first row, which is here just
3 times the first row.
OK, now you know the
multiple we subtract, so 3 is the number we
put at the right position here. And of course
we also have to do the calculation which is 0
here, minus 4, minus 7, and minus 6 here.
Again we can
check that our sign was correct: so if you multiply
this column with this row, we get out 2 times 3,
so our 6. And finally we can do the whole thing
for the last row. So I take the fourth row and I
look at the multiple of the row I have
to subtract. And here it is 2 times the first row.
And now you already know we have to put this
2 into our matrix L. And also the calculation
in last row is not so hard: we have the 0 here,
here we have 8, so 1 remains, and here we have
minus 8, and there 4.
Well now we are finished
with our first column because everything is 0 here.
Now we go to our next column, so the second
column, which means this is our new pivot.
So the procedure would be exactly the same, we now just
produce the zeros here.
OK, in order to do this,
let's start a new line. So let's copy everything
and then do the same Gaussian elimination as
before. We can copy the first two rows because
we won't change them anymore. The first step is
of course to generate a 0 here, which means that
we take the third row and use the second row to
change it. Now you see we have to add 4 times the
second row to get a 0 here; and therefore we write
it as subtracting minus 4 times the second row.
And now this multiple is the number we put here at the right position: minus 4.
And our calculation
in the third row gives us here 0, 0.
Here we have 4 and minus 7 so minus 3, and here we have 2.
So let's to the next step which means generate
a zero here. So take the fourth row and subtract
the second row, so minus 1 times the second row.
And again this one is the thing we put here in our
matrix L. And the last calculation here is very
easy: we just have 0, 0, -9, and 2.
Okay very good, so now you see we just need one
last step in our Gaussian elimination. So let's
do that very quickly now. Well, I copied everything
again except the last row because this is the only
one we change now. And you immediately see what
we need we just have to change the 4th row
by subtracting 3 times the third row. And
as before the number we subtract is the number
we put in here. Then we just have to zeros here and (-4) here.
And there you have it that's our
LU decomposition. On the left we have our lower
triangular matrix, which we call L, and we want
to choose it with only 1s on the diagonal. And
you see that is exactly what we get out with this
algorithm. And on the right hand side you see this
is our upper triangular matrix U. There on the
diagonal everything can happen. Now please recall that you get U by just using Gaussian elimination
and L by saving all these steps in the Gaussian
elimination. Therefore the matrix multiplication
here gives us, in fact, our original matrix back.
However just in the case that we don't need to
use row exchanges in the Gaussian elimination. How to deal with this and how to generalize the whole
concept here, I can show you in another video.
For now, I hope this example really helped you such
that you now can calculate an LU decomposition
of a matrix. And then: see you next time! Bye!