Hello and welcome to
start learning complex
numbers, a video course where
I introduce you to the field
of complex numbers.
So I want to show you how
we can construct these numbers
and how we can calculate
with them.
However, before we do that,
I first want to thank all
the nice people that support
this channel on Steady or
paypal.
Now, the starting point for
the complex numbers is the
real number line R
there.
You should know we find all
integers on the number line,
all fractions but also
irrational numbers like the
square root of two.
Moreover, we also know that
we have two operations, the
addition and the multiplication
and we know that they fulfill
a lot of rules such that
we call R a field.
Then we also have an ordering
so we can compare two numbers
and this ordering also
satisfies some rules.
Finally, the last
property is the completeness
which tells us that there
are no holes on this number
line.
OK.
Then let's discuss what one
can do with these real numbers
here.
For example, we can say
that we are able to solve
a lot of equations
solving X plus five
is equal to one is no
problem at all.
In the same way, we can also
solve X times five
is equal to one.
So here you can see we can
use the property that we
have a field.
Then another equation we
solved is X squared is
equal to two.
This one leads to the square
of two which is in R
by completeness.
However, this does not mean
that we are able to solve
any quadratic equation.
For example, the quadratic
equation X squared is
equal to minus one
has no solutions.
This is not hard to see because
you can show that any
square in the real numbers
is greater or equal than
zero.
And we also need that minus
one is less than
zero.
Here, I can tell you if you
just work with the axioms
of the real numbers, it's
a good exercise to show
both of these things.
Then this implies that this
simple equation does not
have any solution.
However, for us, it makes
sense that we extend our
numbers such that this
equation has solutions.
The first thing you should
note here is that X squared
is nothing else than X
times X.
I say that because the same
equation with the addition
is solvable.
So surprisingly, the
addition and the multiplication
act differently in R
which also has something
to do with the ordering.
Hence, our idea is to
expand the number set such
that we can solve such equations.
Here.
But we already know that
we can't conserve all the
properties in R in
order to see what we can
do.
Let's look at the number
line again.
First, let's fill in the
number 02
and four.
Now, you know, we can go
from 2 to 4 just by
using multiplication, we
simply multiply by two.
However, the interesting
thing is now that we can
split this big jump
into small jumps,
we just multiply by a number
that is a little bit bigger
than one.
You see the smaller the one
jump is the more jumps we
need.
OK.
The splitting up does not
work when we want to jump
to minus two.
For this big jump, we have
to multiply by minus
one.
Also interesting here, if
we multiply again by minus
one, we get back to
two.
So here you see multiplying
with a negative number is
different than multiplying
with a positive number
because in the first case,
we immediately change the
side of the number line.
Now looking back to the splitting
of the jump for positive
numbers here, we can see
the equation from above
because doing two jumps
with the number X means
we have X squared is
equal to two.
So exactly this equation
where we know we have a solution.
Now you might see the problem.
How can we split up this
jump into two parts?
By looking at this picture,
you might already see we
could just add another
direction for the numbers.
Therefore, the idea is that
we also include a Y
axis.
Now here
jumping from one to
minus one is still
given by multiplying with
minus one.
However, now we are able
to split it up into smaller
parts, for
example, into two parts where
we multiply with the number
X.
And there you see this is
our equation from before
X squared is equal to
minus one.
Hence you see the number
we search for is this
point in the plane.
So we need a new name for
this number.
We call it I.
Now with our picture in mind
this I is now a special
number because when we
multiply I with
itself, we get out the
jump minus one or
to put it.
In other words, I
squared is equal to
minus one.
And this is now the important
formula we should remember
all the time.
OK.
With all this, we have some
idea what our goal is to
expand the number set.
And how we can reach that
goal extending the
number line into a second
direction is of course a
completely new idea.
Therefore, we really have
to do this in a formal way,
what we can do in the next
video in this way.
I hope I see you there and
have a nice day.
Bye.