Hello and welcome to
start learning numbers, a
video course where we will
discuss all the different
sets of numbers starting
with the natural numbers
and going all the way until
we reach the complex numbers.
But first, I want to thank
all the nice people that
made this course possible
by supporting me on Steady
and paypal.
When you first see mathematics,
you often see that mathematics
starts with calculations,
calculations with numbers.
And the numbers start with
the natural numbers,
they are called natural numbers
because they are an
abstraction we can immediately
see in our natural world.
In fact, even as Children,
we already get the conception
for counting things
and the abstraction or
generalization that comes
from counting different objects
is what leads us to the natural
numbers.
So they just represent different
sizes we can have for collections
of some objects.
Therefore, it makes sense
to introduce new symbols
for these representations.
Now please keep in mind for
the mathematics we will explore,
it does not matter which
name we give these numbers.
But the actual concept of
numbers is important with
this, you could say the natural
numbers we want to consider
is the set N that consists
of all of these new symbols.
However, if you watch my
explanations for the set
theory, you already know
that this here is not a
complete definition for a
set.
Therefore, the question would
be how do we define the
natural numbers just with
sets?
This is what we'll answer
in this video.
More precisely, we will
construct the natural numbers
that also include zero as
a number.
I will use the symbol N zero
for this set but be careful
often.
Also N is used for this
set here.
OK.
With this, let's start
constructing the natural
numbers.
As we have seen in our examples
with apples and oranges.
The size of a set can be
used to define a number
and we already know one particular
set, namely the empty
set by definition,
the empty set does not have
any elements.
So it represents the number
zero.
And now it makes sense to
use this as a definition
for our new symbol zero.
Maybe it looks a little bit
strange here.
But keep in mind we already
have the set theory.
So it makes sense that every
new object we introduce should
also be a set.
We did the same thing when
we introduced ordered pairs
and maps.
Now for the next step for
defining the number one as
a set, we need a new
set that contains only one
element we could take
any element we want.
But the only thing that is
defined yet is the empty set.
So we put zero inside the
set brackets and we get out
a new set.
What you should see is that
what we do here is exactly
the same thing we had in
mind when we dealt with the
oranges.
However, here we don't need
any real world objects.
We just need the abstract
concepts in set theory.
OK.
Now, for the number two,
we need two elements.
So what do we do?
We take the only two elements
we know.
So zero and one,
because we know they are
different at this point,
you should see how this game
works and we can just continue
it.
Therefore, this is our number
three as a set in the same
way, we can write down the
number four.
However, here you might already
wish for a shorter way to
write it down.
And of course, if you compare
to the set before three,
we just add one element.
For this reason, we can just
write it as a union.
So this is what it is and
maybe it looks again a little
bit strange, but keep in
mind three is a set
here.
And here we have the set
that contains three as an
element.
OK?
But with this formula, you
now know how to construct
the next number in order.
And then we get all the
numbers we want to have.
And after that, we want to
put them into one set
and call it the natural numbers
and zero.
However, there you might
see a problem because this
whole construction here never
stops.
Or to put it.
In other words, the natural
numbers, the set and zero
should have infinitely many
elements.
And that is something we
have to put into our set
theory.
So we call it an axiom.
It's simply something we
put as a true statement
into our theory.
For example, the existence
of the empty set was also
an axiom.
We put into the set theory.
And now we want to put in
the existence of the natural
numbers.
So we say there's a set N
zero with the following two
properties.
The first one is that we
have a starting point at
zero.
So the set zero
lies in N zero.
And the second one tells
us that for all numbers in
N zero, also the
successor lies in N zero.
And now we know we can write
it as this set here
as a reminder here, we have
the conditional form logic.
And I already told you sometimes
it's written with a double
arrow later, we will
also do this just to avoid
confusion with the arrow
for maps.
However, to finish our axiom
here, we also have to say
that N zero is the
smallest set that has
these properties.
This simply means that any
other set with these two
properties is a superset
of N zero.
OK.
And with this, we finally
have the natural numbers.
In our set theory,
it's constructed with sets,
it has sets as elements
such that we can work with
it.
That's how you should see
It's not the explanation
of numbers.
It's a working tool for us.
Therefore, it's often called
a model for the natural numbers.
Now, with the natural numbers,
we immediately get a map,
we call the successor map,
we denote it with S and it
goes from N zero into
N zero.
And the definition, we already
know we send the number X
to the union
because we learned this gives
us the successor.
For example, if we put the
number six into the map,
we get out the number seven.
OK?
I think that's good enough
for an introduction.
In the next video, we will
talk about all the properties
of the natural numbers and
also how we can define the
addition.
So I hope I see you there
and have a nice day.
Bye.