Hello and welcome back to the video series about ODEs.
So you see we are still in the beginning of the topic and in today's part 2 we will first define the important notions we need.
So for example we will give the definition what we mean by an ODE.
However, before we do that I first want to thank all the nice people who support this channel on Steady, via Paypal or by other means
and please don't forget, in the description you find the link, where you can download the PDF version and a quiz for this video.
Ok, then without further ado let's start with the important definitions we will need in this series.
First of all we will often deal with a set of functions called C^k
and usually the domain of definition for these functions is given by an interval "I".
Hence when you see capital "I" it's always a subset of the real number line.
Now in fact most of the time in this series it will denote an interval, but sometimes it will denote a general open set
and in some other cases we might want that "I" stands for a union of 2 intervals.
So you see, depending on what we want to do later, we will stretch this definition a little bit,
but here we will start with an interval "I"
and then this set C^k is well-defined as a set of functions
and here we immediately see the first special feature of this topic, because we will denote functions by a lower case x.
Hence x is a function, where the domain of definition is "I"
and it simply maps into the real number line
and now you should recall from real analysis that C^k means that the function x is k-times continuously differentiable.
This means the kth order derivative of x exists and is a continuous function.
Moreover I should tell you here that the variable name we want to use for the function x is usually a lower case t.
This means we will write x(t).
I tell you that, because if we choose the variable name as t, we will use a dot for denoting derivatives.
Hence the first derivative here would be the function x dot.
Then the second derivative would be x dot dot
and so on and of course if we need too many dots, we will use the common upper index notation.
Of course in situations where the dot could be confusing, we will just use other notations.
So for example you know the common prime notation or the Leibniz notation.
So please keep that in mind. Depending on the context or depending on which book you read,
you will see different notations for the derivative.
However the definition for an ODE should be the same.
Namely it should be given by a combination of the derivatives of the function x.
Indeed, we could write it down by a functional relation.
For that we take a continuous function capital F
and then we have different inputs. First of all the independent variable t
and then the function x and the derivatives of x up to some order.
So as before we could say that the highest derivative is the kth order.
Ok and now this function with all the inputs should be equal to 0.
Ok, so you see in general this is what we mean when we talk of an ODE of order k
and maybe let's immediately look at an example for such an equation.
So we could have t + x + 2xdot + second derivative of x squared
and then this should be equal to 0.
So there you see, this is a well defined ODE of second order.
So the highest derivative that occurs in the equation gives us the order
and at this point you might say, it might be easier for us if we first start with first order differential equations.
In fact soon we will see why it's very helpful to start with the first order differential equations.
Ok, but now it's helpful for the next definitions to abbreviate the term ordinary differential equation.
From now on we will simply write ODE if we need to keep it short and compact.
Therefore in the next definition we will explain explicit ODEs of order 1.
Here explicit means that the derivative we are interested in is on the one side of the equation
and all the other terms like the function x and the variable t are on the other side
and both things we can rewrite with a function w.
Hence w gets 2 inputs, t and x.
Moreover we would say w is a function defined on 2 intervals.
So we have the interval "I" for t and the interval J for x
and in this case here both are simply intervals from the real number line.
Ok, so in summary you see here, this one is a special case of our general case from above.
However it's the common one we will examine.
That's because the 2 restrictions we have here are actually not big restrictions.
Indeed we will discuss soon why this case here is very general,
but first I would say let's look at an example of an explicit ODE of order 1.
Hence we already know, on the left-hand side we need to have x dot
and now on the right-hand side for example we could have x + t
So you see, the function w doesn't have to be very complicated.
In fact here the domain of definition is simply R^2.
Ok, but at this point you might remember what we have discussed in the last video.
There we had examples where more than 1 variable were involved.
Therefore we might ask: "is there also an example here for an explicit ODE of order 1?"
So you could write x_1 dot, the first variable for x is equal to the second variable x_2 + t
and then we could have a similar equation for x_2 dot.
Now this one could be x_1 + t.
Now, important to note here is, these are not just 2 individual ODEs of order 1.
Otherwise it would not be allowed to mix the variables in this way.
However we can just put them together and call it a system of ODEs
and in fact a system of ODEs looks exactly the same again.
We simply have to write it as a vector equation.
So the derivative of the vector x_1, x_2 is equal to a vector given by the right-hand side here
and of course this one can be expressed again by a function w.
So w gets again 2 inputs, but now the second input is a vector instead of the variable x
and then you should see, if we call the vector (x_1, x_2) simply x again, it has the same form as before.
In other words now we are able to define the term system of ODEs.
More precisely you would say we have an n-dimensional system of explicit ODEs of order 1,
but you might already know in the end we will also just say ODE for such a system.
Simply because from the form, from the looks it's the same as our original definition.
However don't forget, the value x(t) is now a vector.
More precisely we would say it's a n-dimensional vector.
So in other words our system now could have n equations here.
Hence the function w now also maps into R^n.
Moreover the domain of definition also changes for the second variable.
Usually we would say we have U there, which is an open set in R^n,
but as we said at the beginning also that changes a little bit depending which problem we consider.
Ok, but for the moment I would say we have a very nice definition for what we mean when we say ODE.
So this is a very general construct, but you see one important ingredient is still missing here.
So now we know what an ODE is, but we remember for applications we are always interested in solutions of this ODE.
So know the question is: what is a solution of a system of ODEs?
Of course it should be a function that is differentiable and can be put into the equation
and then it should fulfill the equation for all points t.
However there you already see, the domain of definition doesn't have to be the whole interval "I".
Indeed, it could be any subinterval which we can call t_0 to t_1.
So this is an open interval and now the solution function we can simply call alpha.
So alpha is defined on this interval and it maps into R^n.
More precisely it has to map into the subset U.
Simply because we want to put it into our function w in the second component and then it should be well-defined.
Ok, there we have it. Solution means it fulfills this equation here.
More concretely the derivative of alpha at the point t is equal to w(t, alpha(t)).
So there you see this is a well-defined equation of vectors and it should be fulfilled for all t in the interval.
So you see, now we can check this condition here pointwisely
and most importantly you should see the solution is always a differentiable function.
Ok, so we have a lot of definitions here. Therefore let's close the video now with a concrete example.
So this one should be very helpful to see what it really means to be a solution for an ODE
and for this let's look at a very simple system of ODEs.
x_1 dot should be equal to x_2 and x_2 dot should be equal to -x_1.
So you see this is a well-defined system for n=2
and moreover we don't have a problem with the domain of definition. U is simply R^2
and then the function w(t, x) is equal to x_2, -x_1.
So you see w does not explicitly depend on t,
but please don't forget t comes in again if you put in the solution alpha(t).
Ok, so now if you look at a system, maybe you immediately see a solution.
Indeed, I know sine and cosine functions fulfill something like that.
In fact alpha(t) = (sin(t), cos(t)) does the job.
Simply because we know the derivative of sine is the cosine and the derivative of the cosine is the -sine function.
Hence we immediately have a solution of this system of ODEs
and know what one can do is to sketch the solution as its image.
So we know the image of the solution lives in U, which is R^2 in this case
and now we can sketch what happens to alpha(t) when we start at t=0 and then increase t.
In fact you see what we get is a nice circle with radius 1.
.
Moreover now you can remember this image of the solution is called the orbit of the solution.
Indeed it's a dynamic picture that tells us what happens to the solution in the time variable t.
Moreover now you should also see that we easily find a second solution here.
Namely if we scale the vector by 1/2 and call the solution alpha tilde, then we see the ODE is also fulfilled
and there we get that the orbit is a circle with radius 1/2.
Hence our first result here is that a system of ODEs can have a lot of different solutions.
Therefore a question should also be: which solution gives us the correct picture?
Or more precisely maybe we want the solution that goes through some particular points
and there we immediately have the questions: Do we have a solution that goes through the points and if we have it, is it unique?
and exactly these questions we want to answer in this video course.
Therefore I hope that you are not scared off by all these definitions and come back to the next video.
There we will make more geometric pictures, such that you can understand the theory visually.
So I hope we meet again and have a nice day. Bye!