Hello and welcome back to the video series about ODEs
and in today's part 3 we will talk about the directional field.
This one will help us here at the beginning of this topic to visualize ODEs.
Indeed it's a vector field that can be sketched such that we understand the problem.
Ok, but before we start with that, you already know,
first I want to thank all the nice people who support this channel on Steady via Paypal or by other means.
In fact you should know only because of your support it's possible to create such videos about mathematics
and as a thank you and as a bonus you can download the PDF version and the quiz for this video.
Ok, then let's start by telling again what we mean by an ODE.
So you might remember if we write x dot (the first derivative of x) is equal to a function w, then we have an ODE.
Moreover this function w has the independent variable t as an input and x itself.
In addition you should know that x can be a vector. So we can have a whole system of ODEs.
However to be more precise you have already learned that an ODE of this form is called explicit and of first order.
This means that we only have the first derivative in the whole equation and the first derivative is also alone on the left-hand side.
However, I can already tell you that in the next video we will show that this is not really a restriction.
Indeed, we will see that we can simplify that even more without losing generality
and in order to see that let's first look at some examples here
and the first one here should be the ODE x dot is equal to lambda times x.
So a very common example, but what we should see here is that the function w doesn't depend on t.
Hence the independent variable, the time variable, does not occur in the equation.
Therefore we introduce a new name for such ODEs. They are called autonomous.
On the contrary we can immediately think of an example which is not autonomous.
Namely x dot is equal to t.
There the first variable t will change the value of the function w.
Hence this one is an ODE, but not an autonomous ODE
and of course this notion can also be used for a system of ODEs.
For example in 2-dimensions.
So here x dot is equal to (x_2, -x_1).
So you see, there is no t on the right-hand side here. Hence the whole system is also called autonomous.
Indeed, exactly these systems will be the interesting ones so let's consider them for the rest of the video
and of course we have to put this into a new definition.
In fact we want to keep it short and just call it an autonomous system.
So it means we have a system of ODEs and the function w on the right-hand side does not depend on t.
Therefore we can just write it as a function w only depending on x.
Moreover you know we have a whole system, so this can be a vector equation. Which means the function v maps R^n to R^n.
However in general you know v can have a domain so it maps U into R^n,
but of course U should then be a subset of R^n as well
and indeed often we will choose U as an open set.
Moreover I would also say that all the times you see that v is at least a continuous function defined on U.
Ok, but now the point is, such an autonomous system can be nicely visualized
and this is done by the so called directional field.
I would say this is easy to understand, because it's simply a plot of our function v.
So you could say this is a vector field which visualizes the function v.
Therefore you would start with the domain U. Which is a subset of R^n.
So for example it could be the whole R^2.
Hence here let's visualize an example where v maps R^2 into R^2.
So if you choose any point p in this coordinate system, the resulting value of v will also be a vector
and this vector we can simply visualize as an arrow starting at p.
Now, this is a common way to explain a vector function like v
and now of course the important fact here is that you could do it at any other point in this coordinate system
and then you simply have a picture with a lot of arrows.
However we now call it the directional field of the ODE, because it explains what solutions have to do.
Namely the ODE, the whole system of ODEs says that at a given point this vector is exactly the derivative of the solution.
Indeed this fits nicely in with the pictures of the orbits we had in the last video.
Please note, an orbit would be the image of a solution here in our domain.
However, now we know this can only be a solution of our system if at each point the vector we see is a tangent for this curve.
Simply because at each point the vectors here tell us in which direction the solution should flow.
In other words if we plot the directional field of this vector function v,
we can already see what the solutions can do and what they can't do.
Therefore this whole thing here is already very helpful to see the behaviour of possible solutions of the ODE,
but of course this whole procedure here, we should explain with examples
and first let's start with a 1-dimensional example.
So x dot should be equal to the sine of x.
So not too complicated, but we also realize that we don't see all the solutions immediately.
However we can recognize that v is defined on the whole real number line
and this means that our directional field is now just a 1-dimensional picture.
Hence for the arrows we want to draw in there are only 2 possible directions.
To see what happens here let's look at some important points like 0, pi/2, pi and so on.
Of course we choose exactly these numbers, because of the sine function.
So for example if we put pi/2 into our function v, we get out 1.
In other words we have an arrow of length 1 that points to the right.
On the other hand if we choose 3/2 times pi and put that into our function v, we get out -1. So an arrow that points to the left.
So you see this is what we could do for all points on the real number line and then we get the whole directional field.
So as another example if you choose a small, positive number here on the right of 0, we also get an arrow that points to the right.
However please note at the point 0 and the point pi, we simply get out 0.
This means at these points, there is no arrow pointing anywhere,
but exactly that is immediately an important information for the solutions.
So for example you could take a solution alpha(t) that is always 0.
So it means alpha(t) vanishes no matter which t you put in
and now we can simply check that this is indeed a solution.
This is not hard to do. You simply put alpha into the ODE.
So we want that alpha-dot(t) is equal to sin(alpha(t)).
So this is what a solution has to fulfill for all t and here we don't have a problem, because the derivative is 0 and sin(0) is also 0.
So here we simply have 0 = 0.
Now, this is important to remember. This always works if you find a point in the directional field that has no arrow at all
and therefore we can immediately give a second solution alpha(t).
We simply choose it as the constant function will value pi.
Indeed, with the same reasoning this is also a solution, because the derivative is 0 and sin(pi) is 0
and the important fact is that this claim holds for all t in R.
In other words you see here that we have solutions that stay with their orbit just on one point
and for this reason these points in the picture are called stationary points.
However the directional field does not only tell us about the constant solutions here.
Moreover you should see that we also get information about the solution that lies in here.
In particular we can look at a solution that hits the value pi/2.
There we know if we now increase t, we have to go to the right with the solution, because this is the direction of the arrow.
Indeed, this is the direction of all the arrows in the interval 0 to pi.
Therefore we can directly conclude that a solution inside this interval has to be monotonically increasing.
Moreover we also see that we can't exceed the value pi in the end, because pi is a stationary point.
This means if we go with t to infinity, we will approach this value pi.
So this is very nice. Without knowing the explicit solution, we can already say something about its behaviour.
So this is the big advantage of the directional field.
It helps you immediately with understanding solutions.
However maybe the whole thing is more interesting if we look at a higher dimensional example.
So I would say let's take a 2-dimensional one and a similar one to the last video.
So x_1 dot should be -x_2 and x_2 dot should be x_1.
So here our function v goes from R^2 into R^2.
Hence there the directional field can be visualized in a 2-dimensional plane.
Each point in the plane get's mapped to a vector which is given by (-x_2, x_1).
Therefore let's draw the plane and let's visualize this directional field.
Indeed, we see that this whole picture is not so complicated, because essentially it's just flipping the arrows.
Therefore the arrows also get longer if we get further away from the origin.
Of course now we could fill in the whole picture and what you should see is such a rotational field.
Now, if you don't want to draw it by hand, you can also use a computer.
For example Python will make this nice picture.
There please note, I have shortened the arrows such that you can see this nice flow here.
In other words, if we have a solution, it will go around the origin. Namely in the positive direction.
That simply because we now know, a solution has to follow the arrows.
Hence in our example here, the orbits will look like circles.
So the result is the same as before. We can already sketch solutions with the help of the directional fields.
Moreover we also see that we have a stationary solution, a stationary point in the picture.
Indeed, there is only one and it is the origin.
Ok, so in summary you see, the directional field helps us a lot to visualize solutions.
However some questions remain. What does it tell us about the existence and uniqueness of solutions?
And I tell you, these questions we will answer with the next videos.
So I really hope we meet again and have a nice day. Bye!