Hello and welcome back to ODEs.
The video series where we solve such equations and talk about the theory behind it.
Indeed in today's part 5 we will talk about solving strategies for autonomous equations.
More precisely we will have a first order, autonomous ODE in one dimension
and in fact it turns out that we have a general solving method for these equations.
However before we start with the details, I first want to thank all the nice people who support this channel on Steady, via PayPal or by other means
and you might already know, as a reward for supporting me you get PDF versions and quizzes for all the videos.
Just use the link in the description to find my web page and there you can download everything.
Ok, then without further ado let's start with the topic of today
by first discussing what we mean, when we talk about an initial value problem.
The name already tells you, we want to find some special solutions for a differential equation that satisfies some initial condition.
More concretely it means, first we have our first order differential equation
given as "x dot" is equal to v(x), where v should be a continuous function.
We already talked about that this is the general form of ODEs, like  we want to consider them.
However now we want to restrict that to one dimension.
In other words it's not a system, it's just one ODE
and to make it simpler, the function v should be defined on the whole real number line and a continuous function
and now the initial value is stated as: x at the position 0 is equal to a given value x_0.
So you see x_0 here is just a given real number
and now solving this initial value problem means that we want to find all solutions alpha
and such a solution could be defined on any interval (t_0, t_1), but it's important that at least the point 0,
the point in time 0 lies inside this interval.
Now, as a reminder solutions simply means: if you put the function alpha into the ODE, it solves it.
In other words alpha dot(t) is equal to v(alpha(t)) for all t in the interval t_0 to t_1.
However for solving the initial value problem we want more. We also want that alpha at the point 0 is equal to x_0.
This means that we fix the value of the solution at a given time point
and please note that this point is chosen as 0, is not a restriction at all.
Simply because we have an autonomous ODE, where the time is not explicitly in it.
This means 0 here is an arbitrary choice, but it is without lost of generality.
Ok and now the question is: "how can we solve such an ODE with a given initial condition?"
and indeed, there is a general solving strategy we now can develop.
However let's first do that in the case that v at our value x_0 is not 0.
In other words this value here should be strictly positive or strictly negative.
We take this case, because there we can simplify the ODE by dividing by v(x).
Hence the ODE now looks like that. x dot divided by v(x) is equal to 1.
Please note, because v is a continuous function this whole thing here makes sense in the neighbourhood around x_0.
This means that the function v could have 0 and it would make problems here. However in some sense they are far off, of x_0.
Therefore only around x_0 we consider the ODE in this form.
Therefore now we know: any solution alpha here with the condition that 0 is in the domain and alpha(0) = x_0 fulfills the following
By definition we have alpha dot(s) divided by v(s) is equal to 1
and you already see, we use s as the independent variable here, because we want to use t for something else later.
Therefore to make this precise we would say this equation holds for all s in the given interval
and now you might already guess. In order to solve this equation now, we will integrate on both sides
and namely we will simply integrate  from the given point 0 to a given point t.
Hence on the right-hand side it simply means that we get out t.
We integrate a constant from 0 to t. So the result would be t
and now please note, that holds for all possible t and you can also go backwards to the original equation.
So you would say this is simply differentiating and then you get the result with the fundamental theorem of calculus.
Indeed, this is a very important result that we need to solve ODEs
and if you don't know it, please check out my real analysis series, where we also prove it.
Moreover in real analysis we also learn how to deal with integrals.
For example we know we can use the substitution rule to solve such an integral here
and in fact this will be exactly our next step here
and there we should immediately see that it helps to introduce a new variable x for alpha(s)
and now by knowing the substitution rule, you know informally that we can write dx = alpha dot(s) ds
and then these 2 things here are exactly the 2 things we will substitute here inside the integral.
In other words we have the integral of 1 divided by v(x)
and then most importantly don't forget the boundaries. Now we integrate from alpha(0) to alpha(t).
However we already know alpha(0) is equal to our initial value x_0.
Therefore let's immediately pull that in instead of alpha(0) we now write x_0.
Moreover the right-hand side is not changed at all. We still have that this integral is equal to t for all t.
Ok and with that we see in order to solve our original ODE we have to find antiderivatives of the function 1 divided by v.
So again we recognize that the fundamental theorem of calculus goes in here,
because from that we can conclude that an integral can be written with antiderivatives.
More precisely we have the antiderivative at the upper limit, alpha(t) - the antiderivative at the lower limit
and in this case we already know this is simply x_0.
So there we see we have our new equation here and please don't forget. Capital F should be an antiderivative of the function 1/v.
This means that this procedure here only works if we are able to find an antiderivative of the function 1/v.
However in the case that we are able to do that, the ODE is almost solved
and maybe in order to see that, let's call F(x_0) just c. So it's just any constant here in this equation.
Therefore in our next step let's put this constant to the right-hand side
and then we see the solution we search for, alpha(t), is almost on the left-hand side.
In fact we just have to find the inverse of F to isolate alpha(t)
and there I can already tell you this is always possible by our assumption around our value x_0.
In other words locally we don't have a problem finding an inverse function of F
and in conclusion that is all we need for solving our ODE.
So on the right we simply have F inverse of t minus our constant c.
So in summary we can say we find a solution of our ODE by doing that
and then we simply have to adjust the constant such that our initial value is also satisfied
and with that we have it. This is the whole procedure of solving an autonomous ODE of first order.
Now, of course the problem is that this looks theoretical. So I want to show you 2 examples and how we can apply this procedure
and there we will also see that you don't have to memorize the procedure from above.
You simply have to know what to do in the calculation.
Now let's say we have the ODE x dot is equal to lambda times x, with a positive lambda
and then for the initial condition we assume that x_0 is not 0,
because in this case we can use our procedure from above.
Ok and in this point I want to show you an informal step that helps you to memorize the procedure from above.
So we rewrite the derivative x dot as dx/dt and then we informally multiply with dt.
It seems strange, but it brings us to the correct form, we have already justified above.
So the idea is to bring everything with x to the left-hand side and everything with t to the right-hand side.
In other words we have lambda times dt on the right-hand side now
and then we simply write an integral sign on both sides,
because then the separated dx and dt makes sense again
and then you should see on the left this is just a short notation for the antiderivative of 1/v.
Of course not completely, because the constant we already put on the other side.
However of course this is not a problem, because we already know on the right-hand side we just have t with a constant anyway.
Ok and now this equation says we have to write antiderivatives on the left-hand side and on the right hand side
and the antiderivative of 1/x is given by the natural logarithm of the absolute value of x
and on the right hand side we just have lambda as t, as we already know it.
However please don't forget, before there was a constant involved, because of the value of the antiderivative at x_0.
In fact different antiderivatives only differ by an additive constant.
This means we can just deal with that fact by adding a constant here in the equation.
I call it capital C and the idea as before is that we find the correct constant such that our initial value is satisfied.
So that's what you should see. It does not matter if we use this -c here or this +C here.
It's all the same. We just have to find the correct constant in the end
and usually we just shift that problem to the end of the whole calculation.
Ok and then you already know in the next step we have to apply the inverse function of the natural logarithm here
and there you should know this is given by the exponential function.
So we have e to the power lambda times t, times e to the power of constant C
and of course this x in the left-hand side here should now be our solution alpha(t).
So in order to make that clear now we should also use this notation
and then you see the only thing that remains is that we have an absolute value here.
Which means either we have +the right-hand side or -the right-hand side
and with these 2 cases we have solved our initial value problem.
So please note, e of something is always positive.
So either we have a completely negative solution or a function that is always positive
and now by putting in t is equal to 0 to find our x_0, we also get that this constant in front should be x_0.
In other words the solution is then very short. It's simply x_0 times exponential function of lambda times t.
Now, this whole thing here is a standard, but also a very important example
and you see, now we have found all the solutions in this form.
So for this example we can also say something about the uniqueness of solutions.
So this is already very good, but of course in general we will talk about this issue later.
First here I want to show you another example. Namely x dot is equal to x squared
and as before our initial condition is given as x_0 not equal to 0
and now as we have learned before we can do exactly the same steps as in the example above.
Indeed, we already know this whole separation idea gives us the correct form in the end.
So on the left we have dx/x^2 and on the right we just have dt
and now as before we write an integral to get antiderivatives into the game.
So the antiderivative on the left hand side is just -1/x and on the right-hand side it's just t as always.
However as before, please don't forget to add a constant, because this is needed to actually solve our initial value problem
or to put it in other words we want to find a general form of the solution and now just 1 particular solution.
Therefore please in this step never forget the constant!
Ok and now as before in order to make it consistent with our notation, let's use alpha(t) now instead of just x
and then in the next step we just have to take the inverse here, to get alpha(t) on the left-hand side alone.
Now this is not hard to see. How solution alpha(t) is -1/(t+C).
So this is the general form of the solution and now we just have to find what the constant C is, in order to satisfy our initial value.
So this is no problem at all. We simply put in 0, into our form here
and then we see we have -1/C
and now we know by our initial value problem that this should be equal to x_0.
Hence we have an equation that we can solve for C
and this is not a problem at all. C is simply given by -1/x_0
and that's exactly the thing we have to put into our general form here
and then indeed, we can state the solution of our initial value problem here.
So it's alpha(t) is equal to -1/(t+(-1/x_0)
and now of course we can simplify that by expanding the fraction.
There we have x_0/(1-x_0 times t)
and there you see this is the solution. We have solved our initial value problem.
Ok and with that we have seen some nice examples and I would say in the next video let's go deeper into the theory again.
So I really hope that I see you there and have a nice day. Bye!