Hello and welcome back to ODEs.
The video series where we talk about the theory of these equations and how to solve them.
Indeed in today's part 6 we will talk about the very important solving method called the separation of variables.
It tells us that we can solve a non-autonomous ODE, if we can separate the two variables
and it turns out that the whole procedure is very similar to the method of the last video.
However before we start
I really want to thank all the nice people who support this channel on Steady, here on YouTube, via PayPal or by other means
and please don't forget to download the PDF version and the quiz for this video with the link in the description.
Ok, then I would say let's immediately start by considering a non-autonomous ODE.
So you already know we consider explicit forms.
So we can write this ODE as x dot is equal to a function w, that has two variables as its input.
The one is the time variable t and the other one our function x
and now you know, if t is actually involved in this function w, then we speak of a non-autonomous ODE
and now the question for this method of today is: "can we separate both variables on the right-hand side?"
Now, what this question actually means I can immediately show you with an example.
Let's say we have x dot is equal to t^3 times the function x^2
Then in this case we have the separation of variables,
because we have a product where in one factor there are only t's and in the other factor there are only x's.
Of course this is not always possible, but if it is, we can solve this one-dimensional ODE
and the method we have for that we simply call separation of variables
and now you already know it's applicable if the ODE can be written as x dot is equal to g(t) times a function h(x)
and as you might recall from the last video we can state an ODE as an initial value problem.
This means that we search for solutions that satisfy a given value.
For example we could say at the point t_0 the solution should have the value x_0.
So now we actually choose a point in time t_0 and then we say it should have a given value at this point
and now please recall from the last video. This is exactly what we call an initial value problem.
Last time we have discussed that for an autonomous ODE and now we take a non-autonomous ODE of exactly this form.
So two functions g and h are involved and both should be continuous
and now I can tell you we will do exactly the same steps as in the last video, just with one small addition.
First let's immediately go to the interesting solutions. Where h(x_0) is not 0.
Otherwise you should see, there is a 0 here on the right-hand side and a constant function will be a solution immediately.
In other words this is actually the fun case, where we have something to do
and indeed the first thing we can do is to bring h(x) to the other side.
We know in a neighbourhood of x_0 we can divide by h(x).
Ok, then let's see what happens if we have a solution of this ODE and let's call it alpha
and you know t_0 should lie in this domain of definition.
This is a requirement of the solution t_0 should be inside this interval.
Moreover alpha should solve the initial value condition. So alpha at t_0 should be equal to x_0.
In other words, here we can just write alpha instead of x in the ODE.
However instead of t I now want to write s. Simply because we want to do an integration again.
In other words the fundamental theorem of calculus comes into the game again.
This means here we just integrate on both sides
and indeed now we will integrate from t_0 to t.
This makes sense because t_0 was our fixed point in time and t is just an arbitrary point
and now you already know on the left-hand side here we can do a nice substitution.
Then the whole thing looks much easier, because we just have to integrate the function 1/h
and please don't forget the boundaries are now x_0 and alpha(t)
and then on the right-hand side of course nothing changes, but we see on both sides we need antiderivatives to solve the thing.
So let's use capital F for the antiderivative of 1/h. So for the one on the left-hand side and capital G for the one right-hand side
and at this point let's say it again. There the fundamental theorem of calculus is at work again
and indeed for this theorem it does not matter which antiderivative we choose, because they only differ by an additive constant
and in fact this helps us, because we can put these 2 constants here and there into a single one.
In other words we simply write F is equal to G + a constant c.
So in this equation here c could be any real number
and with that you see we have solved the problem. We simply have to take the inverse of F now
because then we have alpha of t on the left-hand side.
So maybe it looks a little bit complicated,
but what you should recognize is that the whole procedure here gives us the solution alpha(t)
and that's all. This is the method of separating variables.
However as I have told you in the last video, you don't have to memorize this formula,
because you just have to know what to do in an example
and that's exactly what I want to show you now.
So let's consider a very standard ODE. x dot is equal to x.
However now the factor in front of x should depend on t
and maybe let's look in the case that we have 1/3 times t^3
and moreover let's also write our initial value condition as x(0) is equal to x_0.
Ok and now you already know what you should do here is to rewrite x_0 as dx/dt.
We do that, because it helps separating the variables,
because now we can just informally multiply dt to the right-hand side
and moreover we can also bring x to the left-hand side by dividing by x.
So then it looks strange like that, but then we can just integrate on both sides
and now you know this is just a short notation for the antiderivatives we have discussed before.
So indeed everything is correct here and we can just use an antiderivative on the left-hand side and one on the right-hand side
and there you should know, we have the natural logarithm of the absolute value of x on the left-hand side
and 1/12 times t^4 on the right-hand side and please NEVER forget to add the constant in this step here
and moreover at this point you should see this is definitely correct, because it's exactly this formula here in a general case.
However what I want to tell you here is that you don't need to remember this formula at all,
because you just need to remember these calculation steps.
I think that's much easier, because it's a natural calculation anyway.
Ok, then in the next step let's use the inverse function of the natural logarithm. Which is the exponential function
and moreover let's also write alpha(t) instead of x to denote our solution
and then we see this exponential function here is the absolute value of our solution.
Hence in the last step here we just have to satisfy the initial value condition.
In other words we have to find the correct value of our constant c.
So we do that and then it turns out that we have the exponential function with the factor x_0 in front of it
and there we have it. This is the solution of the initial value problem given here
and you see we have done the separation of variables exactly in this step here.
Ok now in order to close this video, let's look at another example.
Now, let's take x dot is equal to sin(t) times e^x.
So in fact it's more complicated than before, but we also recognize that the 2 variables are separated.
In other words we should be able to do our informal step here again.
So we have dx divided by e^x is equal to sin(t) dt
and then you already know we write the integration symbols and go to the antiderivatives.
So on the left-hand side we have -e to the power -x
and on the right-hand side we have -cos(t)
and again please don't forget to add our constant c here
and then in the next step we just have to find the inverses again to find our solution x
or to say it in better terms: to find our solution alpha(t)
and for that we get - the natural logarithm of cos(t) - our constant c
and there I can tell you. Sometimes it's helpful to change the constant by a factor.
So in other words you simply introduce a new constant.
So we just change the name and then we don't have this annoying - sign there.
This is helpful, because now we want to find the correct constant in order to fulfill our initial value condition.
So we put in 0 in the left-hand side and this should be equal to x_0
and now we simply solve this equation for c tilde.
Now, since the cos(0) is 1 we immediately have the solution here.
Namely, c tilde is given as an exponential function.
More precisely it's e to the power -x_0 and then we have to subtract the cos(0).
Ok and then you see, we put that in and then the whole initial value problem is solved
and with that you now know the method of separating variables to solve an ODE
and in the next video I will show you how you can solve so called linear ODEs.
These are also very common and therefore it's very important to know how to solve them
and with that I really hope that I see you in the next video. Have a nice day and bye bye!